<chapter>
	<chapterinfo>
		<keywordset>
			<keyword>darktable</keyword>
			<keyword>overview</keyword>
			<keyword>application</keyword>
		</keywordset>
	</chapterinfo>
	<title>Overview</title>
	<para>Darktable is an application to manage and develop your digital images.</para>
	<para>It is fully non-destructive and works on a 32 bit floating point format per channel. 
			Most of the actions on the pixelpipe are done in CIELab.</para>

	<sect1 status="final"><title>Preferences</title>
		<para> A recently introduced button located at the upper panel allows you to define various parameters.
		</para>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 status="final"><title>User interface</title>
		<informaltable frame="none"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
					<colspec colwidth='100%'/>
					<colspec colwidth='5cm'/>
					<tbody>
						<row>						
							<entry>This section describes the layout of the user interface. You can change Darktable contrast by using <emphasis>f7</emphasis> and  <emphasis>f8</emphasis>.
							</entry>
							<entry>
								<!--<graphic fileref="images/lighttable_thumb.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />-->
							</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</informaltable>
		
		<sect2 status="final"><title>Views</title>
			<para>Darktable consists of several views also mentioned as modes. For the time being, there are three available views as described 
				in this section. The current view is identified by the label at the top of the right panel.
				Some key accelerators, allowing to access the different views, are described in the table below:
				<informaltable frame="none"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
						<colspec colwidth='3cm'/>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry><emphasis>l</emphasis></entry>
								<entry>switches to lighttable view</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry><emphasis>d</emphasis></entry><entry>switches to darkroom view</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry><emphasis>t</emphasis></entry><entry>switches to camera tethering view</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup></informaltable>
			</para>
			<sect3 status="final"><title>Lighttable</title>
				<para>The lighttable view is where you manage your images and filmrolls; it's in that view that you rate, add tags, add colorlabels, export images among other
					actions.
				</para>
			</sect3>
			<sect3 status="final"><title>Darkroom</title>
				<para>In the darkroom view you develop a specific image using the available modules.
				</para>
			</sect3>
			<sect3 status="final"><title>Tethering</title>
				<para>This view is where you do camera tethering.
				</para>
			</sect3>
		</sect2>		
		
		<sect2 status="final"><title>Filmstrip</title>
			<para>The filmstrip shows the same images as lighttable with respect to filter and sort orders and are turned on/off with key accelerator <emphasis>ctrl-f</emphasis>.
			  You can navigate along the filmstrip by wheel scrolling.
				The filmstrip allows you to interact with images when you are not in lighttable mode. For example you can, while being in darkroom mode and developing an image, 
				switch to another image to develop by double clicking the thumb in the filmstrip.
			</para>
			<graphic fileref="overview/images/filmstrip.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
			<para>The filmstrip also provides some actions to be performed on image under the mouse pointer and here follows a table of available key accelerators
				for specific actions.
				<informaltable frame="none"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
						<colspec colwidth='3cm'/>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry><emphasis>1 - 4</emphasis></entry>
								<entry>set the rating of the image; if an image has 1 star and you hit the <emphasis>1</emphasis> key the image will be unrated
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry><emphasis>F1 - F3</emphasis></entry><entry>set a color label for the image</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry><emphasis>ctrl-c</emphasis></entry><entry>copy the historystack of the image</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry><emphasis>ctrl-v</emphasis></entry><entry>apply the copied historystack onto the image</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup></informaltable>
			</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 status="final"><title>Darktable workflow</title>
		<sect2 status="draft"><title>Importing images</title>
			<para>To begin with Darktable, you first need to import images. You can either import
					from your filesystem or from your camera if supported.</para>
			<para>You can add a picture to filmroll by simply cliking again on "import filmroll", then selecting the folder matching your filmroll.
			Darktable will analyse its content, detect the images already imported and import only the new pictures.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 status="draft"><title>Importing from camera</title>
			<para></para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 status="draft"><title>Exporting images</title>
			<para></para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
</chapter>
