<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>

<chapter id="overview chapter">
	<chapterinfo>
		<keywordset>
			<keyword>darktable</keyword>
			<keyword>overview</keyword>
			<keyword>application</keyword>
		</keywordset>
	</chapterinfo>
	<title>Overview</title>

        <para>darktable is an open source photography workflow application and RAW developer. A virtual lighttable and darkroom for photographers.</para>
        <para>It manages your digital negatives in a database, lets you view them through a zoomable lighttable and enables you to develop raw images and enhance them.</para>

	<itemizedlist>
		<title>General Features</title>
		<listitem>
			<para>darktable runs on GNU/Linux / GNOME, Mac OS X / macports and Solaris 11 / GNOME.</para>
		</listitem>
                <listitem>
			<para>Fully non-destructive editing.</para>
                </listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>All darktable core functions operate on 4x32-bit floating point pixel buffers for high accuracy processing; preventing banding and color breaks.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>Heavy use of SSE instructions of your CPU for speedups.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>GPU acceleration via OpenCL (runtime detection and enabling).</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>Most of the actions on the pixelpipe are done in CIELab color space, which is much larger than the gamut of modern displays, printers or even human vision.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>Full color managed display with softproofing and gamut-check. Built-in ICC profile support for export: sRGB, Adobe RGB, XYZ and linear RGB.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>A collect module allows you to execute flexible database queries, search your images by tags, image rating (stars), color labels and many more. 
			Filtering and sorting your collections within the base query or simple tagging by related tags are useful tools in your every-day photo workflow.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>Import a variety of standard, raw and high dynamic range image formats (e.g. jpg, cr2, hdr, pfm, .. ).</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>darktable has a zero-latency fullscreen, zoomable user interface through multi-level software caches.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>Tethered shooting.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>The powerful export system supports Picasa webalbum, flickr upload, disk storage, 1:1 copy, email attachments and can 
			generate a simple html-based web gallery. darktable allows you to export to low dynamic range (JPEG, JPEG2000, PNG, TIFF), 16-bit (PPM, TIFF), 
			or linear high dynamic range (PFM, EXR) images.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>darktable uses both XMP sidecar files as well as its fast database for saving metadata and processing settings. All Exif data is 
			read and written using libexiv2.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>darktable comes with 50 image operation modules which cover everything from basic operations, tonal value changes, color 
                              manipulation, correction of common image defects to artistic effects.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>Many of darktables modules can be combined with blending operators for even more development options.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>A powerful blend mask feature gives you fine control on module's effect to different parts of an image steered by pixel values.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>Most modules can exist as multiple instances. Together with our blend mask feature you can let an operation have 
                              different effects on different parts of the image.</para>
		</listitem>


	</itemizedlist>
		
		
	<sect1 status="final" id="user interface"><title>User interface</title>
		<informaltable frame="none"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
					<colspec colwidth='6*'/>
					<colspec colwidth='4*'/>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry>This section describes the layout of the user interface. You can change darktable's contrast by using <emphasis>F7</emphasis> and <emphasis>F8</emphasis>
                                                               and darktable's lightness by using <emphasis>F9</emphasis> and <emphasis>F10</emphasis>.
							</entry>
							<entry>
								<graphic fileref="images/lighttable_view.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
							</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</informaltable>

		<sect2 status="final" id="views"><title>Views</title>
			<para>darktable consists of several views also mentioned as modes. For the time being, there are four available views as described
				in this section. The current view is identified by the label at the top of the right panel.
				Some key accelerators, allowing to access the different views, are described in the table below:
				<informaltable frame="none" width="60%"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
						<colspec colwidth='1*'/>
						<colspec colwidth='9*'/>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry><emphasis>l</emphasis></entry><entry>switches to lighttable view</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry><emphasis>d</emphasis></entry><entry>switches to darkroom view</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry><emphasis>t</emphasis></entry><entry>switches to camera tethering view</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry><emphasis>m</emphasis></entry><entry>switches to map view</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup></informaltable>
			</para>
			<sect3 status="final"><title>Lighttable</title>
				<para>The lighttable view is where you manage your images and filmrolls; it's in that view that you rate, add tags, add colorlabels, export images among other
					actions (see <xref linkend="lighttable chapter"/>).
				</para>
			</sect3>
			<sect3 status="final"><title>Darkroom</title>
				<para>In the darkroom view you develop a specific image using the available modules (see <xref linkend="darkroom chapter"/>).
				</para>
			</sect3>
			<sect3 status="final"><title>Tethering</title>
				<para>This view is where you do camera tethering, ie. connecting your camera to the computer and remotely capturing images that will be downloaded and shown on 
                                      your computer screen (see <xref linkend="tethering chapter"/>).
				</para>
			</sect3>
			<sect3 status="final"><title>Map</title>
				<para>This view shows images that are geo-tagged on a map and allows you to manually geo-tag new images (see <xref linkend="map chapter"/>).
				</para>
			</sect3>
               </sect2>
               <sect2 status="final" id="filmstrip overview"><title>Filmstrip</title>
			<para>The filmstrip shows the same images as lighttable with respect to filters and sort order; it is turned on/off with key accelerator <emphasis>ctrl-f</emphasis>.
		  	You can navigate along the filmstrip by wheel scrolling.
			The filmstrip allows you to interact with images when you are not in lighttable mode. For example you can, while being in darkroom mode and developing an image,
			switch to another image to develop by double clicking the thumb in the filmstrip. You can also rate the images as you do in lighttable, copy/paste history stack, etc.
			</para>
			<graphic fileref="overview/images/filmstrip.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
        	</sect2>

		<sect2 status="draft" id="preferences"><title>Preferences</title>
			<para>A button <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_preferences;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center" /> located at the upper panel allows you to define various parameters.
			</para>
			<para>The options are quite self-explaining. In case you need more information, just let your mouse hover a text label and/or entry box to display more information. 
                              Furthermore all configuration parameters are explained in a later chapter of this manual (<xref linkend="preferences chapter"/>).
			</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>


	<sect1 status="final" id="darktable basic workflow"><title>darktable basic workflow</title>
		<sect2 status ="draft"><title>Importing Images</title>
			<para>To begin with darktable, you first need to import images. You can either import
				from your filesystem or from your camera if supported.</para>

			<sect3 status="draft"><title>Importing images from filesystem</title>
				<para>In the left panel of lighttable view you will find the import module (<xref linkend="import"/>). Here you have the choice to import either a single 
                                      image or a folder, darktable will analyse its content, detect images that are already imported and only import new images.
				</para>
			</sect3>

			<sect3 status="draft"><title>Importing from camera</title>
				<para>Connect your camera to your system and if your distribution tries to automount it, select the option to abort the mount operation.
					Otherwise the camera will be locked and not accessible from within darktable.</para>
				<para>In the left panel of lighttable view you have the import pane. If you don't see your camera there, you need to hit the
					scan for devices button. Your camera will then appear in same pane with additional actions: import and tethering.</para>
			</sect3>
		</sect2>

		<sect2 status="draft" id="basic development steps"><title>Basic development steps</title>
			<sect3><title>Introduction</title>
				<para>This section will guide you through the basics about developing your image in darkroom view.
				</para>

				<para>To begin you need to open an image in darkroom mode which you will do by double clicking an image thumbnail on the lighttable,
					it's in the darkroom mode you do the actual adjustments for an image and you have an arsenal of modules at your hand to help you
					reach your goal.
				</para>

				<para>Each change you make on a module when developing your image is turned into a history stack item, the history is stored in a database
				      and in an XMP sidecar file for the specific image. Changes are stored automatically without the need to press a "save" button. 
                                      Therefore you can safely leave darkroom mode and darktable and come back later to continue your work.
				</para>

				<para>
					On the left panel in darkroom mode you have the history stack showing changes starting from bottom and building up with each change
					you have made to the image. You can select a point in this history to show how the image looked in that point for comparison of changes.
					The stack can be compressed and will discard changes done during the development but will make it optimized. When you think you are done
					and have a good feeling of what you have done, just compress the history stack.
				</para>

				<para>
					darktable ships with a bunch of modules and each of them is arranged into groups named module groups, these module groups are accessed
					via toggle buttons in the right panel just under the histogram.
					There are also two special module groups named active and favorites, where active will only show modules enabled in the history for the current image and
					favorites will only show modules selected as a favorite by you. This is done in the <emphasis>more modules</emphasis> dialog (<xref linkend="more modules"/>) 
                                        at the bottom of the right panel. Just click your favorite module until it gets a star displayed in front of the icon and you have chosen your favorite.
				</para>
			</sect3>

			<sect3 status="draft"><title>White balance</title>
				<para>Module <link linkend="whitebalance"><emphasis>white balance</emphasis></link> controls, well, the white balance of the image. It's always enabled and reads 
                                      its defaultvalues from metadata embedded in the image which will be set by your camera. The most common change here will be fine-tuning the 
                                      white balance and this is done using the temperature in slider.	Taking it down will make the color balance cooler and steering it up will
                                      make it warmer.
				</para>
			</sect3>

			<sect3 status="draft"><title>Exposure correction</title>
				<para>Module <link linkend="exposure"><emphasis>exposure</emphasis></link> might be the simplest module of them all, fine-tune your exposure and use the histogram 
                                      to guide you if you don't know what you are doing. You can also boost the black level by increasing the black but be careful, use small amount like 0.005 steps.
                                      If you feel lucky use the auto correction feature, this might fail for several technical reasons&nbsp;&hellip;
				</para>
				<para>You can also click-and-drag in the histogram to change exposure / blackpoint.
				</para>
			</sect3>

  	         	<sect3 status="draft"><title>Noise reduction</title>
           			<para>You have several options in darktable to reduce noise. You'll find them in the correct group. There is <link linkend="raw denoise"><emphasis>raw denoise</emphasis> 
                                      </link>, <link linkend="denoise bilateral"><emphasis>denoising based on bilateral filter</emphasis></link>, <link linkend="denoise non local means">
                                      <emphasis>non-local means</emphasis></link>, and <link linkend="equalizer"><emphasis>equalizer</emphasis></link> based on wavelets. 
                                      Most convenient to use is probably denoising based on non-local means, as it allows you to treat color and luminance noise separately.
                                </para>
			</sect3>

			<sect3 status="draft"><title>Fixing spots</title>
				<para>Sometimes you will need to remove spots caused by sensor dirt. Module <link linkend="spot removal"><emphasis>spot removal</emphasis></link> is at your
                                      hand and can also correct other disturbing elements like skin blemishes. If your camera has stuck
                                      pixels or tends to produce hotpixel at high iso values or longer exposure times, have look at module 
                                      <link linkend="hotpixels"><emphasis>hotpixels</emphasis></link> for an automatic correction.
				</para>
			</sect3>

			<sect3 status="draft"><title>Geometrical corrections</title>
				<para>Quite frequently you want to only show part of the captured scene in your image, e.g. to 
                                      take away some disturbing features close to the edge. In other cases the horizon in your image 
                                      maybe leveled or you observe some perspective distortions. All this can be corrected in 
                                      module <link linkend="crop and rotate"><emphasis>crop and rotate</emphasis></link>. If you need to correct typical flaws of a camera lens 
                                      like cushion distortion, transversal chromatic aberrations or vignetting there is a separate module in darktable called 
                                      <link linkend="lens correction"><emphasis>lens correction</emphasis></link>.
				</para>
			</sect3>

			<sect3 status="draft"><title>Bringing back detail</title>
				<para>Digital RAW images often contain more information than you can see at first sight. Especially 
                                      in the shadows of an image there are lots of details hidden. Module <link linkend="shadows and highlights">
                                      <emphasis>shadows and highlights</emphasis></link>
                                      helps to bring these shades back into tonal values where they contribute to the visual 
                                      impression. Structural details in fully blown-out highlights by nature of the digital sensor can not 
                                      be recovered. However, you can correct unfavorable color casts in these areas with module <link linkend="highlight reconstruction">
                                      <emphasis>highlight reconstruction</emphasis></link>.
				</para>
			</sect3>

			<sect3 status="draft"><title>Adjusting global contrast</title>
				<para>Almost each workflow will cover as one basic element the adjustment of 
                                      global contrast. You will want to control which of the available tonal ranges of your output 
                                      medium are represented in your image. Darktable offers several alternative modules to take 
                                      care of that. In one of them, module <link linkend="tonecurve"><emphasis>tonecurve</emphasis></link>, you adjust tonal values by constructing a 
                                      gradation curve. Module <link linkend="levels"><emphasis>levels</emphasis></link> offers a much simpler interface with just three 
                                      sliders. In addition there is module <link linkend="zone system"><emphasis>zone system</emphasis></link> which allows to control tonal values
                                      in certain zones, inspired by the work of Ansel Adams.
				</para>
			</sect3>

			<sect3 status="draft"><title>Enhancing local contrast</title>
				<para>Local contrast enhancement will emphasize detail and clarity in your image; carefully used it can give your 
                                      photograph the right pop. Darktable offers several modules for this task. Module <link linkend="local contrast">
                                      <emphasis>local contrast</emphasis></link> is 
                                      easy to handle with just a few parameters. A much more versatile but also more complex 
                                      technique is offered by module <link linkend="equalizer"><emphasis>equalizer</emphasis></link>. Have a look at equalizer's preset 
                                      to get a feeling for how it works. Equalizer is darktable's "Swiss Army Knife" for many adjustments where spatial dimension
                                      plays a role. 
				</para>
			</sect3>

			<sect3 status="draft"><title>Color adjustments</title>
				<para>darktable offers many modules to adjust colors in your image. A very straightforward technique is 
                                      implemented in module <link linkend="color correction"><emphasis>color correction</emphasis></link>. Use it to give your image an 
                                      overall tint or to adjust overall color saturation. Module <link linkend="color zones"><emphasis>color zones</emphasis></link> offers 
                                      a much finer control to adjust saturation or lightness 
                                      and even hue in user defined zones. Also darktable's <link linkend="tonecurve"><emphasis>tonecurve</emphasis></link> module - in addition to the 
                                      classical adjustment of tonal values - gives you fine control over the colors in your image. 
                                      Finally, if you intend to convert your image into black&amp;white, a good starting point with an 
                                      easy to use and intuitive user interface is offered by module <link linkend="monochrome"><emphasis>monochrome</emphasis></link>. Alternatively
                                      you might consider to use darktable's <link linkend="channel mixer"><emphasis>channel mixer</emphasis></link>.
				</para>
			</sect3>

			<sect3 status="draft"><title>Sharpening</title>
				<para>If you start your workflow from an RAW image, you will need to have your final output 
                                      sharpened. Module <link linkend="sharpen"><emphasis>sharpen</emphasis></link> can do this with the classical USM (unsharp mask) approach, well 
                                      known from more or less all image processing software around. Another very versatile way to 
                                      enhance edges in your image is offered by module <link linkend="highpass"><emphasis>highpass</emphasis></link> in combination with
                                      darktable's rich set of blending operators.
				</para>
			</sect3>


		</sect2>

		<sect2 status="draft" id="exporting images"><title>Exporting images</title>
			<para>Your changes to an image are not saved as in a regular image editor. darktable is a non destructive editor, which means all your changes are stored 
                              in a database and the original image is untouched and therefore you need to export your images to get an <quote>image</quote> file to distribute with 
                              your special processing.</para>
			<para>Images are exported from lighttable using the <emphasis>export selected</emphasis> dialog in the right panel (<xref linkend="export selected"/>). In general, 
                              export means: save my developed RAW image as a JPEG.</para>
			<para>The export is modularized into storage and format. darktable is shipping several storage modules such as save on disk, picasa and flickr webalbum and more.
			      Format modules are the actual image formats such as JPEG, PNG, TIFF, OpenEXR and more.
			</para>
			<para>Select images on your lighttable that you want to export, then choose your target storage and format to use and set the maximum width and height image restraint. 
                              This means that none of the images will be bigger than any of the width/height restraint. Leave the width and height restraint as zero if you want the original 
                              resolution and hit the export button.
			</para>

		</sect2>
	</sect1>

</chapter>
