<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>

<chapter status="final" id="overview_chapter">
	<chapterinfo>
		<keywordset>
			<keyword>darktable</keyword>
			<keyword>overview</keyword>
			<keyword>application</keyword>
		</keywordset>
	</chapterinfo>
	<title>Overview</title>

        <para>darktable is an open source photography workflow application and RAW developer, a virtual lighttable and darkroom for photographers.</para>
        <para>It manages your digital negatives in a database, lets you view them through a zoomable lighttable and enables you to develop raw images and enhance them.</para>

	<itemizedlist>
		<title>General Features</title>
		<listitem>
			<para>darktable runs on GNU/Linux / GNOME, Mac OS X / macports and Solaris 11 / GNOME.</para>
		</listitem>
                <listitem>
			<para>Fully non-destructive editing.</para>
                </listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>All darktable core functions operate on 4x32-bit floating point pixel buffers for high accuracy processing, preventing banding and color breaks.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>darktable makes heavy use of <emphasis>Streaming SIMD Extensions 2</emphasis> (SSE2) instructions of the CPU to speed up processing. In fact, darktable
                        will only run on a CPU that supports SSE2.</para>
        	</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>GPU acceleration via OpenCL (runtime detection and enabling).</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>Most image processing is done in CIELab color space, which is much larger than the gamut of modern displays, printers or even human vision.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>Full color managed display with softproofing and gamut-check. Built-in ICC profile support for export: sRGB, Adobe RGB, XYZ and linear RGB.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>A collect module allows you to execute flexible database queries, search your images by tags, image rating (stars), color labels and many more. 
			Filtering and sorting your collections within the base query or simple tagging by related tags are useful tools in your every-day photo workflow.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>Import a variety of standard, raw and high dynamic range image formats (e.g. JPG, CR2, OpenEXR, PFM, ...).</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>darktable has a zero-latency fullscreen, zoomable user interface through multi-level software caches.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>Tethered shooting.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>The powerful export system supports Picasa webalbum, flickr upload, disk storage, 1:1 copy, email attachments and can 
			generate a simple html-based web gallery. darktable allows you to export to low dynamic range (JPEG, JPEG2000, PNG, TIFF), 16-bit (PPM, TIFF), 
			or linear high dynamic range (PFM, EXR) images.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>darktable uses both XMP sidecar files as well as its fast database for saving metadata and processing settings. All Exif data is 
			read and written using libexiv2.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>darktable comes with 50 image operation modules which cover everything from basic operations, tonal value changes, color 
                              manipulation, correction of common image defects to artistic effects.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>Many darktable modules can be combined with blending operators for even more development options.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>A powerful mask feature gives you fine control on module's effect to different parts of an image. You can at your choice draw a mask using
                              various shapes or define a parametric mask based on pixel values.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>Most modules can exist as multiple instances. Together with the mask feature, you can let an operation have 
                              different effects on different parts of the image.</para>
		</listitem>
                <listitem><para>darktable introduces a highly efficient, yet simple <quote>single-click</quote> denoiser that always just works (tm). It's designed as a module where the 
                          denoising performance only depends on camera and ISO setting. A database of profiles contains parameters for over
                          100 popular camera models.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem><para>darktable comes with a versatile scripting interface for functionality enhancement using Lua as a scripting language.</para>
                </listitem>



	</itemizedlist>
		
		
	<sect1 status="final" id="user_interface"><title>User interface</title>
		<informaltable frame="none"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
					<colspec colwidth='6*'/>
					<colspec colwidth='4*'/>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry>
                                                               <para>This section describes the layout of the user interface.
                                                               </para>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								<graphic fileref="images/lighttable_view.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
							</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</informaltable>

		<sect2 status="final" id="views"><title>Views</title>
			<para>darktable consists of several views or modes. There are four available views as described
				in this section. You can switch between views by clicking the view name at the top of the right
                                panel - the active view is highlighted - or by using one of the key accelerators:
				<informaltable frame="none" width="60%"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
						<colspec colwidth='1*'/>
						<colspec colwidth='9*'/>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry><emphasis>l</emphasis></entry><entry>switches to lighttable</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry><emphasis>d</emphasis></entry><entry>switches to darkroom</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry><emphasis>t</emphasis></entry><entry>switches to camera tethering</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry><emphasis>m</emphasis></entry><entry>switches to map</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup></informaltable>
			</para>
			<sect3 status="final"><title>Lighttable</title>
				<para>The lighttable view is where images and film rolls are managed. It's also where you rate images, add tags and  
                                      colorlabels, and export images among other actions (see <xref linkend="lighttable_chapter"/>).
				</para>
			</sect3>
			<sect3 status="final"><title>Darkroom</title>
				<para>In the darkroom view you develop a single image using the available modules (see <xref linkend="darkroom_chapter"/>).
				</para>
			</sect3>
			<sect3 status="final"><title>Tethering</title>
				<para>This view is for shooting with the camera connected to the computer and remotely capturing images that will be downloaded and shown on 
                                      computer screen (see <xref linkend="tethering_chapter"/>).
				</para>
			</sect3>
			<sect3 status="final"><title>Map</title>
				<para>This view shows images with geo-tag data on a map and allows manually geo-tagging new images (see <xref linkend="map_chapter"/>).
				</para>
			</sect3>
               </sect2>
               <sect2 status="final" id="screen_layout"><title>Screen layout</title>
                        <para>The general screen layout of all views is similar. There is a center area which contains most of the relevant information of that view. Then there are panels left,
                        right, top and bottom to the center area. The left panel typically has an informational purpose. The right panel offers functions to modify an image. The top 
                        and bottom panel give access to several settings and shortcuts. Each of the panels can be collapsed or expanded by pressing a triangle like
                        <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_general_collapse;" scalefit="1" width="2%"/>, located close to the panel.
                        </para>
                        <para>By pressing the <emphasis>TAB</emphasis> key all panels get collapsed, allowing the center area to occupy all available space. Pressing <emphasis>TAB</emphasis>
                        again brings you back to the previous view.
                        </para>
                        <para>Fullscreen view can be toggled by pressing <emphasis>F11</emphasis>.
                        </para>
                        <para>darktable's contrast can be changed by using <emphasis>F7</emphasis> and <emphasis>F8</emphasis>
                        and darktable's lightness by using <emphasis>F9</emphasis> and <emphasis>F10</emphasis>.
                        </para>
               </sect2>
               <sect2 status="final" id="filmstrip_overview"><title>Filmstrip</title>
			<para>The filmstrip along the bottom shows the same images as lighttable, with respect to filters and sort order. It is turned on/off with key accelerator <emphasis>ctrl-f</emphasis>.
		  	You can navigate along the filmstrip by scrolling with the mouse wheel.
			The filmstrip allows you to interact with images while you are not in lighttable mode. For example, you can, while developing an image in darkroom mode,
			switch to another image to develop, by double clicking the thumbnail in the filmstrip. You can also rate the images as you do in lighttable, copy/paste history stack, etc.
			</para>
                        <para>
			   <graphic fileref="overview/images/filmstrip.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
                        </para>
        	</sect2>

		<sect2 status="final" id="preferences"><title>Preferences</title>
			<para>A button <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_preferences;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center" /> located in the upper panel allows you to define various parameters
                        which control darktable's behavior.
			</para>
			<para>The options are fairly self-explanatory. If you need more information, hover the mouse cursor over the text label or entry box, to display a popup tool-tip. 
                              All configuration parameters are explained in <xref linkend="preferences_chapter"/>.
			</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>


	<sect1 status="final" id="darktable_basic_workflow"><title>darktable basic workflow</title>
                <indexterm>
                     <primary>basic workflow</primary>
                </indexterm>
                <para>This section tries to give a first rough overview of a typical darktable workflow. Novice users may take this as a starting point. We describe 
                      how to get an image into darktable, which basic steps are typically part of a raw development workflow, and how to export the final result.</para>
		<sect2 status ="final"><title>Importing images</title>
			<para>To begin with darktable, you first need to import images. The import module is in the left pane of the lighttable
                                view (<xref linkend="import"/>). You can either import
				from the filesystem or, if darktable supports your camera model, directly from camera.</para>

			<sect3 status="final"><title>Importing images from filesystem</title>
				<para>When importing from disk, you can import either a single 
                                      image or a folder. darktable will analyse its content, detect images that are already imported and only import new images.
				</para>
			</sect3>

			<sect3 status="final"><title>Importing from camera</title>
				<para>Connect your camera to your system. If your distribution tries to automount it, select the option to abort the mount operation.
					Otherwise the camera will be locked and not accessible from within darktable. If you don't see your camera in the import
                                        pane, hit the <quote>scan for devices</quote> button. Your camera will then appear in the same pane with additional choices: 
                                        <emphasis>import</emphasis> and <emphasis>tethering</emphasis>.</para>
			</sect3>
		</sect2>

		<sect2 status="final" id="basic_development_steps"><title>Basic development steps</title>
			<sect3><title>Introduction</title>
				<para>This section will guide you through the basics of developing an image in the darkroom view.
				</para>

				<para>To begin, open an image in darkroom mode by double clicking an image thumbnail on the lighttable.
					The darkroom mode is where the actual adjustments for an image are made, where an arsenal of modules are at hand to help you
					reach your goal.
				</para>

				<para>Each change made on a module while developing an image is turned into a <link linkend="history"><emphasis>history stack</emphasis></link> item.
                                      The history is stored in a database and in an XMP sidecar file for the specific image.</para>

                                <para>All changes are stored automatically. You can safely leave darkroom mode or quit darktable at any time and come back later to continue your work.
                                      That said darktable does not need a <quote>save</quote> button and it does not have one.
                                      <indexterm>
                                           <primary>save button</primary>
                                      </indexterm>
				</para>

				<para>
					On the left panel in darkroom mode is the <link linkend="history"><emphasis>history stack</emphasis></link>, showing changes 
                                        starting from bottom, and building up with each change
					made to the image. You can select a point in this history to show how the image looked at that point, for comparison of changes.
					The stack can be compressed: it will be optimized and redundant changes will be discarded. When you think you are done
					and are happy with what you have done, just compress the history stack.
				</para>

				<para>
					darktable ships with a number of modules, arranged into groups. These module groups are accessed
					via toggle buttons in the right panel, just under the histogram.
					There are also two special module groups named <quote>active</quote> and <quote>favorites</quote>, which only show modules enabled in 
                                        the history for the current image, and modules selected as a favorite, respectively. Marking a module as a favorite 
                                        is done in the <emphasis>more modules</emphasis> 
                                        dialog (<xref linkend="more_modules"/>), 
                                        at the bottom of the right panel, by clicking a module until a star is displayed in front of the icon.
				</para>
			</sect3>

			<sect3 status="final"><title>White balance</title>
				<para>The <link linkend="whitebalance"><emphasis>white balance</emphasis></link> module controls the white balance or color temperature of the image. It's always 
                                      enabled and reads 
                                      its default values from camera metadata embedded in the image. The most common change is fine-tuning the 
                                      white balance, which is done using the <quote>temperature</quote> slider. Moving this slider left will make the color balance cooler, and moving
                                      it right will make it warmer.
				</para>
			</sect3>

			<sect3 status="final"><title>Exposure correction</title>
				<para>The <link linkend="exposure"><emphasis>exposure</emphasis></link> module is probably the most basic module of them all. Exposure is fine-tuned either by
                                      using the slider, or by dragging with the mouse in the <link linkend="histogram"><emphasis>histogram</emphasis></link>. You can 
                                      also boost the black level to enhance contrast; but be careful: use small amounts, like steps of 0.005. There is also an auto-correct feature.
				</para>
			</sect3>

  	         	<sect3 status="final"><title>Noise reduction</title>
           			<para>The best starting point for noise reduction is <link linkend="denoise_profiled"><emphasis>profiled denoise</emphasis></link>. This module offers 
                                      an almost <quote>single-click</quote> solution to fight noise. From a user perspective the effect only depends on camera type and ISO value, both 
                                      derived from EXIF data. All other settings are taken from
                                      a database of noise profiles that the darktable team has collected - now covering already over 70 popular camera models.
                                      In addition you have several other options in darktable to reduce noise. There is <link linkend="raw_denoise"><emphasis>raw denoise</emphasis></link>, 
                                      <link linkend="denoise_bilateral"><emphasis>denoising based on bilateral filter</emphasis></link>, <link linkend="denoise_non_local_means">
                                      <emphasis>denoising based on non-local means</emphasis></link>, and <link linkend="equalizer"><emphasis>equalizer</emphasis></link>, which is based on wavelets. 
                                      If your camera is not yet supported by <link linkend="denoise_profiled"><emphasis>profiled denoise</emphasis></link>,
                                      <link linkend="denoise_non_local_means"><emphasis>denoising based on non-local means</emphasis></link> is probably the most convenient, as it allows you 
                                      to treat color and luminance noise separately.
                                </para>
			</sect3>

			<sect3 status="final"><title>Fixing spots</title>
				<para>Sometimes you will need to remove spots caused by sensor dirt. The <link linkend="spot_removal"><emphasis>spot removal</emphasis></link> 
                                      module is at hand and can also correct other disturbing elements like skin blemishes. If your camera has stuck
                                      pixels or tends to produce hot pixels at high ISO values, or longer exposure times, have a look at the
                                      <link linkend="hotpixels"><emphasis>hot pixels</emphasis></link> module for automatic correction.
				</para>
			</sect3>

			<sect3 status="final"><title>Geometrical corrections</title>
				<para>Quite frequently you want to only show part of the captured scene in your image, e.g. to 
                                      take away some disturbing feature close to the frame. In other cases, the horizon in the image 
                                      may need levelling, or there are perspective distortions. All this can be corrected in 
                                      the <link linkend="crop_and_rotate"><emphasis>crop and rotate</emphasis></link> module. If you need to correct typical camera lens flaws
                                      like cushion distortion, transversal chromatic aberrations or vignetting, there is a 
                                      <link linkend="lens_correction"><emphasis>lens correction</emphasis></link> module.
				</para>
			</sect3>

			<sect3 status="final"><title>Bringing back detail</title>
				<para>Digital RAW images often contain more information than you can see at first sight. Especially 
                                      in the shadows of an image, there are lots of hidden details. The <link linkend="shadows_and_highlights"><emphasis>shadows and highlights</emphasis></link>
                                      module helps bring these details back into visible tonal values. Structural details in fully blown-out highlights, by nature of the digital sensor, can not 
                                      be recovered. However, you can correct unfavorable color casts in these areas with the 
                                      <link linkend="highlight_reconstruction"><emphasis>highlight reconstruction</emphasis></link> module.
				</para>
			</sect3>

			<sect3 status="final"><title>Adjusting tonal values</title>
				<para>Almost each workflow covers as one basic element the adjustment of 
                                      tonal values. You will want to control how the image's tonal values cover the available range of your output 
                                      medium by adjusting global contrast and the overall brightness of your image. darktable offers several alternative modules to take 
                                      care of that. The most basic one is the <link linkend="contrast_brightness_saturation"><emphasis>contrast brightness saturation</emphasis></link> module.
                                      In the <link linkend="tone_curve"><emphasis>tone curve</emphasis></link> module, tonal values are adjusted by constructing a 
                                      gradient curve. The <link linkend="levels"><emphasis>levels</emphasis></link> module offers a concise interface, with three 
                                      markers in a histogram. In addition, there is a <link linkend="zone_system"><emphasis>zone system</emphasis></link> module which allows control over tonal values
                                      by zones, inspired by the work of Ansel Adams.
				</para>
			</sect3>

			<sect3 status="final"><title>Enhancing local contrast</title>
				<para>Local contrast enhancement can emphasize detail and clarity in your image. Carefully used, it can give your 
                                      photograph the right pop. darktable offers several modules for this task. 
                                      The <link linkend="local_contrast"><emphasis>local contrast</emphasis></link> module is 
                                      easy to handle, with just a few parameters. A much more versatile, but also more complex 
                                      technique, is offered by the <link linkend="equalizer"><emphasis>equalizer</emphasis></link> module. Have a look at its presets,
                                      to get a feeling for how it works. Equalizer is darktable's "Swiss Army Knife" for many adjustments where spatial dimension
                                      plays a role. 
				</para>
			</sect3>

			<sect3 status="final"><title>Color adjustments</title>
				<para>darktable offers many modules for adjusting colors in an image. A very straightforward technique is 
                                      implemented in the <link linkend="color_correction"><emphasis>color correction</emphasis></link> module. Use it to give an image an 
                                      overall tint or to adjust overall color saturation. The <link linkend="color_zones"><emphasis>color zones</emphasis></link> module offers 
                                      a much finer control to adjust saturation, or lightness, 
                                      and even hue, in user defined zones. darktable's <link linkend="tone_curve"><emphasis>tone curve</emphasis></link> module - in addition to the 
                                      classical adjustment of tonal values - gives you fine control over the colors in an image. 
                                      Finally, if you intend to convert an image into black &amp; white, a good starting point, with an 
                                      easy to use and intuitive user interface, is offered by the <link linkend="monochrome"><emphasis>monochrome</emphasis></link> module. Alternatively,
                                      you might consider using darktable's <link linkend="channel_mixer"><emphasis>channel mixer</emphasis></link>.
				</para>
			</sect3>

			<sect3 status="final"><title>Sharpening</title>
				<para>If you start your workflow from a RAW image, you will need to have your final output 
                                      sharpened. The <link linkend="sharpen"><emphasis>sharpen</emphasis></link> module can do this with the classical USM (unsharp mask) approach,  
                                      available in most image processing software. Another very versatile way to 
                                      enhance edges in an image is offered by the <link linkend="highpass"><emphasis>highpass</emphasis></link> module, in combination with
                                      darktable's rich set of blending operators.
				</para>
			</sect3>

			<sect3 status="draft"><title>Artistic effects</title>
                                <para>darktable comes with a rich set of artistic effect modules. To name just a few: with the 
                                      <link linkend="watermark"><emphasis>watermark</emphasis></link> module you
                                      add an individual watermark to your image. The <link linkend="grain"><emphasis>grain</emphasis></link> 
                                      module simulates the typical noise of classical analogue footage. Use the
                                      <link linkend="color_mapping"><emphasis>color mapping</emphasis></link> module to transfer the look and feel 
                                      of one color image onto another. darktable's <link linkend="low_light"><emphasis>low light</emphasis></link> module allows to 
                                      simulate human vision to make lowlight pictures look closer to reality. 
                                      The <link linkend="graduated_density"><emphasis>graduated density</emphasis></link> filter adds a neutral
                                      or colored gradient to your image for exposure and color correction.
                                </para>
                        </sect3>

		</sect2>

		<sect2 status="final" id="exporting_images"><title>Exporting images</title>
			<para>Changes to an image are not saved as in a regular image editor. darktable is a non-destructive editor, which means all changes are stored 
                              in a database, and the original image is untouched. Therefore, you need to export images to bake the processing options into an output
                              file that can be distributed outside of darktable.</para>
			<para>Images are exported from the lighttable view, using the <emphasis>export selected</emphasis> dialog in the right panel (<xref linkend="export_selected"/>). In general, 
                              export means: save my developed RAW image as a JPEG.</para>
			<para>The export is modularized into <emphasis>storage</emphasis> and <emphasis>format</emphasis>. darktable ships with several storage modules such as 
                              <emphasis>save on disk</emphasis>, <emphasis>picasa</emphasis> and <emphasis>flickr webalbum</emphasis> and more.
			      Format modules are the actual image formats such as JPEG, PNG, TIFF, OpenEXR and more.
			</para>
			<para>Select images on the lighttable, choose the target storage and format, and set the maximum width and height image restraints. 
                              This means that none of the images will be bigger than any of the width/height restraints and hit the export button. Leave the width and height restraints at zero, 
                              if you want the original resolution.
                        </para>

		</sect2>
	</sect1>

</chapter>
