<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<chapter status="final" id="overview_chapter">

  <chapterinfo>
    <keywordset>
      <keyword>darktable</keyword>
      <keyword>overview</keyword>
      <keyword>application</keyword>
    </keywordset>
  </chapterinfo>

  <title>Overview</title>

  <para>
    darktable is an open source photography workflow application and RAW developer, a virtual
    lighttable and darkroom for photographers.
  </para>

  <para>
    It manages your digital negatives in a database, lets you view them through a zoomable
    lighttable and enables you to develop raw images and enhance them.
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>

    <title>General Features</title>

    <listitem><para>
      darktable runs on GNU/Linux / GTK3, Mac OS X / macports and Solaris 11 / GTK3.
    </para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>
      Fully non-destructive editing.
    </para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>
      All darktable core functions operate on 4x32-bit floating point pixel buffers for high
      accuracy processing, preventing banding and color breaks.
    </para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>
      darktable makes heavy use of <emphasis>Streaming SIMD Extensions 2</emphasis> (SSE2)
      instructions of the CPU to speed up processing. In fact, darktable will only run on a CPU
      that supports SSE2.
    </para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>
      GPU acceleration via OpenCL (runtime detection and enabling).
    </para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>
      Most image processing is done in CIELab color space, which is much larger than the gamut
      of modern displays, printers or even human vision.
    </para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>
      Full color managed display with softproofing and gamut-check. Built-in ICC profile support
      for export: sRGB, Adobe RGB, XYZ and linear RGB.
    </para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>
      A collect module allows you to execute flexible database queries, search your images by
      tags, image rating (stars), color labels and many more. Filtering and sorting your
      collections within the base query or simple tagging by related tags are useful tools in
      your every-day photo workflow.
    </para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>
      Import a variety of standard, raw and high dynamic range image formats (e.g. JPG, CR2,
      OpenEXR, PFM, ...).
    </para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>
      darktable has a zero-latency fullscreen, zoomable user interface through multi-level
      software caches.
    </para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>
      Tethered shooting.
    </para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>
      The powerful export system supports Picasa webalbum, flickr upload, disk storage, 1:1
      copy, email attachments and can generate a simple html-based web gallery. darktable allows
      you to export to low dynamic range (JPEG, JPEG2000, PNG, TIFF, PDF), 16-bit (PPM, TIFF),
      or linear high dynamic range (PFM, EXR) images.
    </para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>
      darktable uses both XMP sidecar files as well as its fast database for saving metadata and
      processing settings. All Exif data is read and written using libexiv2.
    </para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>
      darktable comes with more than 50 image operation modules which cover everything from
      basic operations, tonal value changes, color manipulation, correction of common image
      defects to artistic effects.
    </para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>
      Many darktable modules can be combined with blending operators for even more development
      options.
    </para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>
      A powerful mask feature gives you fine control on module's effect to different parts of an
      image. You can at your choice draw a mask using various shapes or define a parametric mask
      based on pixel values.
    </para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>
      Most modules can exist as multiple instances. Together with the mask feature, you can let
      an operation have different effects on different parts of the image.
    </para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>
      darktable introduces a highly efficient, yet simple <quote>single-click</quote> denoiser
      that always just works&trade;. It's designed as a module where the denoising performance
      only depends on camera and ISO setting. A database of profiles contains parameters for
      well above 100 popular camera models.
    </para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>
      darktable comes with a versatile scripting interface for functionality enhancement using
      Lua as a scripting language.
    </para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>
      Images containing geo coordinates can be displayed on a map with various map sources at
      your choice. Geo coordinates can be assigned to images by manually placing them on the
      map, or by automatically applying GPX track data.
    </para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>
      darktable has a built-in slideshow feature that lets you display your collection of images
      fullscreen.
    </para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>
      A versatile print module lets you send your image to a connected printer with full color
      management support.
    </para></listitem>

  </itemizedlist>

  <sect1 status="final" id="program_invocation">

    <title>Program invocation</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>program invocation</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>command line parameters</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>
      darktable comes with two main binaries: the standard GUI variant which is started by
      calling <filename>darktable</filename> and a command line interface variant which is
      started by calling <filename>darktable-cli</filename> . Additionally darktable is shipped
      with some further binaries for special purposes.
    </para>

    <sect2 status="final" id="darktable_commandline_parameters">

      <title><filename>darktable</filename> binary</title>

      <para>
        This binary starts darktable with its GUI and full functionality; it is the standard way
        of using darktable.
      </para>

      <para>
        <filename>darktable</filename> is called with the following command line parameters:
      </para>

<synopsis>darktable [-d {all,cache,camctl,camsupport,control,dev,
               fswatch,input,lighttable,masks,memory,nan,
               opencl,perf,pwstorage,print,sql}]
          [IMG_1234.{RAW,..}|image_folder] 
          [--version]
          [--disable-opencl] 
          [--library &lt;library file&gt;] 
          [--datadir &lt;data directory&gt;] 
          [--moduledir &lt;module directory&gt;]
          [--tmpdir &lt;tmp directory&gt;] 
          [--configdir &lt;user config directory&gt;]
          [--cachedir &lt;user cache directory&gt;]
          [--localedir &lt;locale directory&gt;]
          [--luacmd &lt;lua command&gt;]
          [--noiseprofiles &lt;noiseprofiles json file&gt;]
          [--conf &lt;key&gt;=&lt;value&gt;]</synopsis>

      <para>
        All parameters are optional; in most cases users will start darktable without any
        additional parameters in which case darktable uses suitable defaults.
        <variablelist>

          <varlistentry>

            <term>-d</term>

            <listitem><para>
              This option enables debug output to the terminal. There are several subsystems of
              darktable and debugging of each of them can be activated separately. You can use
              this option multiple times if you want debugging output of more than one
              subsystem.
            </para></listitem>

          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>

            <term>IMG_1234.{RAW,..} | image_folder</term>

            <listitem><para>
              You may optionally supply the filename of an image or the name of a folder
              containing image files. If a filename is given darktable starts in darkroom view
              with that file opened. If a folder is given darktable starts in lighttable view
              with the content of that folder as the current collection.
            </para></listitem>

          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>

            <term>--version</term>

            <listitem><para>
              This option causes darktable to print its version number, a copyright notice, some
              other useful information, and then terminate.
            </para></listitem>

          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>

            <term>--disable-opencl</term>

            <listitem><para>
              This option prevents darktable from initializing the OpenCL subsystem. Use this
              option in case darktable crashes at startup due to a defective OpenCL
              implementation.
            </para></listitem>

          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>

            <term>--library &lt;library file&gt;</term>

            <listitem><para>
              darktable keeps image information in an sqlite database for fast access. The
              default location of that database file is
              <quote>$HOME/.config/darktable/library.db</quote>. You may give an alternative
              location, e.g. if you want to do some experiments without compromising your
              original library.db. If the database file does not exist, darktable creates it for
              you. You may also give <quote>:memory:</quote> as a library file in which case the
              database is kept in system memory&nbsp;&ndash; all changes are discarded when
              darktable terminates.
            </para></listitem>

          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>

            <term>--datadir &lt;data directory&gt;</term>

            <listitem><para>
              This option defines the directory where darktable finds its runtime data. The
              default place depends on your installation. Typical places are
              <quote>/opt/darktable/share/darktable/</quote> and
              <quote>/usr/share/darktable/</quote>.
            </para></listitem>

          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>

            <term>--moduledir &lt;module directory&gt;</term>

            <listitem><para>
              darktable has a modular structure and organizes its modules as shared libraries
              for loading at runtime. With this option you tell darktable where to look for its
              shared libraries. The default place depends on your installation; typical places
              are <quote>/opt/darktable/lib64/darktable/</quote> and
              <quote>/usr/lib64/darktable/</quote>.
            </para></listitem>

          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>

            <term>--tmpdir &lt;tmp directory&gt;</term>

            <listitem><para>
              The place where darktable stores its temporary files. If this option is not
              supplied darktable uses the system default.
            </para></listitem>

          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>

            <term>--configdir &lt;config directory&gt;</term>

            <listitem><para>
              This option defines the directory where darktable stores the user specific
              configuration. The default place is <quote>$HOME/.config/darktable/</quote>.
            </para></listitem>

          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>

            <term>--cachedir &lt;cache directory&gt;</term>

            <listitem><para>
              darktable keeps a cache of image thumbnails for fast image preview and of
              precompiled OpenCL binaries for fast startup. By default the cache is located in
              <quote>$HOME/.cache/darktable/</quote>. There may exist multiple thumbnail caches
              in parallel&nbsp;&ndash; one for each library file.
            </para></listitem>

          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>

            <term>--localedir &lt;locale directory&gt;</term>

            <listitem><para>
              The place where darktable finds its language specific text strings. The default
              place depends on your installation. Typical places are
              <quote>/opt/darktable/share/locale/</quote> and <quote>/usr/share/locale/</quote>.
            </para></listitem>

          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>

            <term>--luacmd &lt;lua command&gt;</term>

            <listitem><para>
              A string containing lua commands to execute after lua initialization. These
              commands will be run after your <quote>luarc</quote> file.
            </para>

            <para>
              If lua is not compiled in, this option will be accepted but won't do anything.
            </para></listitem>

          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>

            <term>--noiseprofiles &lt;noiseprofiles json file&gt;</term>

            <listitem><para>
              The json file that contains the camera specific noise profiles. The default
              location depends on your installation. Typical places are
              <quote>/opt/darktable/share/darktable/noiseprofile.json</quote> and
              <quote>/usr/share/darktable/noiseprofile.json</quote>.
            </para></listitem>

          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>

            <term>--conf &lt;key&gt;=&lt;value&gt;</term>

            <listitem><para>
              darktable supports a rich set of configuration parameters which the user defines
              in <quote>darktablerc</quote>&nbsp;&ndash; darktable's configuration file in the
              user config directory. You may temporarily overwrite individual settings on the
              command line with this option&nbsp;&ndash; however, these settings will not be
              stored in <quote>darktablerc</quote>.
            </para></listitem>

          </varlistentry>

        </variablelist>
      </para>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 status="final" id="darktable_cli_commandline_parameters">

      <title><filename>darktable-cli</filename> binary</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>darktable-cli</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>
        This binary starts the command line interface variant of darktable which allows
        exporting images.
      </para>

      <para>
        <filename>darktable-cli</filename> is called with the following command line parameters:
      </para>

<synopsis>darktable-cli &lt;input file&gt;
              [&lt;xmp file&gt;] 
              &lt;output file&gt;
              [--width &lt;max width&gt;]
              [--height &lt;max height&gt;]
              [--bpp &lt;bpp&gt;]
              [--hq &lt;0|1|true|false&gt;]
              [--verbose] 
              [--core &lt;darktable options&gt;]</synopsis>

      <para>
        The user needs to supply an input filename and an output filename. All other parameters
        are optional.
        <variablelist>

          <varlistentry>

            <term>&lt;input file&gt;</term>

            <listitem><para>
              The name of the input file to export.
            </para></listitem>

          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>

            <term>&lt;xmp file&gt;</term>

            <listitem><para>
              The optional name of an XMP sidecar file containing the history stack data to be
              applied during export. If this option is not given darktable will search for an
              XMP file that belongs to the given input file.
            </para></listitem>

          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>

            <term>&lt;output file&gt;</term>

            <listitem><para>
              The name of the output file. darktable derives the export file format from the
              file extension.
            </para></listitem>

          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>

            <term>--width &lt;max width&gt;</term>

            <listitem><para>
              This optional parameter allows to limit the width of the exported image to that
              number of pixels.
            </para></listitem>

          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>

            <term>--height &lt;max height&gt;</term>

            <listitem><para>
              This optional parameter allows to limit the height of the exported image to that
              number of pixels.
            </para></listitem>

          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>

            <term>--bpp &lt;bpp&gt;</term>

            <listitem><para>
              An optional parameter to define the bit depth of the exported image; allowed
              values depend on the file format. Currently this option is not yet functional. If
              you need to define the bit depth you need to use the following workaround:
            </para>

<synopsis>--core
--conf plugins/imageio/format/&lt;FORMAT&gt;/bpp=&lt;VALUE&gt;</synopsis>

            <para>
              where &lt;FORMAT&gt; is the name of the selected output format.
            </para></listitem>

          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>

            <term>--hq &lt;0|1|true|false&gt;</term>

            <listitem><para>
              A flag that defines whether to use high quality resampling during export (see
              <xref linkend="core_options"/>). Defaults to true.
            </para></listitem>

          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>

            <term>--verbose</term>

            <listitem><para>
              Enables verbose output.
            </para></listitem>

          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>

            <term>--core &lt;darktable options&gt;</term>

            <listitem><para>
              All command line parameters following <quote>--core</quote> are passed to the
              darktable core and handled as standard parameters. See
              <xref linkend="darktable_commandline_parameters"/> for a detailed description.
            </para></listitem>

          </varlistentry>

        </variablelist>
      </para>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 status="final" id="darktable_generate_cache_commandline_parameters">

      <title><filename>darktable-generate-cache</filename> binary</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>darktable-generate-cache</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>
        This binary updates darktable's thumbnail cache. You can start this program to generate
        all missing thumbnails in the background when your computer is idle.
      </para>

      <para>
        <filename>darktable-generate-cache</filename> is called with the following command line
        parameters:
      </para>

<synopsis>darktable-generate-cache
              [-h, --help]
              [--version]
              [--min-mip &lt;0-7&gt;] [-m, --max-mip &lt;0 - 7&gt;]
              [--min-imgid &lt;N&gt;] [--max-imgid &lt;N&gt;]
              [--core &lt;darktable options&gt;]</synopsis>

      <para>
        All parameters are optional. If started without parameters
        <filename>darktable-generate-cache</filename> uses reasonable defaults.
        <variablelist>

          <varlistentry>

            <term>-h, --help</term>

            <listitem><para>
              Gives usage information and terminates.
            </para></listitem>

          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>

            <term>--version</term>

            <listitem><para>
              Gives copyright and version information and terminates.
            </para></listitem>

          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>

            <term>--min-mip &lt;0 - 7&gt;</term>
            <term>-m, --max-mip &lt;0 - 7&gt;</term>

            <listitem><para>
              darktable can handle and store thumbnails with up to eight different resolution
              steps for each image. These parameters define which maximum resolution should
              be generated and default to a range of 0-2. There is normally no need to
              generate all possible resolutions here; missing ones will be automatically
              generated by darktable the moment they are needed. When asked to generate
              multiple resolutions at once, the lower-resolution images are quickly
              downsampled from the highest-resolution image.
            </para></listitem>

          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>

            <term>--min-imgid &lt;N&gt;</term>
            <term>--max-imgid &lt;N&gt;</term>

            <listitem><para>
              Specifies the range of internal image IDs from the database to work on. If no
              range is given, darktable-generate-cache will process all images from the
              entire collection.
            </para></listitem>

          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>

            <term>--core &lt;darktable options&gt;</term>

            <listitem><para>
              All command line parameters following <quote>--core</quote> are passed to the
              darktable core and handled as standard parameters. See
              <xref linkend="darktable_commandline_parameters"/> for a detailed description.
            </para></listitem>

          </varlistentry>

        </variablelist>
      </para>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 status="final" id="darktable_viewer_commandline_parameters">

      <title><filename>darktable-viewer</filename> binary</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>darktable-viewer</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>
        This binary starts a stand-alone slideshow viewer that displays the images of your
        current collection fullscreen. Press <emphasis>ESC</emphasis> to stop.
      </para>

      <para>
        <filename>darktable-viewer</filename> is called with the following command line
        parameters:
      </para>

<synopsis>darktable-viewer
              [-h, --help]
              [--random]
              [--repeat]
              [--core &lt;darktable options&gt;]</synopsis>

      <para>
        All parameters are optional. If started without parameters
        <filename>darktable-viewer</filename> uses reasonable defaults.
        <variablelist>

          <varlistentry>

            <term>-h, --help</term>

            <listitem><para>
              Gives usage information and terminates.
            </para></listitem>

          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>

            <term>--random</term>

            <listitem><para>
              Displays images in random instead of the default sequential order.
            </para></listitem>

          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>

            <term>--repeat</term>

            <listitem><para>
              Continues the slideshow in an endless loop instead of terminating after the last
              image.
            </para></listitem>

          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>

            <term>--core &lt;darktable options&gt;</term>

            <listitem><para>
              All command line parameters following <quote>--core</quote> are passed to the
              darktable core and handled as standard parameters. See
              <xref linkend="darktable_commandline_parameters"/> for a detailed description.
            </para></listitem>

          </varlistentry>

        </variablelist>
      </para>

      <para>
        <filename>darktable-viewer</filename> uses OpenGL to produce soft transitions between
        images. Although OpenGL and OpenCL (see <xref linkend="darktable_and_opencl"/>) are
        designed to cooperate flawlessly, there have been reports about problems with certain
        setups. If <filename>darktable-viewer</filename> crashes upon startup, please try to use
        it without OpenCL support:
      </para>

      <para>
<programlisting>darktable-viewer --core --disable-opencl
</programlisting>
      </para>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 status="final" id="darktable_cltest_commandline_parameters">

      <title><filename>darktable-cltest</filename> binary</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>darktable-cltest</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>
        This binary checks if there is a usable OpenCL environment on your system that darktable
        can use. It emits some debug output that is equivalent to calling <quote>darktable -d
        opencl</quote> and then terminates.
      </para>

      <para>
        <filename>darktable-cltest</filename> is called without command line parameters:
      </para>

<synopsis>darktable-cltest</synopsis>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 status="final" id="darktable_cmstest_commandline_parameters">

      <title><filename>darktable-cmstest</filename> binary</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>darktable-cmstest</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>
        This binary investigates if the color management subsystem of your computer is correctly
        configured and it displays some useful information about the installed monitor
        profile(s).
      </para>

      <para>
        <filename>darktable-cmstest</filename> is called without command line parameters:
      </para>

<synopsis>darktable-cmstest</synopsis>

    </sect2>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 status="final" id="user_interface">

    <title>User interface</title>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth='6*'/>
        <colspec colwidth='4*'/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>
                This section describes the layout of the user interface.
              </para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="images/lighttable_view.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

    <sect2 status="final" id="views">

      <title>Views</title>

      <para>
        darktable consists of several views or modes. There are five available views as
        described in this section. You can switch between views by clicking the view name at the
        top of the right panel&nbsp;&ndash; the active view is highlighted&nbsp;&ndash; or by
        using one of the key accelerators:
        <informaltable frame="none" width="60%">
          <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
            <colspec colwidth='1*'/>
            <colspec colwidth='9*'/>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <emphasis>l</emphasis>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  switches to lighttable
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <emphasis>d</emphasis>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  switches to darkroom
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <emphasis>t</emphasis>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  switches to camera tethering
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <emphasis>m</emphasis>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  switches to map
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <emphasis>s</emphasis>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  switches to slideshow
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <emphasis>p</emphasis>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  switches to print
                </entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
      </para>

      <sect3 status="final">

        <title>Lighttable</title>

        <para>
          The lighttable view is where images and film rolls are managed. It's also where you
          rate images, add tags and colorlabels, and export images among other actions (see
          <xref linkend="lighttable_chapter"/>).
        </para>

      </sect3>

      <sect3 status="final">

        <title>Darkroom</title>

        <para>
          In the darkroom view you develop a single image using the available modules (see
          <xref linkend="darkroom_chapter"/>).
        </para>

      </sect3>

      <sect3 status="final">

        <title>Tethering</title>

        <para>
          This view is for shooting with the camera connected to the computer and remotely
          capturing images that will be downloaded and shown on computer screen (see
          <xref linkend="tethering_chapter"/>).
        </para>

      </sect3>

      <sect3 status="final">

        <title>Map</title>

        <para>
          This view shows images with geo-tag data on a map and allows manually geo-tagging new
          images (see <xref linkend="map_chapter"/>).
        </para>

      </sect3>

      <sect3 status="final">

        <title>Slideshow</title>

        <para>
          This view shows images as a slideshow, processing them on-the-fly (see
          <xref linkend="slideshow_chapter"/>).
        </para>

      </sect3>

      <sect3 status="final">

        <title>Print</title>

        <para>
          This view allows you to send images to your printer (see
          <xref linkend="print_chapter"/>).
        </para>

      </sect3>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 status="final" id="screen_layout">

      <title>Screen layout</title>

      <para>
        The general screen layout of all views is similar. There is a center area which contains
        most of the relevant information of that view. Then there are panels left, right, top
        and bottom to the center area. The left panel typically has an informational purpose.
        The right panel offers functions to modify an image. The top and bottom panel give
        access to several settings and shortcuts. Each of the panels can be collapsed or
        expanded by pressing a triangle like
        <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_general_collapse;" scalefit="1" width="2%"/>
        , located close to the panel.
      </para>

      <para>
        By pressing the <emphasis>TAB</emphasis> key all panels get collapsed, allowing the
        center area to occupy all available space. Pressing <emphasis>TAB</emphasis> again
        brings you back to the previous view.
      </para>

      <para>
        Fullscreen view can be toggled by pressing <emphasis>F11</emphasis>.
      </para>

      <para>
        darktable's contrast can be changed by using <emphasis>F7</emphasis> and
        <emphasis>F8</emphasis> and darktable's lightness by using <emphasis>F9</emphasis> and
        <emphasis>F10</emphasis>.
      </para>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 status="final" id="filmstrip_overview">

      <title>Filmstrip</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>filmstrip</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>
        The filmstrip along the bottom shows the same images as lighttable, with respect to
        filters and sort order. It is turned on/off with key accelerator
        <emphasis>ctrl-f</emphasis>. You can navigate along the filmstrip by scrolling with the
        mouse wheel and change the height of the filmstrip panel by dragging its top. The
        filmstrip allows you to interact with images while you are not in lighttable mode. For
        example, you can, while developing an image in darkroom mode, switch to another image to
        develop, by double clicking the thumbnail in the filmstrip. You can also rate the images
        as you do in lighttable, copy/paste history stack, etc.
      </para>

      <para>
        <graphic fileref="overview/images/filmstrip.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
      </para>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 status="final" id="preferences">

      <title>Preferences</title>

      <para>
        A button
        <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_preferences;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center" />
        located in the upper panel allows you to define various parameters which control
        darktable's behavior.
      </para>

      <para>
        The options are fairly self-explanatory. If you need more information, hover the mouse
        cursor over the text label or entry box, to display a popup tool-tip. All configuration
        parameters are explained in <xref linkend="preferences_chapter"/>.
      </para>

    </sect2>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 status="final" id="darktable_basic_workflow">

    <title>darktable basic workflow</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>basic workflow</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>
      This section describes a typical darktable workflow which novice users may take as a
      starting point. We describe how to get an image into darktable, the basic steps of a raw
      development workflow and how to export the final result.
    </para>

    <sect2 status ="final">

      <title>Importing images</title>

      <para>
        To begin with darktable, you first need to import images. The import module is in the
        left panel of the lighttable view (<xref linkend="import"/>). You can either import from
        the filesystem or, if darktable supports your camera model, directly from camera.
      </para>

      <sect3 status="final">

        <title>Importing images from filesystem</title>

        <para>
          When importing from disk, you can import either a single image or a folder. darktable
          will analyse its content, detect images that are already imported and only import new
          images.
        </para>

      </sect3>

      <sect3 status="final">

        <title>Importing from camera</title>

        <para>
          Connect your camera to your system. If your distribution tries to automount it, select
          the option to abort the mount operation. Otherwise the camera will be locked and not
          accessible from within darktable. If you don't see your camera in the import module,
          hit the <quote>scan for devices</quote> button. Your camera will then appear in the
          same module with additional choices: <emphasis>import</emphasis> and
          <emphasis>tethering</emphasis>.
        </para>

      </sect3>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 status="final" id="basic_development_steps">

      <title>Basic development steps</title>

      <sect3>

        <title>Introduction</title>

        <para>
          This section will guide you through the basics of developing an image in the darkroom
          view.
        </para>

        <para>
          To begin, open an image in darkroom mode by double clicking an image thumbnail on the
          lighttable. The darkroom mode is where the actual adjustments for an image are made,
          where an arsenal of modules are at hand to help you reach your goal.
        </para>

        <para>
          Each change made on a module while developing an image is turned into a
          <link linkend="history"><emphasis>history stack</emphasis></link> item. The history is
          stored in a database and in an XMP sidecar file for the specific image.
        </para>

        <para>
          All changes are stored automatically. You can safely leave darkroom mode or quit
          darktable at any time and come back later to continue your work. That said darktable
          does not need a <quote>save</quote> button and it does not have one.
          <indexterm>
            <primary>save button</primary>
          </indexterm>
        </para>

        <para>
          On the left panel in darkroom mode is the <link linkend="history"><emphasis>history
          stack</emphasis></link>, showing changes starting from bottom, and building up with
          each change made to the image. You can select a point in this history to show how the
          image looked at that point, for comparison of changes. The stack can be compressed: it
          will be optimized and redundant changes will be discarded. When you think you are done
          and are happy with what you have done, just compress the history stack.
        </para>

        <para>
          darktable ships with a number of modules, arranged into groups. These module groups
          are accessed via toggle buttons in the right panel, just under the histogram. There
          are also two special module groups named <quote>active</quote> and
          <quote>favorites</quote>, which only show modules enabled in the history for the
          current image, and modules selected as a favorite, respectively. Marking a module as a
          favorite is done in the <emphasis>more modules</emphasis> dialog
          (<xref linkend="more_modules"/>), at the bottom of the right panel, by clicking a
          module until a star is displayed in front of the icon.
        </para>

      </sect3>

      <sect3 status="final">

        <title>White balance</title>

        <para>
          The <link linkend="whitebalance"><emphasis>white balance</emphasis></link> module
          controls the white balance or color temperature of the image. It's always enabled and
          reads its default values from camera metadata embedded in the image. The most common
          change is fine-tuning the white balance, which is done using the
          <quote>temperature</quote> slider. Moving this slider left will make the color balance
          cooler, and moving it right will make it warmer.
        </para>

      </sect3>

      <sect3 status="final">

        <title>Exposure correction</title>

        <para>
          The <link linkend="exposure"><emphasis>exposure</emphasis></link> module is probably
          the most basic module of them all. Exposure is fine-tuned either by using the slider,
          or by dragging with the mouse in the
          <link linkend="histogram"><emphasis>histogram</emphasis></link>. You can also boost
          the black level to enhance contrast; but be careful: use small amounts, like steps of
          0.005. There is also an auto-correct feature.
        </para>

      </sect3>

      <sect3 status="final">

        <title>Noise reduction</title>

        <para>
          The best starting point for noise reduction is
          <link linkend="denoise_profiled"><emphasis>profiled denoise</emphasis></link>. This
          module offers an almost <quote>single-click</quote> solution to fight noise. From a
          user perspective the effect only depends on camera type and ISO value, both derived
          from EXIF data. All other settings are taken from a database of noise profiles that
          the darktable team has collected&nbsp;&ndash; now covering well above 100 popular
          camera models. In addition you have several other options in darktable to reduce
          noise. There is <link linkend="raw_denoise"><emphasis>raw denoise</emphasis></link>,
          <link linkend="denoise_bilateral"><emphasis>denoising based on bilateral
          filter</emphasis></link>, <link linkend="denoise_non_local_means"> <emphasis>denoising
          based on non-local means</emphasis></link>, and
          <link linkend="equalizer"><emphasis>equalizer</emphasis></link>, which is based on
          wavelets. If your camera is not yet supported by
          <link linkend="denoise_profiled"><emphasis>profiled denoise</emphasis></link>,
          <link linkend="denoise_non_local_means"><emphasis>denoising based on non-local
          means</emphasis></link> is probably the most convenient, as it allows you to treat
          color and luminance noise separately.
        </para>

      </sect3>

      <sect3 status="final">

        <title>Fixing spots</title>

        <para>
          Sometimes you will need to remove spots caused by sensor dirt. The
          <link linkend="spot_removal"><emphasis>spot removal</emphasis></link> module is at
          hand and can also correct other disturbing elements like skin blemishes. If your
          camera has stuck pixels or tends to produce hot pixels at high ISO values, or longer
          exposure times, have a look at the <link linkend="hotpixels"><emphasis>hot
          pixels</emphasis></link> module for automatic correction.
        </para>

      </sect3>

      <sect3 status="final">

        <title>Geometrical corrections</title>

        <para>
          Quite frequently you want to only show part of the captured scene in your image, e.g.
          to take away some disturbing feature close to the frame. In other cases, the horizon
          in the image may need levelling, or there are perspective distortions. All this can be
          corrected in the <link linkend="crop_and_rotate"><emphasis>crop and
          rotate</emphasis></link> module. If you need to correct typical camera lens flaws like
          cushion distortion, transversal chromatic aberrations or vignetting, there is a
          <link linkend="lens_correction"><emphasis>lens correction</emphasis></link> module.
        </para>

      </sect3>

      <sect3 status="final">

        <title>Bringing back detail</title>

        <para>
          Digital RAW images often contain more information than you can see at first sight.
          Especially in the shadows of an image, there are lots of hidden details. The
          <link linkend="shadows_and_highlights"><emphasis>shadows and
          highlights</emphasis></link> module helps bring these details back into visible tonal
          values. Structural details in fully blown-out highlights, by nature of the digital
          sensor, can not be recovered. However, you can correct unfavorable color casts in
          these areas with the <link linkend="highlight_reconstruction"><emphasis>highlight
          reconstruction</emphasis></link> module. Additionally the
          <link linkend="color_reconstruction"><emphasis>color reconstruction</emphasis></link>
          module is able to fill overexposed areas with suitable colors based on their
          surroundings.
        </para>

      </sect3>

      <sect3 status="final">

        <title>Adjusting tonal values</title>

        <para>
          Almost every workflow is likely to include adjusting the image's tonal range.
          darktable offers several alternative modules to take care of that. The most basic one
          is the <link linkend="contrast_brightness_saturation"><emphasis>contrast brightness
          saturation</emphasis></link> module. In the <link linkend="tone_curve"><emphasis>tone
          curve</emphasis></link> module, tonal values are adjusted by constructing a gradient
          curve. The <link linkend="levels"><emphasis>levels</emphasis></link> module offers a
          concise interface, with three markers in a histogram. In addition, there is a
          <link linkend="zone_system"><emphasis>zone system</emphasis></link> module which
          allows control over tonal values by zones, inspired by the work of Ansel Adams.
        </para>

      </sect3>

      <sect3 status="final">

        <title>Enhancing local contrast</title>

        <para>
          Local contrast enhancement can emphasize detail and clarity in your image. Carefully
          used, it can give your photograph the right pop. darktable offers several modules for
          this task. The <link linkend="local_contrast"><emphasis>local
          contrast</emphasis></link> module is easy to handle, with just a few parameters. A
          much more versatile, but also more complex technique, is offered by the
          <link linkend="equalizer"><emphasis>equalizer</emphasis></link> module. Have a look at
          its presets, to get a feeling for how it works. Equalizer is darktable's "Swiss Army
          Knife" for many adjustments where spatial dimension plays a role.
        </para>

      </sect3>

      <sect3 status="final">

        <title>Color adjustments</title>

        <para>
          darktable offers many modules for adjusting colors in an image. A very straightforward
          technique is implemented in the <link linkend="color_correction"><emphasis>color
          correction</emphasis></link> module. Use it to give an image an overall tint or to
          adjust overall color saturation. The <link linkend="color_zones"><emphasis>color
          zones</emphasis></link> module offers a much finer control to adjust saturation, or
          lightness, and even hue, in user defined zones. darktable's
          <link linkend="tone_curve"><emphasis>tone curve</emphasis></link> module&nbsp;&ndash;
          in addition to the classical adjustment of tonal values&nbsp;&ndash; gives you fine
          control over the colors in an image. Finally, if you intend to convert an image into
          black &amp; white, a good starting point, with an easy to use and intuitive user
          interface, is offered by the
          <link linkend="monochrome"><emphasis>monochrome</emphasis></link> module.
          Alternatively, you might consider using darktable's
          <link linkend="channel_mixer"><emphasis>channel mixer</emphasis></link>.
        </para>

      </sect3>

      <sect3 status="final">

        <title>Sharpening</title>

        <para>
          If you start your workflow from a RAW image, you will need to have your final output
          sharpened. The <link linkend="sharpen"><emphasis>sharpen</emphasis></link> module can
          do this with the classical USM (unsharp mask) approach, available in most image
          processing software. Another very versatile way to enhance edges in an image is
          offered by the <link linkend="highpass"><emphasis>highpass</emphasis></link> module,
          in combination with darktable's rich set of blending operators.
        </para>

      </sect3>

      <sect3 status="final">

        <title>Artistic effects</title>

        <para>
          darktable comes with a rich set of artistic effect modules. To name just a few: with
          the <link linkend="watermark"><emphasis>watermark</emphasis></link> module you add an
          individual watermark to your image. The
          <link linkend="grain"><emphasis>grain</emphasis></link> module simulates the typical
          noise of classical analogue footage. Use the
          <link linkend="color_mapping"><emphasis>color mapping</emphasis></link> module to
          transfer the look and feel of one color image onto another. darktable's
          <link linkend="low_light"><emphasis>low light</emphasis></link> module allows to
          simulate human vision to make lowlight pictures look closer to reality. The
          <link linkend="graduated_density"><emphasis>graduated density</emphasis></link> filter
          adds a neutral or colored gradient to your image for exposure and color correction.
        </para>

      </sect3>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 status="final" id="exporting_images">

      <title>Exporting images</title>

      <para>
        Changes to an image are not saved as in a regular image editor. darktable is a
        non-destructive editor, which means all changes are stored in a database, and the
        original image is untouched. Therefore, you need to export images to bake the processing
        options into an output file that can be distributed outside of darktable.
      </para>

      <para>
        Images are exported from the lighttable view, using the <emphasis>export
        selected</emphasis> dialog in the right panel (<xref linkend="export_selected"/>). In
        general, export means: save my developed RAW image as a JPEG.
      </para>

      <para>
        The export is modularized into <emphasis>storage</emphasis> and
        <emphasis>format</emphasis>. darktable ships with several storage modules such as
        <emphasis>save on disk</emphasis>, various webalbums, a LaTeX photo book template and
        more. Format modules are the actual image formats such as JPEG, PNG, TIFF, OpenEXR and
        more.
      </para>

      <para>
        Select images on the lighttable, choose the target storage and format, and set the
        maximum width and height image restraints. This means that none of the images will be
        bigger than any of the width/height restraints and hit the export button. Leave the
        width and height restraints at zero, if you want the original resolution.
      </para>

    </sect2>

  </sect1>

</chapter>
