<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>

<chapter>
	<chapterinfo>
		<keywordset>
			<keyword>darktable</keyword>
			<keyword>overview</keyword>
			<keyword>application</keyword>
		</keywordset>
	</chapterinfo>
	<title>Overview</title>
	<para>darktable is an application to manage and develop your digital images.</para>
	<para>It is fully non-destructive and works on a 32 bit floating point format per channel.
			Most of the actions on the pixelpipe are done in CIELab.</para>


	<sect1 status="final"><title>User interface</title>
		<informaltable frame="none"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
					<colspec colwidth='100%'/>
					<colspec colwidth='5cm'/>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry>This section describes the layout of the user interface. You can change darktable's contrast by using <emphasis>F7</emphasis> and <emphasis>F8</emphasis>.
							</entry>
							<entry>
								<graphic fileref="images/lighttable_view.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
							</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</informaltable>

		<sect2 status="final"><title>Views</title>
			<para>darktable consists of several views also mentioned as modes. For the time being, there are four available views as described
				in this section. The current view is identified by the label at the top of the right panel.
				Some key accelerators, allowing to access the different views, are described in the table below:
				<informaltable frame="none"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
						<colspec colwidth='3cm'/>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry><emphasis>l</emphasis></entry><entry>switches to lighttable view</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry><emphasis>d</emphasis></entry><entry>switches to darkroom view</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry><emphasis>t</emphasis></entry><entry>switches to camera tethering view</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry><emphasis>m</emphasis></entry><entry>switches to map view</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup></informaltable>
			</para>
			<sect3 status="final"><title>Lighttable</title>
				<para>The lighttable view is where you manage your images and filmrolls; it's in that view that you rate, add tags, add colorlabels, export images among other
					actions.
				</para>

				<para>You can perform some actions on the image under the mouse pointer using key accelerators; see "Lighttable" chapter.
				</para>

			</sect3>
			<sect3 status="final"><title>Darkroom</title>
				<para>In the darkroom view you develop a specific image using the available modules.
				</para>
			</sect3>
			<sect3 status="final"><title>Tethering</title>
				<para>This view is where you do camera tethering, ie. connecting your camera to the computer and remotely capturing images that will be downloaded and shown on your computer screen.
				</para>
			</sect3>
			<sect3 status="final"><title>Map</title>
				<para>This view allows to see images that are geo-tagged on a map.
				</para>
			</sect3>

			<sect3 status="final"><title>Filmstrip</title>
				<para>The filmstrip shows the same images as lighttable with respect to filters and sort order; it is turned on/off with key accelerator <emphasis>ctrl-f</emphasis>.
			  	You can navigate along the filmstrip by wheel scrolling.
				The filmstrip allows you to interact with images when you are not in lighttable mode. For example you can, while being in darkroom mode and developing an image,
				switch to another image to develop by double clicking the thumb in the filmstrip. You can also rate the images as you do in lighttable, copy/paste history stack, etc.
				</para>
				<graphic fileref="overview/images/filmstrip.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />

			</sect3>
		</sect2>


	</sect1>


	<sect1 status="final"><title>darktable basic workflow</title>
		<sect2 status="draft"><title>Importing images</title>
			<para>To begin with darktable, you first need to import images. You can either import
					from your filesystem or from your camera if supported.</para>
			<para>In the left panel you will find the import module, here you have the choice to import either a single image or a folder,
					darktable will analyse its content, detect images that are already imported and only import new images.
			</para>
		</sect2>

		<sect2 status="draft"><title>Importing from camera</title>
		<!--	<sect3><title>Introduction</title> -->
				<para>Connect your camera to your system and if your distribution tries to automount it, select the option to abort the mount operation.
					Otherwise the camera will be locked and not accessible from within darktable.</para>

				<para>In the left panel of lighttable view you have the import pane and if you don't see your camera there you need to hit the
					scan for devices button. Your camera will then appear in same pane with additional actions: import and tethering.</para>
               <!--		</sect3>

			<sect3 status="draft"><title>Settings</title>
			</sect3>  -->
		</sect2>

		<sect2 status="draft"><title>Basic correction</title>
			<sect3><title>Introduction</title>
				<para>This section will guide you through the basics about developing your image which includes most common changes to an image like
					noise reduction, color temperature, exposure etc.
				</para>

				<para>To begin you need to open an image in darkroom mode which you will do by double clicking an image thumbnail on the lighttable,
					it's in the darkroom mode you do the actual adjustments for an image and you have an arsenal of modules at your hand to help you
					reach your goal.
				</para>

				<para>Each change you make on a module when developing your image is turned into a history stack item, the history is stored in a database
					and in an XMP sidecar file for the specific image.
				</para>

				<para>
					On the left panel in darkroom mode you have the history stack showing changes starting from bottom and building up with each change
					you have made to the image. You can select a point in this history to show how the image looked in that point for comparison of changes.
					The stack can be compressed and will discard changes done during the development but will make it optimized. When you think you are done
					and have a good feeling of what you have done, just compress the history stack.
				</para>

				<para>
					darktable ships with a bunch of modules and each of them is arranged into groups named module groups, these module groups are accessed
					via toggle buttons in the right panel just under the histogram.
					There are also two special module groups named active and favorites, where active will only show modules enabled in the history for the current image and
						favorites will only show modules selected as a favorite by you. This is done in the <quote>more plugins</quote> at the bottom of the right panel, just click your favorite module
					until it gets a star displayed in front of the icon and you have chosen your favorite.
				</para>
			</sect3>

			<sect3 status="draft"><title>White balance</title>
				<para>This module controls the white balance of the image, it's always enabled and reads its default
					values from metadata embedded in the image which will be set by your camera.
					The most common change here will be fine-tuning the white balance and this is done using the
					temperature in slider.
					Taking it down will make the color balance cooler and steering it up will make it warmer.
				</para>
			</sect3>

			<sect3 status="draft"><title>Exposure</title>
				<para>This might be the simplest module of them all, fine-tune your exposure and use the histogram to guide you if you don't know what you are doing.
						You can also boost the black level by increasing the black but be careful, use small amount like 0.005 steps.
						If you feel lucky use the auto correction feature, this might fail for several technical reasons&nbsp;&hellip;
				</para>
				<para>You can also click-and-drag in the histogram to change exposure / blackpoint.
				</para>
			</sect3>

  		<sect3 status="draft"><title>Noise reduction</title>
				<para>You have several options in darktable to reduce noise. You'll find them in the correct group.
        There is the hot pixel removal module, raw denosie, denoising based on bilateral filter, non-local means, and based on wavelets (the equalizer). Most convenient to use is probably denoising based on non-local means, as it allows you to treat color and luminance noise separately.
        </para>
			</sect3>


		</sect2>

		<sect2 status="draft"><title>Exporting images</title>
			<para>Your changes to an image are not saved as in a regular image editor. darktable is a non destructive editor which means all your changes are stored in a database and the original image is untouched      			and therefore you need to export your images to get an <quote>image</quote> file to distribute with your special processing.</para>
			<para>Images are exported from lighttable using the export module in the right panel. In general, export means: save my developed RAW image as a JPEG.</para>
			<para>The export is also modularized into storage and format. darktable is shipping several storage modules such as save on disk, picasa and flickr webalbum and more.
				Format modules are the actual image formats such as JPEG, PNG, TIFF, OpenEXR and more.
			</para>
			<para>Select images on your lighttable that you want to export, then choose your target storage and format to use and set the maximum width and height image restraint, this means that 
                              none of the images will be bigger than any of the width/height restraint. Leave the width and height restraint as zero value if you want the original resolution and hit the export button.
			</para>

		</sect2>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 status="draft"><title>Preferences</title>
		<para>A button <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_preferences;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center" /> located at the upper panel allows you to define various parameters.
		</para>
		<para>The options are quite self-explaining. In case you need more information, just let your mouse hover a text label and/or entry box to display more information. Furthermore all
                      configuration parameters are explained in a later chapter of this manual.
		</para>

	</sect1>

</chapter>
