<!DOCTYPE sect3 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect3 status="final" id="perspective_correction">

  <title>Perspective correction</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>modules</primary>
    <secondary>perspective correction</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>perspective correction</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect4>

    <title>Overview</title>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              This module is designed to automatically correct for converging lines, a form of
              perspective distortions frequently seen in architectural photographs. The
              underlying mechanism is inspired by Markus Hebel's
              <ulink url="http://www.shiftn.de/"><emphasis>ShiftN</emphasis></ulink> program.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/ashift.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

    <para>
      Perspective distortions are a natural effect when projecting a three dimensional scene
      onto a two dimensional plane and cause objects close to the viewer to appear larger than
      objects further away. Converging lines are a special case of perspective distortions
      frequently seen in architectural photographs. Parallel lines when photographed at an angle
      get transformed into converging lines that meet at some vantage point within or outside
      the image frame.
    </para>

    <para>
      This module is able to correct converging lines by warping the image in such a way that
      the lines in question become parallel to the image frame. Corrections can be applied in
      vertical and horizontal direction, either separately or in combination. In order to
      perform an automatic correction the module analyzes the image for suitable structural
      features consisting of line segments. Based on these line segments a fitting procedure is
      started that determines the best values of the module parameters.
    </para>

  </sect4>

  <sect4>

    <title>Usage</title>

    <para>
      Clicking the <quote>get structure</quote> icon (
      <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_ashift_structure;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center" />
      ) causes darktable to analyze the image for structural elements. Line segments are
      detected and evaluated. Only lines that form a set of either vertical or horizontal lines
      are used for further processing steps. The line segments are displayed as overlays on the
      image base. A color code describes what type of line darktable has found:
      <informaltable frame="none" width="80%">
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
          <colspec colwidth='1*'/>
          <colspec colwidth='4*'/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis>green</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                lines that are selected as relevant vertical converging lines
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis>red</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                lines that are vertical but are not part of the set of converging lines
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis>blue</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                lines that are selected as relevant horizontal converging lines
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis>yellow</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                lines that are horizontal but are not part of the set of converging lines
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis>grey</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                other lines identified but not of interest to this module
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </para>

    <para>
      Lines marked in red or yellow are regarded as outliers and are not taken into account for
      the automatic fitting step. This outlier elimination involves a statistical process with
      random sampling so that each time you press the <quote>get structure</quote> button the
      color pattern of the lines will look a bit different. You can manually change the status
      of line segments: left-clicking on a line selects it (turns the color to green or blue)
      while right-clicking deselects it (turns the color to red or yellow). Keeping the mouse
      button pressed allows for a sweeping action to select/deselect multiple lines in a row;
      the size of the select/deselect brush can be changed with the mouse wheel. Holding down
      the <emphasis>shift</emphasis> key and keeping the left or right mouse button pressed
      while dragging selects or deselects all lines in the chosen rectangular area.
    </para>

    <para>
      Clicking one of the <quote>automatic fit</quote> icons (see below) starts an optimization
      process which finds the best suited parameters. The image and the overlaid lines are then
      displayed with perspective corrections applied.
    </para>

    <sect5>
      <title>rotation</title>
      <para>
        This parameter controls a rotation of the image around its center and can correct for a
        skewed horizon.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>lens shift (horizontal)</title>
      <para>
        This parameter corrects converging lines horizontally.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>lens shift (vertical)</title>
      <para>
        This parameter corrects converging lines vertically. In some cases you get a more
        naturally looking image if you correct vertical distortions not to their full extent but
        rather at an 80 to 90% level. If desired just reduce the value after having performed
        the automatic correction.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>shear</title>
      <para>
        This parameter shears the image along one of its diagonals and is needed when correcting
        vertical and horizontal perspective distortions simultaneously.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>guides</title>
      <para>
        If activated a number of guide lines is laid over the image to help you judge the
        quality of the correction.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>automatic cropping</title>
      <para>
        When activated the automatic cropping feature clips the image to get rid of any black
        corners. At your choice you can either clip to the <quote>largest area</quote> or to the
        largest rectangle maintaining the original aspect ratio (<quote>original
        format</quote>).
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>lens model</title>
      <para>
        This parameter controls how lens and camera specifics are taken into account. If set to
        <quote>generic</quote> a focal length of 28mm on a full-format camera is assumed. If set
        to <quote>specific</quote>, focal length and crop factor can be set manually.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>focal length</title>
      <para>
        The focal length of the lens used. The default value is taken from the Exif data of your
        image. This parameter is only effective and visible if the <quote>specific</quote> lens
        model has been selected.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>crop factor</title>
      <para>
        The crop factor of the camera used. You will typically need to set this value manually.
        This parameter is only effective and visible if the <quote>specific</quote> lens model
        has been selected.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>aspect adjust</title>
      <para>
        If the <quote>specific</quote> lens model has been selected this parameter allows for a
        free manual adjustment of the image's aspect ratio.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>automatic fit</title>
      <para>
        Clicking on one of the icons starts an automatic fitting of the module parameters based
        on the selected vertical and/or horizontal lines. You can choose to correct only
        vertical distortions (
        <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_ashift_vertical;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center" />
        ), only horizontal distortions (
        <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_ashift_horizontal;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center" />
        ), or both types of distortions simultaneously (
        <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_ashift_both;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center" />
        ). <emphasis>Ctrl-clicking</emphasis> on either icon only fits rotation.
        <emphasis>Shift-clicking</emphasis> on either icon only fits vertical and/or horizontal
        lens shift.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>get structure</title>
      <para>
        Clicking on the
        <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_ashift_structure;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center" />
        icon causes the image to be (re-)analyzed for suitable line segments.
        <emphasis>Shift-clicking</emphasis> applies a prior contrast enhancement step,
        <emphasis>ctrl-clicking</emphasis> applies an edge enhancement step. Both variations can
        be used alone or in combination if the default is not able to detect a sufficient number
        of lines. Clicking on the
        <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_ashift_clear;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center" />
        icon discards all collected structural data. By clicking on the
        <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_ashift_eye;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center" />
        icon you can switch the overlay display of line segments on and off.
      </para>
    </sect5>

  </sect4>

  <sect4>

    <title>Examples</title>

    <para>
      <informaltable frame="none">
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
          <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
          <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/ashift_ex1.png" scalefit="1" width="90%" align="center" />
              </entry>
              <entry>
                An input image with a skewed horizon and converging lines caused by directing
                the camera upwards.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/ashift_ex2.png" scalefit="1" width="90%" align="center" />
              </entry>
              <entry>
                The image after having corrected for vertical and horizontal perspective
                distortions. Note the framing by the automatic cropping feature and the still
                visible overlay of structural lines.
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </para>

  </sect4>

</sect3>
