<!DOCTYPE sect3 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect3 status="final" id="defringe">

  <title>Defringe</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>modules</primary>
    <secondary>defringe</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>defringe</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>purple fringing</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect4>

    <title>Overview</title>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              This module is designed to remove purple or any other color of fringing which
              often results from Longitudinal Chromatic Abberations (LCA), also known as Axial
              Chromatic Abberations.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/defringe.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

  </sect4>

  <sect4>

    <title>Usage</title>

    <para>
      This module helps removing fringe via edge-detection. Where pixels are detected as a
      fringe, it rebuilds the color from lower-saturated neighboring pixels.
    </para>

    <sect5>
      <title>operation mode</title>
      <para>
        Set the operation mode for detecting fringes. <quote>global average</quote> is usually
        the fastest but might show slightly incorrect previews in high magnification. It might
        also protect the wrong regions of color too much or too little by comparison with local
        averaging. <quote>local average</quote> is slower because it computes local color
        references for every pixel, which might protect color better than global average and
        allows for rebuilding color where actually required. The <quote>static</quote> method
        does not use a color reference but directly uses the threshold as given by the user.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>edge detection radius</title>
      <para>
        Set the spatial extent of the gaussian blur used for an edge detection. The algorithm
        uses the difference of gaussian-blurred and original image as an indicator for edges (a
        special case of the <quote>difference of gaussians</quote> edge detection). Try
        increasing this value if you either want a stronger detection of the fringes or the
        thickness of the fringe edges is too high.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>threshold</title>
      <para>
        Sets the threshold over which the edge of a pixel is counted as a <quote>fringe</quote>.
        The colors of the affected pixels will be rebuild from neighboring pixels. Try lowering
        this value if there is not enough fringe detected and try increasing this value if too
        many pixels are desaturated. You may additionally want to play around with the edge
        detection radius.
      </para>
    </sect5>

  </sect4>

</sect3>
