<sect3 status="final" id="denoise_profiled">

  <title>Denoise - profiled</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>modules</primary>
    <secondary>denoise - profiled</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>denoise</primary>
    <secondary>profiled</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>noise removal</primary>
    <see>denoise</see>
  </indexterm>

  <sect4>

    <title>Overview</title>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              This module offers an easy to use and - at the same time - highly efficient
              denoise operation. Under the hood it applies (your choice of) a non-local means or
              edge-aware wavelet denoise algorithm with parameters specifically profiled for
              certain camera models and ISO settings.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/denoise_profiled.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

  </sect4>

  <sect4>

    <title>Usage</title>

    <para>
      The darktable team, with the help of many users, has measured noise profiles for various
      cameras. Differentiated by ISO settings we evaluated how the noise statistics develop with
      brightness for the three color channels. Our set of profiles already covers about 100
      popular camera models from all major manufacturers.
    </para>

    <sect5>
      <title>profile</title>
      <para>
        Based on EXIF data of your RAW file, darktable will automatically determine the camera
        model and ISO setting. If found in its database, the corresponding noise profile will be
        used. If your image has an intermediate ISO value, the statistical properties will be
        interpolated between the two closest datasets in the database, and this interpolated
        setting will show up as the first line in the combo box. You also have the option to
        manually overwrite this selection to suit your personal preferences better. The top-most
        entry in the combo box brings you back to the profile darktable deems most suited.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>mode</title>
      <para>
        This module can eliminate noise with two different core algorithms. <quote>non-local
        means</quote> is a bit better suited to tackle luma (lightness) noise; <quote>
        wavelet</quote> has its strength in eliminating chroma (color) noise. If needed you can
        apply two instances of this module (see <xref linkend="multiple_instances"/>). The
        <quote>non-local means</quote> instance should be combined with blend mode
        <quote>lightness</quote> or <quote>HSV lightness</quote>; the <quote>wavelet</quote>
        instance with blend mode <quote>color</quote> or <quote>HSV color</quote>. For more
        information on blend modes have a look at <xref linkend="blending_operators"/>.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>patch size</title>
      <para>
        This slider is only available if mode <quote>non-local means</quote> is selected. It
        controls the size of the patches being matched when deciding which pixels to average
        (see also <xref linkend="denoise_non_local_means"/>). Setting this to higher values can
        give more sharpness. Processing time will stay about the same.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>strength</title>
      <para>
        This parameter is here to fine-tune the strength of the denoise effect. The default
        value has been chosen to maximize the peak signal to noise ratio. It's mostly a matter
        of taste if you prefer a rather low noise level at the costs of a higher loss of detail,
        or if you accept more remaining noise in order to have finer structures better preserved
        within your image.
      </para>
    </sect5>

  </sect4>

</sect3>
