<!DOCTYPE sect3 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect3 status="final" id="denoise_profiled">

  <title>Denoise&nbsp;&ndash; profiled</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>modules</primary>
    <secondary>denoise&nbsp;&ndash; profiled</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>denoise</primary>
    <secondary>profiled</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>noise removal</primary>
    <see>denoise</see>
  </indexterm>

  <sect4>

    <title>Overview</title>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              This module offers an easy to use and&nbsp;&ndash; at the same time&nbsp;&ndash;
              highly efficient denoise operation. Under the hood it applies (your choice of) a
              non-local means or edge-aware wavelet denoise algorithm with parameters
              specifically profiled for certain camera models and ISO settings.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/denoise_profiled.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

  </sect4>

  <sect4>

    <title>Usage</title>

    <para>
      The darktable team, with the help of many users, has measured noise profiles for various
      cameras. Differentiated by ISO settings we evaluated how the noise statistics develop with
      brightness for the three color channels. Our set of profiles covers well above 200 popular
      camera models from all major manufacturers.
    </para>

    <para>
      darktable stores noise profiles in an external json file. This file can be found in
      <filename>$DARKTABLE/share/darktable/noiseprofile.json</filename> where
      <filename>$DARKTABLE</filename> represents the darktable installation directory. The json
      format is quite straightforward and explained in depth in
      <ulink url="http://json.org/">json.org</ulink>. You can replace the default noise profiles
      by your own ones and specify that file on the command line when starting darktable. For
      more details see <xref linkend="darktable_commandline_parameters"/>. If you generate your
      own noise profiles don't forget to share your results with the darktable team!
    </para>

    <sect5>
      <title>profile</title>
      <para>
        Based on Exif data of your raw file, darktable will automatically determine the camera
        model and ISO setting. If found in its database, the corresponding noise profile will be
        used. If your image has an intermediate ISO value, the statistical properties will be
        interpolated between the two closest datasets in the database, and this interpolated
        setting will show up as the first line in the combo box. You also have the option to
        manually overwrite this selection to suit your personal preferences better. The top-most
        entry in the combo box brings you back to the profile darktable deems most suited.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>mode</title>
      <para>
        This module can eliminate noise with two different core algorithms. <quote>non-local
        means</quote> can tackle efficiently luma (lightness) noise whereas it is less efficient
        with chroma (color noise). <quote>wavelet</quote> is particularly efficient at eliminating
        chroma (color) noise but can also give good results for luma noise. It also lets you adjust
        the force of the denoising depending on the noise coarseness. If needed you can apply two
        instances of this module (see <xref linkend="multiple_instances"/>): one instance to tackle
        luma noise with blend mode <quote>lightness</quote> or <quote>HSV lightness</quote>, and
        another one to tackle chroma noise with blend mode <quote>color</quote> or <quote>HSV color
        </quote>. An example of the use of two instances with blending modes is available within
        the presets of this module. For more information on blend modes have a look at
        <xref linkend="blending_operators"/>.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>patch size</title>
      <para>
        This slider is only available if mode <quote>non-local means</quote> is selected. It
        controls the size of the patches being matched when deciding which pixels to average
        (see also <xref linkend="denoise_non_local_means"/>). Setting this to higher values can
        give more sharpness, especially on strong edges, but may also give more artifacts.
        Processing time will stay about the same.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>search radius</title>
      <para>
	       This slider is only available if mode <quote>non-local means</quote> is selected. It
         controls the how far from a pixel the algorithm will try to find similar patches. The
         processing time is hugely impacted by this parameter: it depends on the square of the
         parameter. A lower value will make execution faster, a higher value will make it slower.
         Increasing the value can give better results for very noisy images when coarse grain
         noise is visible.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>coarse/fine curves</title>
      <para>
        These curves are only available if mode <quote>wavelet</quote> is selected. The noise of
        an image is usually not only fine grain, but also more or less coarse grain. These curves
        allow to denoise more or less depending on the coarseness of the visible noise. The left
        of the curve will act on very coarse grain noise, while the right of the curve will act on
        very fine grain noise. Pushing up the curve will result in more smoothing, pulling it down
        will result in less smoothing. As an example, you can preserve very-fine grain noise by
        pulling down the rightest point of the curve until the minimum value. As another example,
        if you are tackling chroma noise with a blend mode, you can push up the right part of the
        curve, as colors are not supposed to change a lot on fine grain scales: this will help
        especially if you see some isolated pixel left undenoised.
        Considering R, G, and B curves, the best way to use them is to look at one of the channel
        using the channel mixer module in gray mode, denoise this particular channel, and then do
        the same for the other channels. This way, you can take into account the fact that some
        channel may be noisier than others into your denoising. Be aware that guessing which channel
        is noisy without actually seeing the channels individually is not straightforward and can be
        counterintuitive: a pixel which is completely red may not be caused by noise on the R channel,
        but actually by noise on B and G channels.
      </para>
    </sect5>


    <sect5>
      <title>strength</title>
      <para>
        This parameter is here to fine-tune the strength of the denoise effect. The default
        value has been chosen to maximize the peak signal to noise ratio. It's mostly a matter
        of taste if you prefer a rather low noise level at the costs of a higher loss of detail,
        or if you accept more remaining noise in order to have finer structures better preserved
        within your image.
      </para>
    </sect5>

  </sect4>

</sect3>
