<sect3 status="final" id="dithering">

  <title>Dithering</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>modules</primary>
    <secondary>dithering</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>dithering</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect4>

    <title>Overview</title>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              This module eliminates some of the typical banding artifacts which can occur, when
              darktable's internal 32-bit floating point data are transferred into a discrete
              8-bit or 16-bit integer output format for display or file export.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/dithering.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

    <para>
      Banding is a problem which can arise, when an image is downsampled into a lower bit-depth.
      Downsampling happens regularly, when darktable displays or exports the results of a
      pixelpipe. In order to avoid banding, you may activate this modules.
    </para>

  </sect4>

  <sect4>

    <title>Usage</title>

    <para>
      If you export images with a reduced width/height and want best dithering results, please
      make sure that you de-activate option <quote>do high quality resampling during
      export</quote> in <emphasis>core options</emphasis> (see <xref linkend="core_options"/>),
      else the final scaling step will counteract dithering.
    </para>

    <para>
      Viewing from some distance an image dithered into a very low bit depth (like
      <quote>floyd-steinberg 1-bit b&amp;w</quote>) will give the impression of a homogeneous
      grayscale image. We try to mimic this impression in darktable when you look at zoomed-out
      images in the center view, in the navigation window and for thumbnails. This is
      accomplished by dithering those images into a higher number of grayscale levels. Note that
      as a consequence the histogram - which is derived from the navigation window - will show
      this increased number of levels and is no longer a full match of the output image.
    </para>

    <sect5>
      <title>method</title>
      <para>
        This combobox sets the dithering method. Floyd-Steinberg error diffusion - with some
        typical output bit depths - and random noise dithering are both supported.
        Floyd-Steinberg systematically distributes quantization errors over neighboring pixels,
        whereas random dithering just adds some level of randomness to break sharp tonal value
        bands. The default setting is <quote>floyd-steinberg auto</quote>, which automatically
        adapts to the desired output format.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>damping</title>
      <para>
        This slider is only displayed if you choose method <quote>random</quote>. It controls
        the level of added random noise expressed as a damping factor in a 10*log
        <subscript>2</subscript>
        basis. A value of -80 is a good fit for 8-bit output formats and -160 for 16-bit ones.
      </para>
    </sect5>

  </sect4>

</sect3>
