<!DOCTYPE sect3 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect3 status="final" id="dithering">

  <title>Dithering</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>modules</primary>
    <secondary>dithering</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>dithering</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>banding</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>artifact mitigation</primary>
    <secondary>banding</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect4>

    <title>Overview</title>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              This module eliminates some of the typical banding artifacts which can occur, when
              darktable's internal 32-bit floating point data are transferred into a discrete
              8-bit or 16-bit integer output format for display or file export.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/dithering.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

    <para>
      Banding is a problem which can arise, when an image is downsampled into a lower bit-depth.
      Downsampling happens regularly, when darktable displays or exports the results of a
      pixelpipe. In order to avoid banding, you may activate this module. As dithering consumes
      significant resources this module is disabled by default.
    </para>

    <para>
      Although banding is not an inherent problem of any of darktable's modules, some operations
      may provoke it as they produce a lightness gradient in the image. To mitigate possible
      artifacts you should consider to activate dithering when using the
      <emphasis>vignette</emphasis> and the <emphasis>graduated density</emphasis> module,
      respectively (see <xref linkend="vignetting"/> and <xref linkend="graduated_density"/>).
      This is especially relevant for images with extended homogeneous areas like cloudless sky.
      Also when using a <emphasis>gradient mask</emphasis> (see
      <xref linkend="gradient_shape"/>) you should watch out for possible banding artifacts.
    </para>

  </sect4>

  <sect4>

    <title>Usage</title>

    <para>
      Viewing from some distance an image dithered into a very low bit depth (like
      <quote>floyd-steinberg 1-bit b&amp;w</quote>) will give the impression of a homogeneous
      grayscale image. We try to mimic this impression in darktable when you look at zoomed-out
      images in the center view, in the navigation window and for thumbnails. This is
      accomplished by dithering those images into a higher number of grayscale levels. Note that
      as a consequence the histogram&nbsp;&ndash; which is derived from the navigation
      window&nbsp;&ndash; will show this increased number of levels and is no longer a full
      match of the output image.
    </para>

    <sect5>
      <title>method</title>
      <para>
        This combobox sets the dithering method. Floyd-Steinberg error diffusion&nbsp;&ndash;
        with some typical output bit depths&nbsp;&ndash; and random noise dithering are both
        supported. Floyd-Steinberg systematically distributes quantization errors over
        neighboring pixels, whereas random dithering just adds some level of randomness to break
        sharp tonal value bands. The default setting is <quote>floyd-steinberg auto</quote>,
        which automatically adapts to the desired output format.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>damping</title>
      <para>
        This slider is only displayed if you choose method <quote>random</quote>. It controls
        the level of added random noise expressed as a damping factor in a 10*log
        <subscript>2</subscript>
        basis. A value of -80 is a good fit for 8-bit output formats and -160 for 16-bit ones.
      </para>
    </sect5>

  </sect4>

  <sect4>

    <title>Examples</title>

    <para>
      The visibility of the following examples depends on the quality of your monitor or the
      print quality.
    </para>

    <para>
      <informaltable frame="none">
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
          <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
          <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/dithering_ex1.png" scalefit="1" width="90%" align="center" />
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Banding artifact caused by vignetting (100% crop of a 8-bit PNG; effect heavily
                exaggerated by strong contrast enhancement).
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/dithering_ex2.png" scalefit="1" width="90%" align="center" />
              </entry>
              <entry>
                The same image area, processed as above but with activated Floyd-Steinberg
                dithering.
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </para>

  </sect4>

</sect3>
