<!DOCTYPE sect3 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect3 status="final" id="equalizer">

  <title>Equalizer</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>modules</primary>
    <secondary>equalizer</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>equalizer</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>denoise</primary>
    <secondary>equalizer</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>clarity</primary>
    <see>equalizer</see>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>artifact mitigation</primary>
    <secondary>halos</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect4>

    <title>Overview</title>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              This versatile module can be used to achieve a variety of effects, such as: bloom,
              denoising, clarity, and local contrast enhancement. It works in the wavelet domain
              and parameters can be tuned for each frequency band separately.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/atrous.png" scalefit="1" width="90%" align="right" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

  </sect4>

  <sect4>

    <title>Usage</title>

    <para>
      Each frequence band can be tweaked independently. In particular, you can adjust contrast
      boost and denoise threshold splines for both lightness and chromaticity, as well as the
      acuteness (<quote>edge</quote>) of the wavelet basis on each frequency scale.
    </para>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              Each spline can be dragged with a proportional edit approach; use the mouse wheel
              to adjust the radius in which your changes will have an effect. The transparent
              area indicates where you would drag the spline with the current mouse position and
              radius. The small little triangles on the x-axis can be moved to alter the
              x-position of the spline nodes.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/atrous-1.png" scalefit="1" width="90%" align="right" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              Drag the upper line (bright circles, here for the lightness channel) to affect
              local contrast. Pulling it up, as shown here, will result in a contrast boost for
              that frequency band. Higher frequencies, i.e. smaller details, are to the right of
              the grid. Pulling it down works, too.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/atrous-2.png" scalefit="1" width="90%" align="right" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              The bottom spline (black circles) is used to perform denoising. It adjusts the
              wavelet shrinkage threshold for each frequency band. Pull it up to see the effect.
              In this example, the noise which has been amplified by local contrast enhancement
              is removed.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/atrous-4.png" scalefit="1" width="90%" align="right" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              This screen shows the effect of the edge parameter. It is here pulled down to
              zero for all bands. This is effectively a regular à trous wavelet, without edge
              detection, and results in the characteristic halos around sharp edges in the
              image.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/atrous-5.png" scalefit="1" width="90%" align="right" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              This image is the other extreme. The wavelet basis now oversharpens, which results
              in ugly gradient reversals near the ridge of the rock.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/atrous-6.png" scalefit="1" width="90%" align="right" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

    <para>
      Note that the edge parameter only affects the wavelet basis, not the image directly.
      You will have to change some denoise/contrast boost parameters to see an effect following
      adjustments to the edge parameter.
    </para>

    <para>
      This module additionally has a <quote>mix</quote> slider below the spline GUI. Adjusting
      the slider will upscale or downscale the splines on the y-axis. The slider was added as a
      convenience tool to help you modify the strength of the effect. It is not a module
      parameter in itself; when you leave darkroom mode all changes will be consolidated into
      the spline curves.
    </para>

    <para>
      Have a look at the presets where there are a broad variety of examples that will provide a
      good starting point to gain an intuitive understanding of the controls. Among others there
      are two presets to enhance an image's <quote>clarity</quote>.
    </para>

  </sect4>

</sect3>
