<!DOCTYPE sect3 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect3 status="final" id="liquify">

  <title>Liquify</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>modules</primary>
    <secondary>liquify</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>liquify</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect4>

    <title>Overview</title>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              The liquify module offers a versatile way of moving pixels around by applying free
              style distortions to parts of the image. There are three tools to help doing that:
              points, lines, and curves.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/liquify.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

    <para>
      Each of liquify's tools is based on nodes. A point is given by a single node, a line or a
      curve consist of a set of nodes defining the path.
    </para>

    <para>
      There is a limit of 100 nodes in a single liquify instance. For more distortions one can
      use multiple instances of the liquify module. However, take into account that the liquify
      module requires a lot of computing resources.
    </para>

  </sect4>

  <sect4>

    <title>Usage</title>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              The basic elements of all tools in liquify are nodes.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/liquify_ex1.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

    <para>
      You can drag the central point of a node to move the node around. The radius describes the
      area of the applied effect: the distortion occurs only inside this radius. To change the
      radius drag the handle at the circumference. A strength vector starting from the center
      describes the direction of the distortion, and its strength is depicted by the length of
      the vector. You change the vector by dragging its arrowhead.
    </para>

    <sect5>
      <title>warps and nodes count</title>
      <para>
        This information field displays the number of warps (individual distortion object)
        and nodes currently used.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>point tool</title>
      <para>
        Click the
        <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_liquify_point;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center" />
        icon to activate the point tool and left-click on the image to place it.
      </para>
      <para>
        A point is formed by a single node. In a point the strength vector has three different
        modes which are toggled using ctrl-click over the arrowhead of the strength vector:
        <informaltable frame="none" width="80%">
          <tgroup cols="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
            <colspec colwidth='2*'/>
            <colspec colwidth='4*'/>
            <colspec colwidth='4*'/>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <emphasis>linear</emphasis>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  The linear mode produces a linear distortion inside the circle. Starting from
                  the opposite side of the strength vector and following the strength vector's
                  direction. This is the default mode.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/liquify_ex1.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <emphasis>radial growing</emphasis>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  In this mode the strength vector's effect is radial, starting with a strength
                  of 0% in the center and growing when going away from the center. This mode is
                  depicted by an additional circle with the arrow pointing outwards.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/liquify_ex4.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <emphasis>radial shrinking</emphasis>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  In this mode the strength vector's effect is radial, starting with a strength
                  of 100% in the center and shrinking when going away from the center. This mode
                  is depicted by an additional circle with the arrow pointing inwards.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/liquify_ex3.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
                </entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
      </para>
      <para>
        Note that the strength by default varies linearly from 0% to 100% between the center and
        the radius of the control point. It is possible to modify the feathering effect by
        clicking on the center of the circle:
        <informaltable frame="none" width="80%">
          <tgroup cols="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
            <colspec colwidth='2*'/>
            <colspec colwidth='4*'/>
            <colspec colwidth='4*'/>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <emphasis>default</emphasis>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  Linear from the center to the radius.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/liquify_ex1.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <emphasis>feathered</emphasis>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  Two control circles are displayed and can be modified independently to feather
                  the strength of the effect. Note that clicking again the center of the circle
                  only hides the feathering controls but does not return to the default.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/liquify_ex2.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
                </entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
      </para>
      <para>
        A point can be removed by right-clicking on the center.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>line tool</title>
      <para>
        Click the
        <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_liquify_line;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center" />
        icon to activate the line tool and left-click on the image to place the first point,
        move and left-click to place another point and start forming the path. To end the line
        just right-click anywhere.
      </para>
      <para>
        <informaltable frame="none" width="80%">
          <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
            <colspec colwidth='6*'/>
            <colspec colwidth='4*'/>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  A line is a set of points. The points are linked together, the effect is
                  interpolated by a set of strength vectors.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/liquify_ex5.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
                </entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
      </para>
      <para>
        It is possible to add a control point on a line by ctrl-click on a segment. You may
        remove a control point from a line by ctrl-right- click on the node center.
      </para>
      <para>
        A right-click on a segment will remove the shape completely.
      </para>
      <para>
        A ctrl-alt-click on a segment will change it to a curve segment.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>curve tool</title>
      <para>
        Click the
        <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_liquify_curve;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center" />
        icon to activate the curve tool and left-click on the image to place the first point,
        move and left-click to place another point and start forming the path. To end the line
        just right-click anywhere.
      </para>
      <para>
        <informaltable frame="none" width="80%">
          <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
            <colspec colwidth='6*'/>
            <colspec colwidth='4*'/>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  A curve is a set of points. The points are linked together, the effect is
                  interpolated as a bezier curve by a set of strength vectors.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/liquify_ex6.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
                </entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
      </para>
      <para>
        It is possible to add a control point on a curve by ctrl-click on a segment. You may
        remove a control point from a curve by ctrl-right- click on the node center.
      </para>
      <para>
        A right-click on a segment will remove the shape completely.
      </para>
      <para>
        A ctrl-alt-click on a segment will change it to a line segment.
      </para>
      <para>
        It is possible to change the way the points of the curve are linked together by using
        ctrl-click on the center. There are four modes which correspond to different ways of
        handling the steepness of the bezier curve by control handles:
        <informaltable frame="none" width="80%">
          <tgroup cols="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
            <colspec colwidth='4*'/>
            <colspec colwidth='6*'/>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <emphasis>autosmooth</emphasis>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  This is the default mode in which the control handles are not displayed as
                  they are automatically computed to always give a smooth curve.
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <emphasis>cusp</emphasis>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  Control handles can be moved independently. This mode is depicted by a
                  triangle symbol in the node center.
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <emphasis>smooth</emphasis>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  Control handles are always giving a smooth curve. This mode is depicted by a
                  diamond symbol in the node center.
                </entry>
                <entry></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <emphasis>symmetrical</emphasis>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  Control handles are always moved together. This mode is depicted by a square
                  symbol in the node center.
                </entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>node edit tool</title>
      <para>
        Clicking the
        <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_liquify_edit;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center" />
        icon activates or deactivates the node edit tool displaying all defined distortion
        objects and their controls. Alternatively you can at any time right-click on the image
        for the same effect.
      </para>
    </sect5>

  </sect4>

</sect3>
