<!DOCTYPE sect3 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect3 status="final" id="base_curve">

  <title>Base curve</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>modules</primary>
    <secondary>base curve</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>base curve</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>exposure fusion</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>exposure bias</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect4>

    <title>Overview</title>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              Camera sensors provide data in linear RGB format, the original image appears flat
              and dull. That's the reason why camera manufacturers apply their characteristic
              base curves to the raw data when they generate in-camera JPEG images with better
              colors and contrast.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/basecurve.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

  </sect4>

  <sect4>

    <title>Usage</title>

    <para>
      darktable comes with base curve presets that mimic the curves of various manufacturers.
      These are automatically applied to raw images according to the manufacturer ID found in
      Exif data. For several camera models darktable comes with base curves adapted for that
      specific model. A configuration option in the core preferences dialog (see
      <xref linkend="core_options"/>) defines whether darktable by default should apply the
      per-camera base curve or the manufacturer one.
    </para>

    <para>
      You can adjust an existing base curve or create a new one. The base curve is defined by
      two or more nodes. You can move any node to modify the curve. You can also create
      additional nodes by <emphasis>clicking</emphasis> on a curve segment between two nodes.
      With <emphasis>ctrl-click</emphasis> you generate a new node at the x-location of the
      mouse pointer and the corresponding y-location of the current curve&nbsp;&ndash; this adds
      a node without risking to accidentally modify the curve. In order to remove a node move it
      outside of the widget area.
    </para>

    <para>
      Tip: If you intend to take full manual control of the tonal values with the <emphasis>tone
      curve</emphasis> module or the <emphasis>zone system</emphasis> module (see
      <xref linkend="tone_curve"/> and <xref linkend="zone_system"/>) it may be easier to leave
      the image in linear RGB. Disable the <emphasis>base curve</emphasis> module in this case.
    </para>

    <sect5>
      <title>scale</title>
      <para>
        This combobox toggles between <quote>linear</quote> and <quote>logarithmic</quote> view.
        In the double logarithmic view more space is given to the lower values allowing a more
        fine-grained adjustment of the shadows.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>fusion</title>
      <para>
        This control triggers the
        <ulink url="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Exposure_Fusion"><emphasis>exposure
        fusion</emphasis></ulink> feature. You can choose to merge the image with one or two
        copies of itself after applying the current base curve and boosting its exposure by a
        selectable number of ev units. The resulting image is thus a combination of two or three
        different exposures of the original image. Use this to compress dynamic range for
        extremely underexposed images or for true HDR input. For best results, use the exposure
        module (see <xref linkend="exposure"/>) to apply a suitable adjustment for correctly
        exposed highlights.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>exposure shift</title>
      <para>
        This slider is only visible if the <emphasis>exposure fusion</emphasis> feature is
        activated. It allows you to set the exposure difference between the merged images in ev
        units (default 1).
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>exposure bias</title>
      <para>
        This slider is only visible if the <emphasis>exposure fusion</emphasis> feature is
        activated. It allows you to chose how the multiple exposures are computed. With a bias
        of 1 (the default), the image is fused with overexposed copies of itself. With a bias of
        -1, it is fused with underexposed copies. A bias of 0 tries to preserve the overall
        lightness of the image by combining both over and under-exposed copies of the image.
      </para>
    </sect5>

  </sect4>

</sect3>
