<sect2 status="final"><title>Crop and rotate</title>
	<sect3 status="final"><title>Overview</title>
		<informaltable frame="none"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
				<colspec colwidth='70%'/>
				<colspec colwidth='30%'/>
				<tbody>
					<row>						
						<entry>This module is used to crop, rotate and correct perspective of your image. 
							It also includes many helpful guidelines that assist you using the tools.
						</entry>
						<entry>
							<graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/cropandrotate.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
						</entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</informaltable>
	</sect3>

	<sect3 status="draft"><title>Usage</title>

		<para>First off, select what aspect ratio you want and size the crop bounds by dragging border and corner handles.
			Use <emphasis>ctrl-x</emphasis> or the button right to the aspect box, to swap between portrait and landscape of the cropping rectangle.
			You can move around the crop rectangle by holding down left mouse button and move around.
			When you are done and want to execute the crop, hit enter key or double click in the crop rectangle.
			<emphasis>TIP:hit "backspace" to reset the crop rectangle.</emphasis>
		</para>

		<sect4><title>Flip image</title>
			<para>Use these toggle buttons to flip image horizontally and vertically.</para>
		</sect4>
		<sect4><title>Angle</title>
			<para>This is the rotation angle to correct, for example, a non-horizontal horizon.
			You can either type a numerical value or use your mouse directly on the image.
			To use your mouse, right-click, hold it down and draw a line along the horizon ; the image is then rotated so the line you drew matches the horizontal axis.
			</para>
		</sect4>
		<sect4><title>Keystone h and v</title>
			<para>This tool is used to correct any perspective distortions in your image. Useful when you shoot 
				an high building from ground, aiming upwards with camera with short focal length for example.
			</para>
		</sect4>
		
		<sect4><title>Aspect</title>
			<para>Here you can change what aspect ratio you want to have on the result, thus constraining the ability to drag and crop 
				rectangle out of the aspect ratio of your choice..
			</para>
			<para>
				<informaltable frame="none"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
					<colspec colwidth='3cm'/>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry><emphasis>free</emphasis></entry><entry>free forming the rectangle without any ratio restrictions</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><emphasis>image</emphasis></entry><entry>this option constrains the ratio to be equal to image ratio</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><emphasis>golden cut</emphasis></entry><entry>this option constrains the ratio to be equal the golden number</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><emphasis>square</emphasis></entry><entry>this option constrains the ratio to be 1</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup></informaltable>
			</para>
		</sect4>
		<sect4><title>Guides</title>
			<para>Many self-explaining guides are available to help you compose your image.
			</para>
		</sect4>
	</sect3>
</sect2>
