<!DOCTYPE sect3 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect3 status="final" id="crop_and_rotate">

  <title>Crop and rotate</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>modules</primary>
    <secondary>crop and rotate</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>crop and rotate</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>cropping an image</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>rotating an image</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect4>

    <title>Overview</title>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              This module is used to crop, rotate and correct perspective distortions of your
              image. You can overlay your image with various helpful guidelines that assist you
              using the tools.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/crop_and_rotate.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

    <para>
      Some of the tools of this module, namely adjustment of angle and corrections of
      perspective distortion, will require the original image data to be interpolated. For best
      sharpness results set <quote>lanczos3</quote> as pixel interpolator in <emphasis>core
      options</emphasis> (see <xref linkend="core_options"/>).
    </para>

  </sect4>

  <sect4>

    <title>Usage</title>

    <para>
      Whenever the user interface of this module is in focus, you will see the full uncropped
      image overlaid with handles and guiding lines.
    </para>

    <para>
      First off, select what aspect ratio you want and size the crop boundaries by dragging
      border and corner handles. Use the button right of the aspect box, to swap between
      portrait and landscape mode. You can move around the crop rectangle by holding down left
      mouse button and move around. When you are done and want to execute the crop, just give
      focus to another module or double-click into the image base. You can at any time change
      your crop area by just revisiting this module.
    </para>

    <sect5>
      <title>flip</title>
      <para>
        This tool is used to flip the image on the horizontal,vertical or both axis.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>angle</title>
      <para>
        This tool corrects the rotation angle helping you level an image. You can either set a
        numerical value or use your mouse directly on the image. To use your mouse, right-click,
        hold it down and draw a line along a suited horizontal or vertical feature; as soon as
        you release the mouse button the image is rotated so the line you drew matches the
        horizontal/vertical axis.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>keystone</title>
      <para>
        This tool is used to correct perspective distortions in your image. Useful for example
        when you shoot a high building from ground with a short focal length, aiming upwards
        with your camera. The combobox lets you select the type of correction you want to use :
      </para>
      <para>
        <informaltable frame="none">
          <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
            <colspec colwidth='3cm'/>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <emphasis>vertical</emphasis>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  if you want to limit the correction to vertical lines
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <emphasis>horizontal</emphasis>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  limit the correction to horizontal lines
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <emphasis>free</emphasis>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  if you want to correct horizontal and vertical lines
                </entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
      </para>
      <para>
        <informaltable frame="none">
          <tgroup cols="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
            <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
            <colspec colwidth="2*"/>
            <colspec colwidth="2*"/>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    Depending on the selected correction type you will see two or four straight
                    adjustment lines overlaid to your image. Two red circles on every line let
                    you modify the line positions with your mouse. Each line additionally
                    carries a <quote>symmetry</quote> button. If activated (and highlighted in
                    red) all movements of the affected line will be mirrored by the opposite
                    line.
                  </para>

                  <para>
                    In order to correct perspective distortions, you need to find suitable
                    horizontal and/or vertical features in your image and align the adjustment
                    lines with them. When done, press the <quote>OK</quote> button, which is
                    located close to the center of your image. The image will be corrected
                    immediately. You can at any time come back and refine your corrections by
                    selecting <quote>correction applied</quote> in combobox keystone.
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/crop_and_rotate_k_set.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/crop_and_rotate_k_applied.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
                </entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>automatic cropping</title>
      <para>
        Use this options to avoid black edges on the image borders. Useful when you rotate the
        image.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>aspect</title>
      <para>
        Here you can change what aspect ratio you want to have on the result, thus constraining
        the proportion of width and height of the crop rectangle to the aspect ratio of your
        choice. Many common numerical ratios are pre-defined. A few special aspect ratios
        deserve explanation:
      </para>
      <para>
        <informaltable frame="none">
          <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
            <colspec colwidth='3cm'/>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <emphasis>free</emphasis>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  free forming the rectangle without any ratio restrictions
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <emphasis>image</emphasis>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  this option constrains the ratio to be equal to image ratio
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <emphasis>golden cut</emphasis>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  this option constrains the ratio to be equal the golden number
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <emphasis>square</emphasis>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  this option constrains the ratio to be 1
                </entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
      </para>
      <para>
        You can also select any other ratio after opening the combobox and typing it in the form
        of <quote>x:y</quote>. If you want a certain aspect ratio to be added to the pre-defined
        ones you can do so by including a line of the form
      </para>
      <para>
<programlisting>plugins/darkroom/clipping/extra_aspect_ratios/foo=x:y
</programlisting>
      </para>
      <para>
        into darktable's configuration file
        <filename>$HOME/.config/darktable/darktablerc</filename>. Here <quote>foo</quote>
        defines the name of the new aspect ratio and <quote>x</quote> and <quote>y</quote> the
        corresponding numerical values.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>guides</title>
      <para>
        Many self-explaining guides are available to help you compose your image.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>guides flip</title>
      <para>
        In case the chosen guidelines are not symmetrical relative to the image frame, you can
        flip them on the horizontal,vertical or both axis.
      </para>
    </sect5>

  </sect4>

  <sect4>

    <title>Examples</title>

    <para>
      <informaltable frame="none">
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
          <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
          <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/crop_and_rotate_ex1.png" scalefit="1" width="90%" align="center" />
              </entry>
              <entry>
                A cropped image in center view when module crop and rotate is in focus. The
                cropped area is visible as well as some guiding lines.
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </para>

  </sect4>

</sect3>
