<sect3 status="final" id="demosaic">

  <title>Demosaic</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>modules</primary>
    <secondary>demosaic</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>demosaic</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect4>

    <title>Overview</title>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              This module allows you to control how the demosaic is processed.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/demosaic.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

  </sect4>

  <sect4>

    <title>Usage</title>

    <para>
      Demosaic is an essential step of any raw image development process.
    </para>

    <para>
      A detailed description would be beyond the scope of this manual. In a nutshell, the sensor
      cells of a digital camera are only able to record different levels of lightness, not
      different color. In order to get a color image, each cell is covered by a color filter,
      either in red, green or blue. Due to the color sensitivity of the human vision, there are
      two times more green cells than red or blue. Filters are arranged in a certain mosaic,
      called Bayer pattern. Therefore each pixel of your image originally only has information
      about one color channel. Demosaic reconstructs the missing color channels by interpolation
      with data of the neighboring pixels. For further reading see the Wikipedia article on the
      <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bayer_filter">Bayer filter</ulink>.
    </para>

    <para>
      As interpolation is prone to produce artifacts, various different demosaic algorithms have
      been developed in the past. Artifacts would typically be visible as moiré-like patterns
      when you strongly zoom into your image. Currently darktable supports PPG and AMAZE. Both
      algorithms produce high quality output with a low tendency to artifacts. AMAZE is reported
      to sometimes give slightly better results. However, as AMAZE is significantly slower,
      darktable uses PPG as a default.
    </para>

    <para>
      Some further parameters of this module can activate additional averaging and smoothing
      steps. They might help to reduce remaining artifacts in special cases.
    </para>

    <para>
      Demosaic is always applied when exporting images. Demosaic is done on monitor display only
      when zoom is greater than 50% or when the according preference setting <quote>demosaicing
      for zoomed out darkroom mode</quote> (see <xref linkend="core_options"/>) is set
      accordingly. Else color channels are taken from neighboring pixels without an expensive
      interpolation.
    </para>

    <sect5>
      <title>method</title>
      <para>
        Set the demosaic method. darktable currently supports PPG and AMAZE.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>edge threshold</title>
      <para>
        Set the threshold for an additional median pass. Defaults to <quote>0</quote> which
        disables median filtering.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>color smoothing</title>
      <para>
        Activates a number of additional color smoothing passes. Defaults to <quote>off</quote>.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>match greens</title>
      <para>
        In some cameras the green filters have slightly varying properties. This parameter adds
        an additional equalization step to suppress artifacts. Available options are
        <quote>disabled</quote>, <quote>local average</quote>, <quote>full average</quote> and
        <quote>full and local average</quote>.
      </para>
    </sect5>

  </sect4>

</sect3>
