<!DOCTYPE sect3 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect3 status="final" id="demosaic">

  <title>Demosaic</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>modules</primary>
    <secondary>demosaic</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>demosaic</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect4>

    <title>Overview</title>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              This module allows you to control how the demosaic is processed.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/demosaic.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

  </sect4>

  <sect4>

    <title>Usage</title>

    <para>
      Demosaic is an essential step of any raw image development process.
    </para>

    <para>
      A detailed description would be beyond the scope of this manual. In a nutshell, the sensor
      cells of a digital camera are only able to record different levels of lightness, not
      different color. In order to get a color image, each cell is covered by a color filter,
      either in red, green or blue. Due to the color sensitivity of the human vision, there are
      two times more green cells than red or blue. Filters are arranged in a certain mosaic,
      called Bayer pattern. Therefore each pixel of your image originally only has information
      about one color channel. Demosaic reconstructs the missing color channels by interpolation
      with data of the neighboring pixels. For further reading see the Wikipedia article on the
      <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bayer_filter">Bayer filter</ulink>.
    </para>

    <para>
      As interpolation is prone to produce artifacts, various different demosaic algorithms have
      been developed in the past. Artifacts would typically be visible as moir&eacute;-like
      patterns when you strongly zoom into your image. Currently darktable supports PPG, AMAZE,
      and VNG4. All these algorithms produce high quality output with a low tendency to
      artifacts. AMAZE is reported to sometimes give slightly better results. However, as AMAZE
      is significantly slower, darktable uses PPG as a default. VNG4 produces the softest
      results of the three algorithms, but if you see "maze" artifacts, try VNG4 to eliminate
      them.
    </para>

    <para>
      There are a few cameras whose sensors do not use a Bayer filter. Cameras with an "X-Trans"
      sensor have their own set of demosaicing algorithms. The default algorithm for X-Trans
      sensors is Markesteijn 1-pass, which produces fairly good results. For a bit better
      quality (at the cost of much slower processing), choose Markesteijn 3-pass. Though VNG
      demosaic is faster than Markesteijn 1-pass on certain computers, it is more prone to
      demosaicing artifacts.
    </para>

    <para>
      Additionally, darktable supports a special demosaicing algorithm&nbsp;&ndash; passthrough
      (monochrome). It is not a general-purpose algorithm that is useful for all the images. It
      is only useful for cameras with the color filter array physically removed from the sensor,
      e.g. physically scratched off. Normally, demosaic reconstructs the missing color channels
      by interpolation with data of the neighboring pixels. But since the color filter array is
      not present, there is nothing to interpolate, so this algorithm simply sets all the color
      channels to the same value, which results in pixels being gray, thus producing a
      monochrome image. This method guarantees that there are no interpolation artifacts that
      would otherwise be present should one of the standard demosaicing algorithm be used.
    </para>

    <para>
      Some further parameters of this module can activate additional averaging and smoothing
      steps. They might help to reduce remaining artifacts in special cases.
    </para>

    <para>
      Demosaic is always applied when exporting images. Demosaic is done on monitor display only
      when zoom is greater than 50% or when the according preference setting <quote>demosaicing
      for zoomed out darkroom mode</quote> (see <xref linkend="core_options"/>) is set
      accordingly. Else color channels are taken from neighboring pixels without an expensive
      interpolation.
    </para>

    <sect5>
      <title>method</title>
      <para>
        Set the demosaic method. darktable currently supports PPG, AMAZE, and VNG4 for Bayer
        sensors. For X-Trans sensors darktable supports VNG, Markesteijn 1-pass, and Markesteijn
        3-pass.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>edge threshold</title>
      <para>
        Set the threshold for an additional median pass. Defaults to <quote>0</quote> which
        disables median filtering. This option is not shown for X-Trans sensors.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>color smoothing</title>
      <para>
        Activates a number of additional color smoothing passes. Defaults to <quote>off</quote>.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>match greens</title>
      <para>
        In some cameras the green filters have slightly varying properties. This parameter adds
        an additional equalization step to suppress artifacts. Available options are
        <quote>disabled</quote>, <quote>local average</quote>, <quote>full average</quote> and
        <quote>full and local average</quote>. This option is not shown for X-Trans sensors.
      </para>
    </sect5>

  </sect4>

</sect3>
