<!DOCTYPE sect3 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect3 status="final" id="exposure">

  <title>Exposure</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>modules</primary>
    <secondary>exposure</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>exposure</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>time-lapse photography</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>deflicker</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect4>

    <title>Overview</title>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              This module is used to tweak the exposure. It is directly linked to the histogram
              panel. If you correct exposure graphically, using the <emphasis>histogram
              </emphasis> (see <xref linkend="histogram"/>), you automatically activate the
              exposure module. The histogram simply acts as a view for the exposure module.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/exposure.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

    <para>
      You can activate multiple instances of this module each with different parameters acting
      on different parts of the image which you select by a drawn mask (see
      <xref linkend="multiple_instances"/> and <xref linkend="drawn_mask"/>). The histogram is
      always linked to the last instance in pixelpipe.
    </para>

  </sect4>

  <sect4>

    <title>Usage</title>

    <para>
      This module is responsible for one of the most basic steps in each raw image development.
      An exposure adjustment value allows you&nbsp;&ndash; within certain limits&nbsp;&ndash; to
      correct for under- or overexposure. A shift by 1EV is equivalent to a change of exposure
      time by a factor of 2.
    </para>

    <para>
      Positive exposure corrections will make the image brighter. As a side effect noise level
      gets higher. Depending on the basic noise level of your camera and the ISO value of your
      image, positive exposure compensations with up to 1EV or 2EV still give reasonable
      results.
    </para>

    <para>
      Negative exposure corrections will make the image darker. Given the nature of digital
      images this can not correct for fully blown out highlights but allows to reconstruct data
      in case that only some of the RGB channels are clipped (see also
      <xref linkend="highlight_reconstruction"/>).
    </para>

    <para>
      A black level adjustment is a basic tool to increase contrast and pop of an image. The
      value defines at what threshold dark gray values are cut off to pure black. Use with care
      as the clipped values can not be recovered in other modules further down the pixelpipe.
      Please also have a look at the <emphasis>tone curve</emphasis> module (see
      <xref linkend="tone_curve"/>) and the <emphasis>levels</emphasis> module (see
      <xref linkend="levels"/>) which can produce similar results with less side effects as they
      come later in pixelpipe.
    </para>

    <para>
      The exposure module has two modes of operation.
    </para>

    <para>
      In <quote>manual</quote> mode you directly define the value for exposure correction that
      you want to apply to your image.
    </para>

    <para>
      In <quote>automatic</quote> mode darktable analyses the histogram of your image. You
      select a reference point within the histogram as a <emphasis>percentile</emphasis> and
      define a <emphasis>target level</emphasis>&nbsp;&ndash; darktable automatically calculates
      the exposure compensation that is needed to shift the selected position to that target
      value. The computed exposure compensation value is displayed in the module's GUI for your
      information.
    </para>

    <para>
      The <quote>automatic</quote> mode has a black level adjustment that works as in manual
      mode.
    </para>

    <para>
      Automatic adjustment is only available for raw images. A typical use case is deflickering
      of <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Time-lapse_photography"><emphasis>time-lapse
      photographs</emphasis></ulink>. You apply an automatic exposure correction with the same
      set of parameters to all images of the series&nbsp;&ndash; differences in lighting get
      compensated so that the final video sequence does not show any flickering.
    </para>

    <sect5>
      <title>mode</title>
      <para>
        Defines the mode of operation. Defaults to <quote>manual</quote>.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>black</title>
      <para>
        Adjust the black level in both <quote>manual</quote> and <quote>automatic</quote> mode.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>exposure</title>
      <para>
        Adjust the exposure correction [EV] (only available in <quote>manual</quote> mode).
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>clipping threshold</title>
      <para>
        darktable can calculate correct black level and exposure values for your image based on
        the content of a rectangular area. The adjustment slider lets you define what percentage
        of bright values are to be clipped out in the calculation. Pressing the
        <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_module_picker;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center" />
        icon starts the calculation and lets you draw a rectangular area of your choice using
        your mouse. This feature is only available in <quote>manual</quote> mode.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>percentile</title>
      <para>
        Defines a location in the histogram for automatic exposure correction. A percentile of
        50% denotes a position in the histogram where 50% of pixel values are below and 50% of
        pixel values are above. For more details see
        <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Percentile"><emphasis>percentile</emphasis>
        </ulink>. Only available in <quote>automatic</quote> mode.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>target level</title>
      <para>
        Defines the target level for automatic exposure correction in terms of [EV] relative to
        the white point of the camera. The white point is camera specific and defines the
        highest lightness value that the camera sensor can detect. Only available in
        <quote>automatic</quote> mode.
      </para>
    </sect5>

  </sect4>

</sect3>
