<sect3 status="final" id="exposure">

  <title>Exposure</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>modules</primary>
    <secondary>exposure</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>exposure</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect4>

    <title>Overview</title>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              This module is used to tweak the exposure. It is directly linked to the histogram
              panel. Indeed, if you correct exposure graphically, using the <emphasis>histogram
              </emphasis> (see <xref linkend="histogram"/>), you automatically activate the
              exposure module. The histogram simply acts as a view for the exposure module.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/exposure.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

    <para>
      You can activate multiple instances of this module each with different parameters acting
      on different parts of the image which you select by a drawn mask (see
      <xref linkend="multiple_instances"/> and <xref linkend="drawn_mask"/>). The histogram is
      always linked to the lowest instance in pixelpipe.
    </para>

  </sect4>

  <sect4>

    <title>Usage</title>

    <para>
      This module is responsible for one of the most basic steps in each raw image development.
      An exposure adjustment value allows you - within certain limits - to correct for under- or
      overexposure. A shift by 1EV is equivalent to a change of exposure time by a factor of 2.
    </para>

    <para>
      Positive exposure corrections will make the image brighter. As a side effect noise level
      gets higher. Depending on the basic noise level of your camera and the ISO value of your
      image, positive exposure compensations with up to 1EV or 2EV still give reasonable
      results.
    </para>

    <para>
      Negative exposure corrections will make the image darker. Given the nature of digital
      images this can not correct for blown out highlights (see also
      <xref linkend="highlight_reconstruction"/>).
    </para>

    <para>
      A black level adjustment is a basic tool to increase contrast and pop of an image. The
      value defines at what threshold dark gray values are cut off to pure black. Use with care
      as the clipped values can not be recovered in other modules further down the pixelpipe.
      Please also have a look at the <emphasis>tone curve</emphasis> module (see
      <xref linkend="tone_curve"/>) and the <emphasis>levels</emphasis> module (see
      <xref linkend="levels"/>) which can produce similar results with less side effects as they
      come later in pixelpipe.
    </para>

    <sect5>
      <title>black</title>
      <para>
        Adjust the black level.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>exposure</title>
      <para>
        Adjust the exposure correction [EV].
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>auto</title>
      <para>
        Calculate a correct exposition for the rectangular view appearing in the centre of the
        image. You can draw your own selection using your mouse. An adjustment slider right to
        the auto exposure checkbox lets you define what percentage of bright values are to be
        clipped out in the calculation.
      </para>
    </sect5>

  </sect4>

</sect3>
