<!DOCTYPE sect3 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect3 status="final" id="negadoctor">

  <title>Nega-Doctor</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>modules</primary>
    <secondary>nega-doctor</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>nega-doctor</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect4>

    <title>Overview</title>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              Negadoctor is a module designed to help you process a scanned film negative.
              Whether the negative was scanned on a film scanner, held up to a white
              light source like a computer screen, or back lit with off-camera flash
              is irrelevant.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic
                  fileref="darkroom/modules/images/negadoctor_film.png"
                  scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

  </sect4>

  <sect4>

    <title>Preparation</title>

    <para>
      In case your film is scanned with a DSLR, you will need to
      correct the color deviations of the DSLR first, in the workflow
      and in the pipeline, to ensure maximal reliability of the film
      color corrections. That is :
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>
	white-balancing against the light source used to scan,
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
	applying the standard matrice in the color input profile,
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
	ensuring exposure is set to use a maximum range
	of the histogram without clipping.
      </para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>
      You are advised to take a profiling picture of the light source
      alone, with no film mounted, to sample the white balance. That
      sampled value can then be copy-pasted to all your images
      processed with the same setting.
    </para>

    <para>
      The film should be scanned such that the frame is visible, so
      you have a visible sample of the unexposed film base (substrate
      ?) that you can use to set the Dmin. If your film holder
      completely hides this mask, you are advised to take a profiling
      picture of the shifted film in the holder, sample the Dmin once
      for the film stripe on that profiling picture, and copy-paste
      the settings for all other edits.
    </para>

    <para>
      The modules <quote>filmic</quote>, <quote>filmic RGB</quote> and
      <quote>base curve</quote> should better be disabled when working
      with scanned film.
    </para>

    <para>
      The working color profile, for darktable's pipeline, should be
      set to Rec2020 linear or to a profile that actually represents
      your film emulsion color space. See such ICC profiles provided
      here :
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>
	<ulink url="https://discuss.pixls.us/t/any-interest-in-a-film-negative-feature-in-rt/12569/177">
	  <emphasis>Pixls.us Ref Msg 1</emphasis>
	</ulink>
    </para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>
	<ulink url="https://discuss.pixls.us/t/input-color-profile-to-use-for-negatives/20271/13">
	  <emphasis>Pixls.us Ref Msg 2</emphasis>
	</ulink>
    </para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

  </sect4>

  <sect4>

    <title>Usage</title>

    <para>
      It is strongly recommended that you set the parameters following
      the order that the GUI presents (from top to bottom, tabs from
      left to right) since the next settings depend on the previous.
    </para>

    <para>
      The first option is the drop-down menu, Film Stock. Here, you
      choose whether the negative you are working with is color, or
      black and white. Selecting the black and white option simply
      removes sliders in the module which pertain to color
      information. This tidies up the interface by removing controls
      you don't need.
    </para>

    <para>
      Next are 3 tabs: <quote>Film Properties</quote>,
      <quote>Corrections</quote>, and <quote>Print Properties</quote>.
    </para>

    <sect5>
      <title>film properties</title>
      <para>
        The <quote>Colour of the film base</quote> section allows you
        to sample an area from your scan which comprises the base film
        stock. This is the area just outside of the image (IE. an
        unexposed part of the film).  When working with black and
        white negatives, you can leave this at its default value of
        white.  If working on color film, click the eye dropper to the
        right of the color bar. This will create a bounding box which
        covers about 98% of your image. Then, left-click and drag
        across an area of your negative which only has unexposed film
        stock in it.  This will automatically calculate values for the
        <quote>D min red component</quote>, <quote>D min green
        component</quote> and <quote>D min blue component</quote>
        sliders. At this point, it is likely that your image will
        still look too dark.
      </para>

      <para>
        Next we move to the D Max slider in the <quote>Dynamic range
        of the film</quote> section. This slider effectively sets our
        white point. Dragging this to the left will make the neg
        brighter. Dragging to the right will make the neg darker. If
        adjusting manually, it's a good idea to watch your histogram
        and ensure that you don't push the highlights into clipping
        (where the histogram is pushed off the right hand side of the
        graph).  Again, you can use the eye dropper (on the right) to
        allow Negadoctor to automatically calculate this value to
        ensure maximal use of the histogram without clipping. If using
        the eye dropper, left-click and drag to draw a rectangle
        across only the exposed parts of the neg. Don't include the
        unexposed film stock in the rectangle, as this will skew the
        result.
      </para>

      <para>
        Then, the <quote>Scan exposure bias</quote> slider under <quote>Scanner exposure
        settings</quote> allows us to set a black point. Dragging this to the
        left will make the neg brighter. Dragging to the right will
        make the neg darker. If adjusting manually, it's a good idea
        to watch your histogram and ensure that you don't push the
        shadows into clipping (where the histogram is pushed off the
        left hand side of the graph).  Again, you can use the eye
        dropper to allow Negadoctor to automatically calculate any
        needed offset.
      </para>

      <para>
        By now, your neg should be looking pretty close to what you
        were expecting to see. However, for color negs, you might need
        an extra step.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>corrections</title>

      <para>
        <informaltable frame="none">
          <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
            <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
            <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  Moving to the <quote>Corrections</quote> tab, we
                  have sliders which allow for corrections within both
                  the shadows regions, and the highlight
                  regions. Again, there are eye droppers to allow for
                  automatic definition of shadow color casts, and/or
                  highlight color casts.  For shadows, select the eye
                  dropper, and left-click and drag a large rectangle
                  across the majority of your image. Negadoctor will
                  calculate appropriate values, and these will be
                  displayed under <quote>shadows red offset</quote>,
                  <quote>shadows green offset</quote>,and
                  <quote>shadows blue offset</quote>.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <graphic
                      fileref="darkroom/modules/images/negadoctor_correction.png"
                      scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
                </entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
      </para>

      <para>
	This settings should not be needed for most well-preserved
	negatives and will mostly be useful for old and
	poorly-preserved negatives having a decayed film base that
	induces undesirable color casts. Be aware that the shadows
	color cast setting will have no effect if the <quote>scan
	exposure bias</quote> setting, in the <quote>film</quote> tab,
	is set to a non-zero value.
      </para>

      <para>
        It's important to understand that the Highlights white balance
        should always be calculated <emphasis>after</emphasis> shadows
        color cast, as the values of the shadows color cast sliders
        play a role in the values chosen for Highlights white balance
        (if using the eye dropper to have Negadoctor calculate those
        values).  For highlight color casts, select the eye dropper
        and <emphasis>click</emphasis> and drag a rectangle across the
        brightest area of your image.
      </para>

      <para>
	This setting should not be needed if your film has been
	exposed with a light source close to the one for which it was
	balanced, for example if you shot a scene lit by daylight on a
	daylight-balanced film.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>print properties</title>

      <para>
        <informaltable frame="none">
          <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
            <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
            <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  On the <quote>Print Properties</quote> tab, we have
                  sliders for <quote>paper black</quote>, <quote>paper
                  grade</quote>, <quote>paper gloss</quote>, and
                  <quote>print exposure</quote> adjustment.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <graphic
                      fileref="darkroom/modules/images/negadoctor_print.png"
                      scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
                </entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
      </para>

      <para>
	These settings will mimic the tonal effect of photochemical
	papers that will finally create the real image, in the analog
	process.
      </para>

      <para>
        For the <quote>paper black</quote>, select the eye dropper, and
        <emphasis>click</emphasis> and drag across only the exposed
        part of the negative. If you can see unexposed film stock
        around the edges of your image, ensure that these areas are
        excluded from the drawn rectangle for calculating the Paper
        black value.
      </para>

      <para>
	Paper black represents the density of the blackest
	silver-halide cristal available on the virtual paper. Since
	that black density always results in non-zero luminance in the
	analog process, but the digital pipeline usually expects black
	encoded at zero (RGB value), this setting lets you remap paper
	black to pipeline black with an offset.
      </para>

      <para>
        <quote>Paper grade</quote> is your gamma (contrast) control,
        and defaults to a value of 4. If all has gone well, this value
        (4) minus the value of D max (from the <quote>Film
        Properties</quote> tab) should leave you with a value between
        2 and 3.
      </para>

      <para>
        <quote>Paper gloss</quote> is essentially a highlights
        compression tool. As you drag this slider to the left, you
        will see in the histogram that the highlight values are being
        compressed (pushed to the left). Adjust this accordingly, so
        that your highlights are not clipped in the histogram or to
        simulate a mat printing with low-contrast highlights.
      </para>

      <para>
        The <quote>Print exposure adjustment</quote> slider is to
        correct any last minute clipping of highlights, although if
        you have followed all prior instructions, you shouldn't need
        it. It is also possible to increate print exposure while
        deccreasing the paper gloss to brighten midtones without
        losing highlights.
      </para>
    </sect5>
  </sect4>

</sect3>
