<!DOCTYPE sect3 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect3 status="final" id="whitebalance">

  <title>White balance</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>modules</primary>
    <secondary>white balance</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>white balance</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect4>

    <title>Overview</title>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              This module is used to set the white balance. You have three ways to interact with
              it: (a) Set up tint and temperature, (b) define the value of each channel, or (c)
              choose from predefined white balances.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/whitebalance.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

  </sect4>

  <sect4>

    <title>Usage</title>

    <sect5>
      <title>tint</title>
      <para>
        Alter the color tint of the image, from magenta (value &lt; 1) to green (value &gt; 1).
        The channel sliders will be updated when you adjust this parameter.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>temperature</title>
      <para>
        Set the color temperature (in Kelvin). The channel sliders will be updated when you
        adjust this parameter. darktable derives the color temperature from the Exif data using
        some model assumptions. The value given is not meant to be authoritative. In the end
        only the updated channel values determine how the image is modified.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>red, green and blue channels</title>
      <para>
        Set the channel values on a scale from 0 to 8.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>preset</title>
      <para>
        Select a preset white balance.
        <informaltable frame="none" width="80%">
          <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
            <colspec colwidth='4*'/>
            <colspec colwidth='6*'/>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <emphasis>camera white balance (default)</emphasis>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  White balance reported by the camera.
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <emphasis>camera neutral</emphasis>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  Essentially sets temperature to 6502K. The actual math: it computes such white
                  balance channel multipliers, so that pure white color in camera colorspace is
                  converted into pure white color in sRGB D65. (pure white color here means
                  having the same equal value for each channel = 1.0)
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <emphasis>spot white balance</emphasis>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  Select a square area in your image containing mostly grey pixels. The white
                  balance is calculated based on the selected area.
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <emphasis>camera presets</emphasis>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  Camera specific white balance presets. Examples: direct sunlight, flash,
                  cloudy, shade and a number of indoor lighting options.
                </entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>finetune</title>
      <para>
        Some cameras offer additional finetuning parameters if one of the camera presets is
        selected. Depending on camera white balance, can be adjusted in steps within a certain
        range. The adjustments are usually towards yellow (value &lt; 1) or blue (value &gt; 1).
      </para>
    </sect5>

  </sect4>

</sect3>
