<!DOCTYPE sect3 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect3 status="final" id="color_reconstruction">

  <title>Color reconstruction</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>modules</primary>
    <secondary>color reconstruction</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>color reconstruction</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>artifact mitigation</primary>
    <secondary>blown out highlights</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect4>

    <title>Overview</title>

    <informaltable frame="none" >
      <tgroup cols="2" rowsep="0" colsep="0" >
        <colspec colwidth="6*" />
        <colspec colwidth="4*" />
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              The color reconstruction module is able to bring back color into blown out
              highlights.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic width="80%" fileref="darkroom/modules/images/color_reconstruction.png" align="center" scalefit="1" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

  </sect4>

  <sect4>

    <title>Usage</title>

    <para>
      Due to the nature of digital sensors, overexposed highlights are lacking valid color
      information. Most frequently they appear neutral white or exhibit some color
      cast&nbsp;&ndash; depending on which other image processing steps are involved. This
      module can <quote>heal</quote> overexposed highlights by replacing their colors with
      better fitting ones. The module acts on highlight pixels whose luminance values exceed a
      user defined threshold. Replacement colors are taken from the neighborhood. Both, the
      spatial distance and the luminance distance <emphasis>(range)</emphasis> are taken into
      account for color selection.
    </para>

    <para>
      As a limitation of the underlying algorithm reconstructed colors may sometimes be
      displayed incorrectly if you zoom into the image in the darkroom view. If this happens you
      might observe a magenta shift in highlight areas close to high contrast edges, or you
      might see colorless highlight areas if you combine this module with the <quote>reconstruct
      color</quote> method of the <quote>highlight reconstruction</quote> module (see
      <xref linkend="highlight_reconstruction"/>). These artifacts only influence image
      display&nbsp;&ndash; the final output remains unaffected. It is recommended that you
      finetune the parameters of this module while viewing the full, not zoomed-in image.
    </para>

    <sect5>
      <title>threshold</title>
      <para>
        The color reconstruction module replaces the color of all target pixels characterized by
        luminance values above this threshold. Inversely, only pixels with luminance values
        below this threshold are taken as valid source pixels for replacement colors. Too high
        settings of this parameter will cause the module to have no effect on any pixels. Too
        low values will minimize the <quote>pool</quote> of replacement colors&nbsp;&ndash; if
        no suited ones are available the original colors are maintained. Therefore, this
        parameter exhibits a <quote>sweet spot</quote> characteristic with an optimum setting
        depending on the individual image.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>spatial extent</title>
      <para>
        Defines the spatial distance (x,y-coordinates) that source pixels may have from a target
        pixel in order for them to contribute to color replacement. Higher values cause ever
        more distant pixels to contribute; this increases the chance to find a replacement color
        but makes that color more undefined and less clear.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>range extent</title>
      <para>
        Defines the range distance (difference in luminance values) that source pixels may have
        from target pixels in order for them to contribute to color replacement. Higher values
        cause more pixels to contribute even if their luminance differs more strongly from the
        target pixels; this again increases the chance to find a replacement color but at the
        same time increases the risk of unfitting colors creeping in.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>preference</title>
      <para>
        This combobox defines if certain replacement colors shall take precedence over others.
        In its default setting <quote>off </quote> all pixels contribute equally. Setting it to
        <quote>saturated colors</quote> makes pixels contribute according to their
        chromaticity&nbsp;&ndash; the higher saturated a color the more it contributes. By
        selecting <quote>hue</quote> you get a choice of giving precedence to a specific hue.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>hue</title>
      <para>
        This slider is visible if you set the preference combobox to <quote>hue</quote>. It
        allows you to select a preferred hue of replacement colors. This only has an effect if
        the preferred hue is actually present within the selected spatial and range distance of
        the target pixels (see above). A typical use case is repairing highlights on human skin
        in situations where diverging colors are in close proximity (e.g. textiles or hair with
        a luminance close to skin). Setting a hue preference on skin tones avoids these other
        colors from creeping in.
      </para>
    </sect5>

  </sect4>

  <sect4>

    <title>Examples</title>

    <para>
      <informaltable frame="none">
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
          <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
          <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/color_reconstruction_ex1.png" scalefit="1" width="90%" align="center" />
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Original image with overexposed highlights on head, arm and shoulder of the
                statue.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/color_reconstruction_ex2.png" scalefit="1" width="90%" align="center" />
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Color reconstruction with default settings of all module parameters.
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </para>

  </sect4>

</sect3>
