<!DOCTYPE sect3 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect3 status="final" id="haze_removal">

  <title>Automatic haze removal</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>modules</primary>
    <secondary>haze removal</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>haze removal</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect4>

    <title>Overview</title>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              The haze removal module is designed to automatically reduce the effect of dust and
              haze in the air, which often reduces the color contrast in landscape photographs.
              In general, this module may be employed to give pictures a color boost
              specifically in low-contrast image regions.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/hazeremoval.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

    <para>
      The higher the haze density in the air and the longer the distance between the camera and
      the photographed object the less colorful the object appears in the image. Haze absorbs
      light approaching from the objects into the direction of the camera but it is also a
      source of diffusive background light. Thus the haze removal module estimates for each
      image region the amount of haze in the scene first and then removes the diffusive
      background light according to its local strength and recovers the original object light.
    </para>

  </sect4>

  <sect4>

    <title>Usage</title>

    <para>
      The haze removal module has two controls that determine the amount of haze reduction and
      limit the distance up to which haze is removed. Setting both controls to unity maximizes
      the amount of haze removal but this is also likely to produce some artifacts. Removing the
      atmospheric light entirely may render the image flat and may result in an unnatural
      looking style. Optimal values are typically below unity and these are rather image
      dependent but also a matter of personal aesthetic preferences.
    </para>

    <sect5>
      <title>strength</title>
      <para>
        The strength parameter controls the amount of haze removal. Setting it to unity, the
        module removes 100 percent of the detected haze between the camera and up to the
        specified distance; see below. Negative values for the strength increase the amount of
        haze in the image.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>distance</title>
      <para>
        This parameter limits the distance up to which haze is removed. For small values, haze
        removal is restricted to the foreground of the image. Haze is removed from the
        foreground to the far background if the distance parameter is set to unity. In case of a
        negative strength the distance control has no effect.
      </para>
    </sect5>

  </sect4>

</sect3>
