<!DOCTYPE sect3 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect3 status="final" id="lens_correction">

  <title>Lens correction</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>modules</primary>
    <secondary>lens correction</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>lens correction</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect4>

    <title>Overview</title>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              This module is able to correct certain lens flaws, namely distortions, transversal
              chromatic aberrations (TCA) and vignetting. It relies on the external library
              <ulink url="http://lensfun.sourceforge.net/">lensfun</ulink>, which comes with
              correction profiles for many (but not all) common cameras and lenses.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/lenscorrection.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

  </sect4>

  <sect4>

    <title>Usage</title>

    <para>
      In order to perform lens corrections the module uses Exif data of your image to identify
      the specific camera/lens combination and collects the needed correction parameters from a
      profile in lensfun's database.
    </para>

    <sect5>
      <title>camera</title>
      <para>
        The camera make and model as determined by Exif data. You can override this manually and
        select your camera from a hierarchical menu.
      </para>
      <para>
        Only lenses with correction profiles matching the selected camera will be shown.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>lens</title>
      <para>
        The lens make and model as determined by Exif data. You can override this manually and
        select your lens from a hierarchical menu. This is mainly needed for pure mechanical
        lenses, but may also be needed for off-brand / third party lenses.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>photometric parameters: focal length, aperture, focal distance</title>
      <para>
        Corrections additionally depend on certain photometric parameters that are read from
        Exif data: focal length (needed for distortion, TCA, vignetting), aperture (needed for
        TCA, vignetting) and focal distance (needed for vignetting). Many cameras do not record
        focal distance in their Exif data; most likely you need to set this manually.
      </para>
      <para>
        You can manually override all automatically selected parameters. Either take one of the
        predefined values from the pull-down menu; or&nbsp;&ndash; with the pull-down menu still
        open&nbsp;&ndash; just type in your own value.
      </para>
      <para>
        If your system's lensfun library has no correction profile for the automatically
        identified camera/lens combination the controls for the three photometric parameters are
        not displayed, and you get a warning message instead. You may try to find the right
        profile yourself by searching for it in the menu. If you can't find your lens, check if
        it is in the <ulink url="http://lensfun.sourceforge.net/lenslist/">list of currently
        supported lenses</ulink>, and refer to the
        <ulink url="http://lensfun.sourceforge.net/manual/lensfun-update-data.html">
        lensfun-update-data tool</ulink>. If there is no matching profile for your lens, please
        visit <ulink url="https://www.darktable.org/2013/07/have-your-lens-calibrated/">this
        lens calibration service</ulink> offered by Torsten Bronger, one of darktable's users.
        Alternatively you may go to <ulink url="http://lensfun.sourceforge.net/">lensfun's home
        page</ulink> and learn how to generate your own set of correction parameters. Don't
        forget to share your profile with the lensfun team!
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>corrections</title>
      <para>
        This combobox gives you a choice about which corrections (out of distortion, TCA and
        vignetting) darktable shall apply. Change this from its default <quote>all</quote>, if
        your camera has already done some internal corrections (e.g. of vignetting), or if you
        plan to do certain corrections with a separate program.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>geometry</title>
      <para>
        In addition to the correction of lens flaws, this module can change the projection type
        of your image. Set this combobox to the aimed projection type, like
        <quote>rectilinear</quote>, <quote>fish-eye</quote>, <quote>panoramic</quote>,
        <quote>equirectangular</quote>, <quote>orthographic</quote>,
        <quote>stereographic</quote>, <quote>equisolid angle</quote>, <quote>thoby
        fish-eye</quote>.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>scale</title>
      <para>
        This slider allows you to adjust the scaling factor of your image. Pressing the auto
        scale button (right to the slider) will let darktable find the best fit to avoid black
        corners.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>mode</title>
      <para>
        The default behavior of this module is to correct lens flaws. Switch this combobox to
        <quote>distort</quote> in order to simulate the behavior of a specific lens (inverted
        effect).
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>TCA red</title>
      <para>
        This slider allows to override the correction parameter for TCA. You can also use this
        slider to manually set the parameter in case the lens profile does not contain TCA
        correction. Look out for colored seams at features with high contrast edges and adjust
        this parameter and the following one to minimize those seams.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>TCA blue</title>
      <para>
        This slider allows to override the correction parameter for TCA. You can also use this
        slider to manually set the parameter in case the lens profile does not contain TCA
        correction.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>corrections done</title>
      <para>
        You will sometimes observe that for a given camera/lens combination only part of the
        possible corrections (distortion, TCA, vignetting) are supported by lensfun's profiles.
        This message box will tell you what corrections have actually been applied.
      </para>
    </sect5>

  </sect4>

</sect3>
