<!DOCTYPE sect3 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect3 status="final" id="raw_denoise">

  <title>Raw denoise</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>modules</primary>
    <secondary>raw denoise</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>denoise</primary>
    <secondary>raw</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect4>

    <title>Overview</title>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              Raw denoise allows you to perform denoising on the data before it gets demosaiced.
              It is ported from
              <ulink url="http://www.cybercom.net/~dcoffin/dcraw/"><emphasis>dcraw</emphasis></ulink>.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/rawdenoise.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

  </sect4>

  <sect4>

    <title>Usage</title>

    <sect5>
      <title>noise threshold</title>
      <para>
        Set the threshold for noise detection. Higher values lead to stronger noise removal and
        higher loss of image detail.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>coarse/fine curves</title>
      <para>
        The noise of an image is usually not only fine grain, but also more or less coarse grain.
        These curves allow to denoise more or less depending on the coarseness of the visible noise.
        The left of the curve will act on very coarse grain noise, while the right of the curve will
        act on very fine grain noise. Pushing up the curve will result in more smoothing, pulling it
        down will result in less smoothing. As an example, you can preserve very-fine grain noise by
        pulling down the rightest point of the curve until the minimum value. As another example, if
        you are tackling chroma noise with a blend mode, you can push up the right part of the curve,
        as colors are not supposed to change a lot on fine grain scales: this will help especially if
        you see some isolated pixel left undenoised.
        Considering R, G, and B curves, the best way to use them is to look at one of the channel using
        the channel mixer module in gray mode, denoise this particular channel, and then do the same for
        the other channels. This way, you can take into account the fact that some channel may be noisier
        than others into your denoising. Be aware that guessing which channel is noisy without actually
        seeing the channels individually is not straightforward and can be counterintuitive: a pixel
        which is completely red may not be caused by noise on the R channel, but actually by noise on
        B and G channels.
      </para>
    </sect5>

  </sect4>

</sect3>
