<!DOCTYPE sect3 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect3 status="final" id="local_contrast">

  <title>Local contrast</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>modules</primary>
    <secondary>local contrast</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>local contrast</primary>
    <seealso>equalizer</seealso>
  </indexterm>

  <sect4>

    <title>Overview</title>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              This module allows enhancing local contrast. It supports two modes of operation:
              the default one uses a local laplacian filter, the other one uses the unnormalized
              bilateral filter. Both work exclusively on the L channel from Lab.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/localcontrast.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

  </sect4>

  <sect4>

    <title>Usage</title>

    <para>
      Local contrast boosts details of your image, much like the <emphasis>equalizer</emphasis>
      does (see <xref linkend="equalizer"/>). However, it is easier to use as it does not
      require you to work on different frequency bands. The local laplacian filter has been
      designed to be very robust against unwanted halo effects and gradient reversals along
      edges.
    </para>

    <sect5>
      <title>mode</title>
      <para>
        Choice of "local laplacian filter" or "unnormalised bilateral grid". The options for the
        bilateral grid are: coarseness, contrast, and detail. The local laplacian filter
        supports: detail, highlights, shadows, and midtone range. The local laplacian mode
        supports shadow lifting and highlight compression, similar to the shadows and highlights
        module.
      </para>
    </sect5>

  </sect4>

  <sect4>

    <title>Bilateral grid</title>

    <sect5>
      <title>coarseness</title>
      <para>
        Make the details you want to adjust finer or coarser.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>contrast</title>
      <para>
        How strongly the algorithm distinguishes between brightness levels. Increasing the value
        results in a more contrasty look.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>detail</title>
      <para>
        Add or remove detail. Higher values will increase local contrast.
      </para>
    </sect5>

  </sect4>

  <sect4>

    <title>Local laplacian</title>

    <para>
      To understand the parameters of the local laplacian filter, you can think of it as
      applying a curve to the image, similar to this picture:
      <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/locallaplacian-curve.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
      It will then be applied to the image in a way that works locally and avoids halo
      artifacts.
    </para>

    <sect5>
      <title>detail</title>
      <para>
        Add or remove detail. Higher values will increase local contrast. This will insert an S
        shaped element in the center of the curve, to increase or decrease local contrast. For
        monochrome images it is often possible to push this parameter to extreme settings
        without ridiculous results or artifacts.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>highlights</title>
      <para>
        This affects one end of the curve, effectively increasing or compressing contrast in the
        highlights. A low value will pull the highlights down.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>shadows</title>
      <para>
        Similar to the highlights parameter, this affects the other far end of the curve, and
        will increase or decrease contrast in the shadows. A higher value gives more contrast in
        the shadows. A lower value will lift the shadows and can effectively simulate a fill
        light. Note that this is done via local manipulation of the image, however: this means
        that a completely dark image cannot be brightened this way, only dark things in front of
        bright things will be affected.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>midtone range</title>
      <para>
        This controls the extent of the S shaped part of the contrast curve. A larger value will
        make the S wider, and thus classify more values to be midtone range and fewer values to
        belong to the highlights and shadows part. In more high dynamic range settings it can be
        useful to reduce this value to achieve stronger range compression by lowering the
        contrast in the highlights and the shadows. Note however that for really strong HDR
        scenarios this may work best in combination with a base curve which pre-compresses the
        range, maybe with an approximately logarithmic base curve. Also the exposure fusion
        feature in the base curve module may lead to more pleasing results at times, but is more
        prone to producing halo effects.
      </para>
      <para>
        This setting can cause banding artifacts in the image if pushed to extreme values. This
        is due to the way darktable computes the fast approximation of the local laplacian
        filter.
      </para>
    </sect5>

  </sect4>

  <sect4>

    <title>Example</title>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              Before
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/localcontrast_before.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              After, a little overdone to demonstrate the effect. Use this sparingly, to avoid a
              cheap, overprocessed look.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/localcontrast_after.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

  </sect4>

</sect3>
