<!DOCTYPE sect3 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect3 status="final" id="retouch">

  <title>Retouch</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>modules</primary>
    <secondary>retouch</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>retouch</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect4>

    <title>Overview</title>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              Retouch allows to heal, clone, fill and blur certain areas of the image. It can
              perform a wavelet decomposition which separates the image into different frequency
              scales, from fine to coarse, and apply retouch operations to each wavelet scale
              individually.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/retouch.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

  </sect4>

  <sect4>

    <title>Usage</title>

    <para>
      For a basic use, with default parameters, add the shapes to the image like with the spot
      removal module (see <xref linkend="spot_removal"/>). To use the wavelet decompose first
      select one of the scales as the current scale (see below) and then add the shapes.
    </para>

    <para>
      The GUI is divided in three main sections: wavelet decompose, retouch tools and shapes.
    </para>

    <sect5>
      <title>wavelet decompose section</title>
      <para>
        The wavelet decompose toolbar controls the wavelet decompose algorithm. It has a central
        area divided in boxes and two sliders. The first box, scale zero, represents the
        original image, the second is the wavelet scale 1, and so on.
      </para>
      <para>
        The bottom slider adjusts the number of scales, zero means no wavelet decompose is done.
        The maximum number of scales depends on the image size, but any number can be selected.
        If the image is not big enough for the selected number of scales the maximum number of
        scales for this image size is used and the rest of the scales are ignored.
      </para>
      <para>
        The image is decomposed to the selected number of scales plus the residual image, so if
        5 is selected as the number of scales, scale zero is the original image, scales 1 to 5
        are the detail scales, and scale 6 is the residual image. As a visual aid, the original
        image is always represented by a black box, detail scales are light gray, residual image
        white and inactive scales dark gray.
      </para>
      <para>
        The central area allows to select the current scale on which the user can then apply
        retouch tools by left clicking any of the boxes. The selected scale is marked by a red
        frame. Any scale can be selected as the current scale, even if it is greater than the
        number of scales. If a shape is added to a scale greater than the residual image it will
        be ignored, as the scale is not processed.
      </para>
      <para>
        Only the shapes on the current scale are displayed, when the current scale is changed
        shapes will be displayed accordingly.
      </para>
      <para>
        A green line on top of each box indicates that the scale has shapes associated with it.
      </para>
      <para>
        Fine detail scales can only be seen at certain zoom level, a light gray line on top of
        each box will indicate that the scale is visible at current zoom level.
      </para>
      <para>
        The top slider adjusts the <emphasis>merge scale</emphasis> feature. This setting allows
        to apply a common edit on multiple consecutive scales within a group starting from the
        highest scale (not including the residual image) down to the one selected by this
        slider. If the slider is set to 3 and the maximum scale is 5 then all edits that are
        added to scale 5 will be applied to scales 3 to 5. Edits added to scale 4 will be
        applied to scales 3 and 4, and edits added to scale 3 will be applied only to scale 3.
        <emphasis>Merged scales</emphasis> are represented by a green-yellow color. A value of
        zero means that the merge feature is not used.
      </para>
      <para>
        The display wavelet scale button (
        <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_retouch_display_scale;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center" />
        ) allow to view the current wavelet scale. The module's blend feature is temporary
        disabled when this option is set. If blending in the module is active and the option to
        display masks is active this option cannot be set. When this option is active a new
        section, <quote>preview single scale</quote>, will be displayed, allowing to adjust the
        levels for the displayed image. This is purely a convenience feature so you can adjust
        wavelet scale display to your needs. It does not have an effect on the final output
        image. An auto levels button (
        <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_retouch_auto_levels;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center" />
        ) is also available; it works on the displayed image, so different results can be
        expected depending on the image displayed when zoomed in/out. Levels are only applied to
        detail scales, not the original or residual image.
      </para>
      <para>
        The cut and paste buttons allow to move all the shapes from one scale to another. In
        order to do this first select the current scale, click the cut button (
        <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_retouch_cut;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center" />
        ), select the destination scale and click paste (
        <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_retouch_paste;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center" />
        ). This can be useful when there are edits on the residual image and one has to change
        the number of scales; since the residual image is changed, shapes need to be moved to
        the new one.
      </para>
      <para>
        The switch off shapes button (
        <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_retouch_switch;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center" />
        ) temporarily disables the processing of all shapes for a simple before/after
        comparison.
      </para>
      <para>
        The display masks button (
        <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_retouch_mask;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center" />
        ) works similar to the one on the blend module, but it will display only the shapes on
        the current scale. This option and display mask on the blend module cannot be set at the
        same time.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>retouch tools section</title>
      <para>
        The shapes toolbar allows to add new shapes to the image. Shapes creation/editing
        behaves like in the spot removal module. In addition, by Ctrl+click on any shape button,
        the <emphasis>continuous add mode</emphasis> is activated. Once a shape is added,
        darktable will remain in creation mode, allowing to add another shape of the same type.
        To change the shape type to be added Ctrl+click on a different shape button to continue
        on continuous add mode or plain click to add a single shape. To leave the continuous add
        mode right click on any clear area of the image.
      </para>
      <para>
        The algorithms toolbar allows to select between heal (
        <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_retouch_heal;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center" />
        ), clone (
        <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_retouch_clone;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center" />
        ), fill (
        <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_retouch_fill;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center" />
        ) and blur (
        <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_retouch_blur;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center" />
        ) algorithms. Before actually creating a shape the algorithm must be
        selected&nbsp;&ndash; once a shape is created the algorithm cannot be changed.
      </para>
      <para>
        Any combination of shape type and algorithm can be added to the image.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>shapes section</title>
      <para>
        The shape selected field displays the selected shape (if any). To select a shape click
        on it, to deselect click on a free area on the image.
      </para>
      <para>
        Mask opacity is displayed when a shape is selected. It displays/sets the opacity of the
        mask. Opacity is a property of the currently selected shape and won't be used as default
        value for newly added shapes.
      </para>
      <para>
        Different properties will be displayed depending on the selected algorithm:
        <informaltable frame="none" width="80%">
          <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
            <colspec colwidth='1*'/>
            <colspec colwidth='4*'/>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <emphasis>fill algorithm</emphasis>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <variablelist>

                    <varlistentry>

                      <term>fill mode</term>

                      <listitem><para>
                        Can be erase or color. Erase is used to delete details from a wavelet
                        scale. Color allows to select a color to fill the area defined by the
                        shape.
                      </para></listitem>

                    </varlistentry>

                    <varlistentry>

                      <term>brightness</term>

                      <listitem><para>
                        Adds the selected value to the color, allowing to make it brighter or
                        darker. Works the same with both fill modes.
                      </para></listitem>

                    </varlistentry>

                  </variablelist>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <emphasis>blur algorithm</emphasis>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <variablelist>

                    <varlistentry>

                      <term>blur type</term>

                      <listitem><para>
                        Can be gaussian or bilateral.
                      </para></listitem>

                    </varlistentry>

                    <varlistentry>

                      <term>blur radius</term>

                      <listitem><para>
                        Sets the blur radius.
                      </para></listitem>

                    </varlistentry>

                  </variablelist>
                </entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
        The value set on each one of these properties is used as a default when a new shape is
        created.
      </para>
    </sect5>

  </sect4>

</sect3>
