<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect2 status="final" id="darkroom_bottom_panel">

  <title>Bottom panel</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>darkroom panels</primary>
    <secondary>bottom panel</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    The bottom panel provides quick access to apply presets and styles to your image and allows
    to activate over/underexposure warning as well as softproofing and gamut check. You can also
    activate a filmstrip for quick navigation within the current collection.
  </para>

  <sect3 status="final" id="favorite_presets">

    <title>Quick access to favorite presets</title>

    <para>
      Clicking the
      <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_module_presets;"  scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center"/>
      icon opens a combobox that gives you quick access to your favorite module's presets. Click
      on the preset name to apply it to the image.
    </para>

  </sect3>

  <sect3 status="final" id="darkroom_bottom_panel_styles">

    <title>Quick access to styles</title>

    <para>
      Clicking the
      <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_styles;"  scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center"/>
      icon opens a combobox with your styles. Hovering with the mouse over a style name opens a
      tooltip showing the involved modules. Click on a style name to apply that style to the
      image.
    </para>

  </sect3>

  <sect3 status="final" id="rawoverexposed">

    <title>Raw overexposed warning</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>darkroom panels</primary>
      <secondary>raw overexposed warning</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>raw overexposed warning</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>
      Clicking the
      <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_module_rawoverexposed;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center" />
      icon warns you about areas of your raw input image with clipped color channels. Clipped
      color channels imply an overexposed image with loss of information in the affected areas.
      You may use the <emphasis>highlight reconstruction</emphasis> module or the
      <emphasis>color reconstruction</emphasis> module in order to reconstruct those areas (see
      <xref linkend="highlight_reconstruction"/> and <xref linkend="color_reconstruction"/>).
    </para>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              Right-clicking on the icon opens a dialog with configuration parameters.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="darkroom/images/panel_rawoverexposed.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect5">mode</bridgehead>

    <para>
      The default <quote>mark with CFA color</quote> mode displays a pattern of the respective
      primary colors (red, green, and blue) to indicate which color channels are found to be
      clipped. In the <quote>mark with solid color</quote> mode clipped areas are marked with a
      user defined solid color (see below) independent of the affected color channels. In the
      <quote>false color</quote> mode clipped color channels are set to zero in the affected
      areas.
    </para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect5">color scheme</bridgehead>

    <para>
      Selects the solid color for the <quote>mark with solid color</quote> mode.
    </para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect5">clipping threshold</bridgehead>

    <para>
      This slider sets the threshold of what values are considered to be overexposed. You can
      leave it at its default value 1.0 (white level) in most cases.
    </para>

  </sect3>

  <sect3 status="final" id="overexposed">

    <title>Over/underexposed warning</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>darkroom panels</primary>
      <secondary>overexposed warning</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>darkroom panels</primary>
      <secondary>underexposed warning</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>overexposed warning</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>underexposed warning</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>
      By clicking the
      <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_module_overexposed;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center" />
      icon an over/underexposed warning is toggled on or off. Pixels outside the dynamic range,
      close to pure white or close to pure black, are prominently displayed in a signal color.
      You can also activate the over/underexposure warning with the keyboard shortcut
      <quote>o</quote>.
    </para>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              Right-clicking on the icon opens a dialog with configuration parameters.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="darkroom/images/panel_overexposed.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect5">color scheme</bridgehead>

    <para>
      In the default color scheme underexposed pixels are shown in blue and overexposed pixels
      in red. These colors are easy to identify in most cases. In some cases you may want to
      change the color scheme to <quote>black &amp; white</quote> or <quote>purple &amp;
      green</quote>, eg. if you experience overexposed highlights in red blossoms.
    </para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect5">lower threshold</bridgehead>

    <para>
      Sets the threshold for underexposure warning, expressed as a percentage of the maximal
      brightness.
    </para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect5">upper threshold</bridgehead>

    <para>
      Sets the threshold for overexposure warning, expressed as a percentage of the maximal
      brightness.
    </para>

  </sect3>

  <sect3 status="final" id="softproof">

    <title>Soft proof</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>darkroom panels</primary>
      <secondary>soft proof</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>soft proof</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>
      Clicking the
      <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_module_softproof;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center" />
      icon activates the soft proof display mode of your image. Soft proof allows you to preview
      your image rendered using a printer profile so as to see how colors will end up on the
      final print. You can also activate soft proof with the keyboard shortcut
      <quote>ctrl-s</quote>. An information message <quote>soft proof</quote> on the bottom left
      of your image tells you that you are in soft proof display mode.
    </para>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              Right-clicking on the icon opens a dialog with configuration parameters.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="darkroom/images/panel_softproof.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect5">display intent</bridgehead>

    <para>
      Sets the rendering intent for your display&nbsp;&ndash; only available if rendering with
      LittleCMS2 is activated. See <xref linkend="rendering_intent"/> for available options.
    </para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect5">softproof profile</bridgehead>

    <para>
      Sets the color profile for soft proofing. darktable searches for available profiles in
      <filename>$DARKTABLE/share/darktable/color/out</filename> and
      <filename>$HOME/.config/darktable/color/out</filename>. <filename>$DARKTABLE</filename> is
      used here to represent your chosen darktable installation directory and
      <filename>$HOME</filename> your home directory. Typically these profiles are supplied by
      your printer or generated during printer profiling.
    </para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect5">display profile</bridgehead>

    <para>
      Sets the color profile for the display. The option <quote>system display profile</quote>
      is the preferred setting when working with a calibrated display; the profile is taken
      either from your system's color manager or from your X display server. In <emphasis>GUI
      options</emphasis> (see <xref linkend="gui_options"/>) you can specify which method to
      use. For more information see <xref linkend="display_profile"/>.
    </para>

  </sect3>

  <sect3 status="final" id="gamutcheck">

    <title>Gamut check</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>darkroom panels</primary>
      <secondary>gamut check</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>gamut check</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>
      Clicking the
      <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_module_gamutcheck;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center" />
      icon activates the gamut check display mode of your image. Gamut check highlights in cyan
      all pixels out of gamut with respect to the selected softproof profile. You can also
      activate gamut check with the keyboard shortcut <quote>ctrl-g</quote>. An information
      message <quote>gamut check</quote> on the bottom left of your image tells you that you are
      in gamut check display mode. Gamut check and soft proof are mutually exclusive modes.
    </para>

    <para>
      Right-clicking on the icon opens a dialog with configuration parameters&nbsp;&ndash; they
      are the same as for the soft proof option (see <xref linkend="softproof"/>).
    </para>

  </sect3>

  <sect3 status="final" id="darkroom_filmstrip">

    <title>Filmstrip</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>darkroom panels</primary>
      <secondary>filmstrip</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>
      The optional filmstrip can be used to quickly switch between images while remaining in the
      darkroom view. The images viewed are the same as the ones in the lighttable view.
    </para>

    <para>
      The filmstrip can be switched on and off using the shortcut <emphasis>ctrl-f</emphasis>.
      You can change the height of the filmstrip panel by dragging its top.
    </para>

    <para>
      You can scroll with your mouse to quickly navigate through the images. You can change the
      photo being processed by double clicking on another picture. You can also use space bar to
      process the next photo and use backspace key to process the previous photo.
    </para>

    <para>
      The picture currently processed is selected and highlighted; with a single click you can
      select any other picture from the filmstrip without changing the picture currently
      processed. With the <emphasis>ctrl-a</emphasis> shortcut you select all the pictures of
      the filmstrip. With the shortcut <emphasis>ctrl-shift-a</emphasis> you unselect all
      images, and with <emphasis>ctrl-i</emphasis> you reverse the current selection.
    </para>

    <para>
      The following shortcuts are available to act on the selected picture(s):
      <informaltable frame="none">
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
          <colspec colwidth="1*"/>
          <colspec colwidth="3*"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis>F1&nbsp;&ndash; F5</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                toggle color label (red, yellow, green, blue, purple)
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis>0&nbsp;&ndash; 5</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                set/change image rating
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis>r</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                reject image
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis>ctrl-d</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                duplicate image
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis>ctrl-c</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                copy the full history stack
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis>ctrl-v</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                paste all of the copied history stack
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis>alt-ctrl-c</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                selectively copy the history stack
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis>alt-ctrl-v</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                selectively paste from the copied history stack
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </para>

    <para>
      <graphic fileref="darkroom/images/filmstrip.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
    </para>

  </sect3>

</sect2>
