<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>

	<sect2 status="draft" id="color picker"><title>Color picker</title>
		<informaltable frame="none"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
				<colspec colwidth="6*"/>
				<colspec colwidth="4*"/>
				<tbody>
					<row>						
						<entry>
						<para>Within the global color picker panel you can take color samples from your image, display their
                                                      values in multiple ways and compare colors from different locations. Color picker is activated
						      by pressing icon <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_module_picker;" scalefit="1" width="3%" align="center" />.
                                                      Various parameters control how color picker works. All settings remain in effect until you leave
                                                      darkroom mode.</para>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							<graphic fileref="darkroom/images/panel_colorpicker.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
						</entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</informaltable>
                <para>Besides the global color picker, which we describe here, there are local color pickers in various modules (eg. <link linkend="tonecurve">
                      <emphasis>tonecurve</emphasis></link>).
                      Global and local color pickers are different. The global color picker works in monitor color space; it takes samples after
                      the complete pixelpipe has been processed and colors are transfered into RGB suited for your monitor. The local color pickers
                      run in the color space of the individual module, which is most often Lab; they only see input and/or output colors of that
                      specific module within pixelpipe.
                </para>
		<para>Color picker can be run in point or area mode. When in point mode only a small spot under your cursor is taken as a sample.
                      In area mode you can draw a rectangle with your mouse; darktable samples the area within that rectangle. The combobox to switch
                      between point and area mode can also be used to toggle the mode of local color pickers.
                </para>
                <para>If samples are taken in area mode, darktable will calculate mean, min and max color channel values. A combobox allows you to select
                      which of those are displayed. For obvious reasons mean, min and max are identical in point mode.
                </para>
                <para>A color swatch representing the sampled point or area is displayed. Numerical values are shown as well. As said before global 
                      color picker works in monitor RGB color space. You can also let darktable translate these numerical values into Lab
                      color space. Beware that Lab values are approximated here; darktable does not take your specific monitor profile into account.
                </para>
		<para>On activation of checkbox <quote>restrict histogram to selection</quote> only the values of your selected area or point are taken into account
                      by the histogram on top of right panel (see <xref linkend="histogram"/>). This is a useful tool if you want to know which tonal 
                      values are present in a specific area.
		</para>
		<para>Picked colors in area or point mode can be <quote>stored</quote> as live samples by pressing the <quote>add</quote> button. darktable shows a color swatch
                      and numerical values for each stored sample. You can once again select which numerical value (mean, min, max) is to be displayed and
                      if this is to be done in RGB or Lab color space.
		</para>
		<para>Newly created live samples are not locked. If you change the parameters of your image these changes will be reflected in your stored
                      samples. Use this if you want to get an overview how changing a parameters has effect to different parts of an image. If you click
                      on the color swatch of a stored live sample it gets locked - a lock symbol is displayed. Further changes of parameters will not affect
                      this live sample any longer. You can for example take two live samples from the same location and have one of them locked. This way
                      you can keep the locked one as a reference sample for comparison.
                </para>
                <para>Live sample locations are indicated in your image if you check option <quote>display sample areas on image</quote>.
		</para>
	</sect2>
