<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
                <!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
                %darktable_dtd;
                ]>
<sect2 status="final" id="histogram">

  <title>Histogram</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>darkroom panels</primary>
    <secondary>histogram</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>histogram</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>waveform</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>RGB parade</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>scopes</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect3>

    <title>Overview</title>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
	      <para>
		This is a graphical depiction of aspects of the developed image. Moving the
		mouse over the panel displays buttons to adjust the display. The leftmost button
		allows for cycling the mode between a "regular" and a waveform-style
		histogram. The next button over adjusts how the data for the current mode is
		displayed. The three rightmost colored squares are toggles which enable or
		disable the display of specific color channels.
	      </para>

	      <para>
		When the mouse is over the histogram panel, scrolling while holding down the
		<emphasis>Ctrl</emphasis> key will change the height of the panel. You can
		hide/show the histogram entirely with a keyboard shortcut. The default shortcut
		is <emphasis>Shift+Ctrl+H</emphasis>.
	      </para>

	      <para>
		It is possible to assign keyboard shortcuts to cycle through or switch histogram
		mode/type. Separate shortcuts can be set for the darkroom and tethering
		views. By default, none of these shortcuts are associated with keys.
	      </para>

	      <para>
		For the purposes of speed, the scopes are calculated from the image
		preview. This is the image which is displayed in the navigation panel (see <xref
		linkend="navigation"/>), rather than the higher quality developed image which is
		displayed in the center view. The preview is calculated at a lower resolution
		and may use shortcuts to bypass time-consuming image processing steps. Hence
		scopes may not represent fine detail in the image, and may deviate in other ways
		from the final developed image.
	      </para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="darkroom/images/panel_histogram_logarithmic.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

  </sect3>

  <sect3>

    <title>"Regular" Histogram</title>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
	      <para>
		This shows the distribution of pixels by lightness for each color channel
		channel. In its default state, data for all three RGB color channels are
		displayed. The x-axis runs from 0% to 100% lightness for each channel. The
		y-axis height gives the count of pixels which have the given lightness, up to
		the maximum count for the developed image.
	      </para>

	      <para>
		Clicking the second-to-leftmost button on the panel toggles between a
		logarithmic and a linear rendering of the y-axis data.
	      </para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="darkroom/images/panel_histogram_linear.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

  </sect3>

  <sect3>

    <title>Waveform</title>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
	      <para>
		The leftmost button of the panel is a toggle which flips to a waveform
		scope. This scope includes spatial data about the image. The y-axis represents
		the distribution of pixels by lightness for each channel. The scope's x-axis
		represents the distribution of this data across the x-axis of the image. The
		lightness of each point of the waveform represents the quantity of pixels
		represented at that scope position.
	      </para>

	      <para>
		The thick dotted horizontal line at the top of the waveform histogram represents
		100% lightness. Hence, any channel which displays above that line may be clipped
		in the resulting image. The thinner dotted horizontal line represents 50%
		lightness. The bottom of the scope represents 0% lightness.
	      </para>

	      <para>
		As with the "regular" histogram, it is possible to selectively display red,
		green, and blue channels, or (the default) overlay all three of them.
	      </para>

	      <para>
		See <ulink
		url="https://www.darktable.org/2013/12/of-histograms-and-waveforms/">Of
		Histograms and Waveforms</ulink> for more on darktable's waveform scope.
	      </para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="darkroom/images/panel_histogram_waveform.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

  </sect3>

  <sect3>

    <title>RGB Parade</title>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
	      <para>
		This shows the same data as the waveform, but with the red, green, and blue
		channels side-by-side. When in waveform mode, clicking the second-to-leftmost
		button on the panel toggles between waveform (overlaid) and RGB parade rendering
		of the data.
	      </para>

	      <para>
		The RGB parade can be useful for matching the intensities of the red, green, and
		blue channels. It can also help with understanding the differences between and
		individual qualities of each channel.
	      </para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="darkroom/images/panel_histogram_rgb_parade.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

  </sect3>

  <sect3>

    <title>Exposure Adjustment</title>

    <para>
      The histogram is directly linked to the <emphasis>exposure</emphasis> module described in
      <xref linkend="exposure"/>, and you can operate some of the exposure module's controls
      from the histogram.
    </para>

    <para>
      For the regular histogram, you can left-click towards the right hand side of the histogram
      and then drag right to increase or drag left to decrease the exposure. In a similar manner
      you can control the black level by clicking and dragging in the left hand side.
    </para>

    <para>
      For a waveform-style scope, dragging the upper portion of the histogram up/down will
      increase/decrease exposure. Dragging the lower portion up/down will increase/decrease the
      black level.
    </para>

    <para>
      Scrolling in the appropriate area -- rather than dragging -- will also adjust exposure and
      black point. Double-clicking in the histogram resets the exposure module's parameters to
      their defaults.
    </para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>

    <title>Histogram Profile</title>

    <para>
      For the regular histogram, the image data is converted to the <emphasis>histogram
      profile</emphasis> before the histogram is calculated. You can choose this profile by
      right-clicking on the <emphasis>softproofing</emphasis> or <emphasis>gamut
      checking</emphasis> icons in the bottom panel (see <xref
      linkend="darkroom_bottom_panel"/>) then selecting the profile of interest.
    </para>

    <para>
      Besides choosing a specific colorspace, you can also choose the <emphasis>work
      profile</emphasis>, <emphasis>export profile</emphasis>, <emphasis>softproof
      profile</emphasis>, or <emphasis>display profile</emphasis>.
    </para>

    <para>
      In the case of the waveform and RGB parade scopes, the colorspace depends on the
      <programlisting>cache_color_managed</programlisting> configuration variable. In its
      default (<emphasis>true</emphasis>) setting, these scopes are calculated in the
      <quote>Adobe RGB (compatible)</quote> colorspace. Otherwise, they are calculated in the
      display colorspace.
    </para>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
