<!DOCTYPE sect3 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
    <!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
    %darktable_dtd;
    ]>
<sect3 status="final" id="rgb_curve">

  <title>RGB curve</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>modules</primary>
    <secondary>rgb curve</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>rgb curve</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect4>

    <title>Overview</title>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              This module is a classic digital photography tool. darktable's RGB curve
              works on RGB color space.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/rgbcurve.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

  </sect4>

  <sect4>

    <title>Usage</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>color picker</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>
      In its default state, curves will be straight lines, defined by few anchor nodes. You can
      move the nodes to modify the curve. You can generate new nodes by
      <emphasis>clicking</emphasis> on the curve. With <emphasis>Ctrl+click</emphasis> you
      generate a new node at the x-location of the mouse pointer and the corresponding
      y-location of the current curve&nbsp;&ndash; this adds a node without risking to
      accidentally modify the curve. Up to 20 nodes per curve can be defined. To remove a node,
      move it out of the widget area.
    </para>

    <para>
      A color picker is activated by pressing
      <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_module_picker;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center" />
      and will show the picked values in the graph. You can use an area
      sampling mode using with
      <emphasis>Ctrl+click</emphasis>.
    </para>

    <para>
      A second color picker can be used to directly change the curve
      based on the sampled area. A <emphasis>Click</emphasis> on
      <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_module_action_picker;"
                     scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center" /> will
      activate the action picker. Then, on the picture, a
      <emphasis>Ctrl+Click+Drag</emphasis> will create a positive curve for
      the sampled area and a <emphasis>Shift+Click+Drag</emphasis> a negative curve.
    </para>

    <sect5>
      <title>color spaces</title>
      <para>
        Depending on the desired intent, you can apply the RGB curve in two different color spaces:
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem><para>RGB, linked channels.</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>RGB, independent channels.</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>

      <para>
        RGB spaces are linear color spaces designed to capture and display images in additive
        synthesis. They are related to capture and display media and do not isolate
        color and lightness information.
        The <quote>RGB, linked channels,</quote> works in ProPhoto RGB and applies the L-channel
        curve to all three channels in the RGB color space. Adding contrast in RGB space
        is known to desaturate highlights and boost saturation in lowlights, but this has proven to
        be the most reliable way to edit contrast, and is the standard way to do it in most
        software.
      </para>

    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>interpolation method</title>
      <para>
        The interpolation is the process by which a continuous curve is derived from a few
        punctual nodes. As this process is never perfect, several methods are offered that
        can alleviate the potential issues you may encounter with some nodes setups.
      </para>
      <para>
        Arguably, the most visually pleasing method is the <quote>cubic spline</quote>. Since
        it gives smooth curves, the contrast in the image is better enhanced. However, this
        method is very sensitive to the nodes position, and can produce cusps and oscillations
        when the nodes are too close to each other, or when there are too many of them.
        This method works best when there are only 4 to 5 nodes, evenly spaced.
      </para>
      <para>
        The <quote>centripetal spline</quote> is a method designed specifically to avoid
        cusps and oscillations, but as a drawback it will follow the nodes more loosely.
        It is very robust, no matter the number of nodes and their spacing, but will produce
        a more faded and dull contrast.
      </para>
      <para>
        The <quote>monotonic spline</quote> is a method designed specifically to give a monotonic
        interpolation, meaning that there will be none of the oscillations the cubic spline may
        produce. This method is very suitable when you try to build an analytical function
        from a node interpolation (for example: exponential, logarithm, power, etc.). Such
        functions are provided as presets. It is a good trade-off between the two
        aforementioned methods.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>compensate middle grey</title>
      <para>
        Will change the histogram display on the module, this option
        does not change the processing but may help editing the
        picture. It is activated by default.
      </para>
    </sect5>
  </sect4>

</sect3>
