<!DOCTYPE sect3 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect3 status="final" id="rgblevels">

  <title>RGB Levels</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>modules</primary>
    <secondary>RGB levels</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>RGB levels</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>artifact mitigation</primary>
    <secondary>black pixels</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>artifact mitigation</primary>
    <secondary>blue light sources</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect4>

    <title>Overview</title>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              A tool for adjusting black, white, and mid-gray points. This module is especially
              useful if the histogram of an image does not span the whole horizontal range, from
              pure black to pure white.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/rgblevels.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

  </sect4>

  <sect4>

    <title>Usage</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>color picker</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>
      Depending on the desired intent, you can work in two different modes:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>RGB, linked channels</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>RGB, independent channels</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>

    <para>
      You can move the black and white bars to match the left and right borders of the
      histogram, which will make the output image span the full available tonal range. A
      previously flat looking image will get more contrast and pop.
    </para>

    <para>
      Moving the middle bar will modify the middle gray tones. Shifting it left will make the
      image look brighter, shifting it right will make it darker. This is often referred to as a
      change of image gamma.
    </para>

    <para>
      There are three color pickers in <emphasis>black</emphasis>,
      <emphasis>gray</emphasis>, and <emphasis>white</emphasis>,
      available by pressing the respectively colored
      <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_module_picker;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center" />
      icon. You can use them to sample the corresponding level directly from the image.
    </para>

    <para>
      The <quote>auto</quote> button autoadjusts the black and white point and puts the gray
      point exactly in the mean between them.
    </para>

    <para>
      The picker on the right of <quote>auto</quote> button
      autoadjusts based on a selected area on the picture.
    </para>

    <para>
      Tip: Under certain conditions, especially highly saturated blue light sources in the
      frame, the levels module may produce black pixel artifacts. See the <emphasis>gamut
      clipping</emphasis> option (<xref linkend="input_color_profile"/>) on how to mitigate this
      issue.
    </para>

    <sect5>
      <title>mode</title>
      <para>
        Set the mode of operation of this module. Defaults to <quote>RGB, linked channels</quote>.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>black</title>
      <para>
        Sets the black point in percentiles relative to the left border of the histogram.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>gray</title>
      <para>
        Sets the gray point in percentiles relative to the left and right borders of the
        histogram <emphasis>after</emphasis> having applied the black point and white point
        corrections.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>white</title>
      <para>
        Sets the white point in percentiles relative to the right border of the histogram.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>preserve colors</title>
      <para>
        Select one of the color preservation methods. The default mode
        is <quote>luminance</quote>.
      </para>
    </sect5>

  </sect4>

</sect3>
