<!DOCTYPE sect3 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect3 status="final" id="shadows_and_highlights">

  <title>Shadows and Highlights</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>modules</primary>
    <secondary>shadows and highlights</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>shadows and highlights</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>artifact mitigation</primary>
    <secondary>halos</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect4>

    <title>Overview</title>

    <informaltable frame="none" >
      <tgroup cols="2" rowsep="0" colsep="0" >
        <colspec colwidth="6*" />
        <colspec colwidth="4*" />
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              The shadows and highlights module allows adjustment to the tonal range of darker
              parts of an image (shadows) and lighter parts (highlights); it can bring back
              details in shadows and highlights by enhancing local contrast.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic width="80%" fileref="darkroom/modules/images/shadhi.png" align="center" scalefit="1" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

  </sect4>

  <sect4>

    <title>Usage</title>

    <sect5>
      <title>shadows</title>
      <para>
        This slider controls the effect on shadows; positive values will lighten up shadows
        while negative values will darken them.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>highlights</title>
      <para>
        This slider controls the effect on highlights; negative values will darken highlights
        while positive values will lighten them up.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>white point adjustment</title>
      <para>
        By default the algorithm of this modules leaves black point and white point untouched.
        In some cases an image might contain tonal variations beyond the white point, i.e. above
        a luminance value of 100. A negative shift in the white point adjustment slider allows
        to bring these values down into the proper range so that further details in the
        highlights get visible.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>soften with</title>
      <para>
        This combobox chooses the underlying blurring filter, gaussian or bilateral. Try
        bilateral filter if you experience halos with gaussian blur.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>radius</title>
      <para>
        This slider controls the radius of the involved blurring filter. Higher values give
        softer transitions between shadows and highlights but might introduce halos. Lower
        values will reduce the size of halos but may lead to an artificial look. As said,
        bilateral filter is much less prone to halo artifacts.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>compress</title>
      <para>
        This slider controls how strong the effect extends to midtones; high values reduce the
        effect to the extreme shadows and highlights; low values cause strong adjustments also
        to midtones. You normally only need to touch this parameter if you want to limit the
        effects to the extreme shadows and highlights; increase the value in this case. At 100%
        this module has no visible effect any longer as only absolute black and absolute white
        are affected.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>shadows color adjustment</title>
      <para>
        This slider controls the color saturation adjustment made to shadows; high values cause
        saturation enhancements on lightened shadows; low values cause desaturation on lightened
        shadows. It is normally safe to leave this at its default of 100%. This gives a natural
        saturation boost on shadows&nbsp;&ndash; similar to the one you would also expect in
        nature if shadows would receive more light.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>highlights color adjustment</title>
      <para>
        This slider controls the color saturation adjustment made to highlights; high values
        cause saturation enhancements on darkened highlights; low values cause desaturation on
        darkened highlights. Often highlights do not contain enough color information to give
        convincing colors when darkened. You might need to play a bit with this parameter in
        order to find the best fitting value depending on your specific image; but be aware that
        sometimes results still might not be fully satisfying.
      </para>
    </sect5>

  </sect4>

  <sect4>

    <title>Examples</title>

    <para>
      <informaltable frame="none">
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
          <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
          <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/shadhi_ex1.png" scalefit="1" width="90%" align="center" />
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Original image exposed for the outer sunlit wall to avoid clipped highlights. As
                a consequence the interior of the barn has pitch black shadows.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/shadhi_ex2.png" scalefit="1" width="90%" align="center" />
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Shadows get lightened; highlights are untouched; overall effect toned down a bit
                by <link linkend="blending_operators"><emphasis>blend mode</emphasis></link>
                <quote>normal</quote> and an opacity of 65%.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/shadhi_ex3.png" scalefit="1" width="90%" align="center" />
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Resulting image.
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </para>

  </sect4>

</sect3>
