<!DOCTYPE sect3 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect3 status="final" id="color_zones">

  <title>Color zones</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>modules</primary>
    <secondary>color zones</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>color zones</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect4>

    <title>Overview</title>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              This module selectively modifies the colors in your image. It is highly versatile
              and allows every transformation possible in the LCh colorspace.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/colorzones.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

  </sect4>

  <sect4>

    <title>Usage</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>color picker</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>
      The horizontal axis represents the range of values you can work on. The vertical axis
      shows the modifications you can apply by designing a curve. For both horizontal and
      vertical axes you can work on lightness, saturation or hue.
    </para>

    <para>
      You can click on any of the eight nodes on the curve and drag to adjust it vertically. A
      circle indicates how strong adjacent nodes will be affected. Use the scroll wheel of your
      mouse to change the circle diameter. You can also use the eight controlpoints (triangles
      which define the vertical value of the nodes) at the bottom to adjust the curve.
    </para>

    <para>
      A color picker is activated by pressing
      <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_module_picker;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center" />
      and will show the picked values in the diagram. You can switch between point and area
      sampling mode from within the global color picker panel (see
      <xref linkend="global_color_picker"/>).
    </para>

    <sect5>
      <title>tabbed controls</title>
      <para>
        You can define curves for each of the three channels <quote>lightness</quote>,
        <quote>saturation</quote>, and <quote>hue</quote> individually.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>select by</title>
      <para>
        Defines the horizontal axis, i.e. the range of values you work on. You can choose
        between <quote>lightness</quote>, <quote>saturation</quote>, and <quote>hue</quote>
        (default). Changing this parameter resets any defined curve to a straight horizontal
        line.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>mix</title>
      <para>
        Use this parameter to tune the strength of the overall effect.
      </para>
    </sect5>

  </sect4>

</sect3>
