<!DOCTYPE sect3 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect3 status="final">

  <title>Color balance</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>modules</primary>
    <secondary>color balance</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>color balance</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect4>

    <title>Overview</title>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              This module offers a versatile tool for adjusting an image's color balance.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/colorbalance.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

  </sect4>

  <sect4>

    <title>Usage</title>

    <para>
      For each of the three primary colors&nbsp;&ndash; red, green, and blue&nbsp;&ndash; there
      are three sliders <quote>lift</quote>, <quote>gamma</quote> and <quote>gain</quote> to
      control dark tones, mid tones and high tones, respectively. Changing these parameters adds
      offsets to the individual RGB channels and influences the color balance of the image.
    </para>

    <para>
      Additional <quote>factor</quote> sliders act on all colors at once. Their effect is
      similar to the controls of the <emphasis>levels</emphasis> module (see
      <xref linkend="levels"/>).
    </para>

    <para>
      The way to best envision the module's way of working is if you consider
      <quote>lift</quote>, <quote>gamma</quote> and <quote>gain</quote> as parameters
      influencing the properties of a tone curve which&nbsp;&ndash; in its original
      state&nbsp;&ndash; is a straight line going diagonally from bottom left to top right.
    </para>

    <para>
      The lift parameter adjusts the left axis intercept of the line&nbsp;&ndash; this point can
      be shifted from its default location with zero abscissa to points with negative or
      positive ones. The gamma parameter modifies the line shape&nbsp;&ndash; the default shape
      is linear and can be turned into a convex curve with increased or into a concave curve
      with lowered gamma values. Finally, the gain parameter defines the steepness of the
      curve&nbsp;&ndash; by default the curve runs diagonally, higher values lead to a steeper
      curve and lower values to a flatter one.
    </para>

    <para>
      Side note: although this module acts on RGB colors its location in pixelpipe puts it into
      the Lab color space. Accordingly the modules converts from Lab to RGB, does its color
      adjustments, and then converts back to Lab.
    </para>

    <sect5>
      <title>lift</title>
      <para>
        Adjusts the value of dark colors with individual sliders for each RGB color and with a
        <quote>factor</quote> slider acting on all three colors at once.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>gamma</title>
      <para>
        Adjusts the mid tones with individual sliders for each RGB color and with a
        <quote>factor</quote> slider acting on all three colors at once.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>gain</title>
      <para>
        Adjusts the high tones with individual sliders for each RGB color and with a
        <quote>factor</quote> slider acting on all three colors at once.
      </para>
    </sect5>

  </sect4>

</sect3>
