<!DOCTYPE sect3 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect3 status="final" id="color_look_up_table">

  <title>Color look up table</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>modules</primary>
    <secondary>color look up table</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>color look up table</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect4>

    <title>Overview</title>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              This module implements a generic color look up table in Lab space. The input is a
              list of source and target points, the complete mapping will be interpolated using
              splines. The resulting luts are editable by hand and can be created using the
              <filename>darktable-chart</filename> utility to match given input (such as
              hald-cluts and RAW/JPEG with in-camera processing pairs). See
              <xref linkend="darktable_chart"/> for details.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/colorchecker.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

  </sect4>

  <sect4>

    <title>Usage</title>

    <sect5>
      <title>color board</title>
      <para>
        When you select the module in darkroom mode, it should look something like the image
        above (configurations with more than 24 patches are shown in a 7x7 grid instead). By
        default, it will load the 24 patches of a color checker classic and initialise the
        mapping to identity (no change to the image).
      </para>
      <para>
        The grid shows a list of colored patches. The colors of the patches are the source
        points. The target color of the selected patch is shown as offsets controlled by sliders
        in the GUI under the grid of patches. An outline is drawn around patches that have been
        altered, i.e. the source and target colors differ.
      </para>
      <para>
        The selected patch is marked with a white square, and its number is displayed in the
        combo box below. Select a patch by left clicking on it, or using the combo box, or using
        the color picker.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>interaction</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>color picker</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>
        To modify the color mapping, you can change source as well as target colors.
      </para>
      <para>
        The main use case is to change the target colors. You start with an appropriate palette
        of source colors (either from the presets menu or from a style you download). You can
        then change lightness (L), green-red (a), blue-yellow (b), or saturation (C) of the
        patches' target values via sliders.
      </para>
      <para>
        To change the source color of a patch you select a new color from your image by using
        the color picker, and shift-click on the patch you want to replace. You can switch
        between point and area sampling mode from within the global color picker panel (see
        <xref linkend="global_color_picker"/>).
      </para>
      <para>
        To reset a patch, double-click it. Right-click a patch to delete it. Shift-click on
        empty space to add a new patch (with the currently picked color as source color).
      </para>
    </sect5>

  </sect4>

</sect3>
