<!DOCTYPE sect3 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
    <!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
    %darktable_dtd;
    ]>
<sect3 status="final" id="color_balance">

  <title>Color balance</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>modules</primary>
    <secondary>color balance</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>color balance</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect4>

    <title>Overview</title>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              This module offers a versatile tool for adjusting an image's color balance.
              It can be used to revert parasite color casts or to enhance the visual
              atmosphere of a picture using color grading, a popular technique in the cinema
              industry.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/colorbalance.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

  </sect4>

  <sect4>

    <title>Usage</title>

    <para>
      The color balance allows you to shift colors selectively by luminance range: shadows,
      mid-tones, and highlights. It does so using two different methods:

      <itemizedlist>

        <listitem><para>
          <emphasis>lift, gamma, gain</emphasis>, the classic way, that allows a more
          separated control of shadows versus highlights,
        </para></listitem>

        <listitem><para>
          <emphasis>slope, offset, power</emphasis>, the new standard defined by the
          American Society of Cinematographers Color Decision List <emphasis>(ASC CDL)</emphasis>,
          more suited for scene-referred editing.
        </para></listitem>

      </itemizedlist>

      Three different control layouts can be accessed by clicking on
      the shadows label: A <emphasis>vertical</emphasis> view as shown
      on the screenshot above, a <emphasis>tabulated</emphasis> view
      presenting one of the three group at a single time and a
      <emphasis>columned</emphasis> view displaying all controls
      horizontally.
    </para>

    <para>
      The master settings affect the whole image. They are not available in
      <emphasis>lift, gamma, gain (sRGB)</emphasis> mode. The slider ranges are limited
      to usual values ([50%; 150%] for saturations, [-50%; 50%] for contrast), but higher and lower
      values can be defined from keyboard inputs after a right-click on the corresponding
      slider.
    </para>

    <para>
      Side note: although this module acts on RGB colors its location in pixelpipe puts it into
      the Lab color space. Accordingly the modules converts from Lab to RGB, does its color
      adjustments, and then converts back to Lab.
    </para>

    <sect5>
      <title>Mode</title>

      <para>
        <itemizedlist>

          <listitem><para>
            <emphasis>lift, gamma, gain (sRGB)</emphasis> is the legacy mode from darktable
            2.4 and previous. In this mode, the color transformations are applied in sRGB
            color space encoded with the sRGB gamma (average gamma of 2.2).
          </para></listitem>

          <listitem><para>
            <emphasis>lift, gamma, gain (ProPhotoRGB)</emphasis> is the same as the previous
            but works in ProPhoto RGB space, encoded linearly. In this mode, the RGB parameters
            are corrected in XYZ luminance (Y channel) internally so they affect only the color,
            and only the <quote>factors</quote> adjust the luminance.
          </para></listitem>

          <listitem><para>
            <emphasis>slope, offset, power (ProPhotoRGB)</emphasis> applies the <emphasis>ASC CDL</emphasis>
            in ProPhoto RGB space, encoded linearly. Similarly to the previous mode, the RGB
            parameters are corrected in XYZ luminance internally. In this mode, the slope
            parameter acts as an exposure compensation, the offset acts as a black level
            correction, and the power acts as a gamma correction. All parameters will have some
            impact on the whole luminance range, but the slope will mostly affect the highlights,
            the offset will mostly affect the shadows, and the power will mostly affect the
            mid-tones.
          </para></listitem>

        </itemizedlist>
      </para>

      <para>
        For better efficiency, in <emphasis>slope, offset, power</emphasis>, it is recommended
        to set the slope first, then the offset, and finally the power, in this order. The
        name of the mode can be use as a mnemonic to remember the order.
      </para>

      <para>
        In <emphasis>slope, offset, power</emphasis> mode, the shadows parameter has a far heavier
        effect than in <emphasis>lift, gamma, gain</emphasis>. Switching from the former to
        the latter, you should adapt the saturation in shadows, dividing by around 10.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>Color control sliders</title>

      <para>
        These parameters affect the user interface used for the shadows, mid-tones and highlights
        controls.
      </para>

      <para>
        The <emphasis>RGBL</emphasis> controls allow direct access of the RGB parameters
        that will be sent to the algorithm and internally adjusted in XYZ luminance,
        depending on the <emphasis>mode</emphasis> used. They are the only ones stored in darktable's
        development history.
      </para>

      <para>
        The <emphasis>HSL</emphasis> controls allow a more intuitive control, but are only
        an interface: the hues and saturations are computed dynamically from and to the RGB
        parameters and never stored. During the HSL to RGB conversion, the HSL lightness is always
        assumed to be 50%, so the RGB parameters are always balanced to avoid lightness
        changes. However, during the RGB to HSL conversion, the HSL lightness is not corrected.
      </para>

      <para>
        As a consequence, editing in RGB, then in HSL, then again in RGB will not retain
        the original RGB parameters, but will normalize them so their HSL lightness is 50%.
        The difference is barely noticeable in most cases, especially using the
        modes that already correct the RGB parameters internally in XYZ luminance.
      </para>

      <para>
        In both modes, additional <quote>factor</quote> sliders act on all RGB channels at
        once. Their effect is similar to the controls of the <emphasis>levels</emphasis>
        module (see <xref linkend="levels"/>) and affect only the luminance.
      </para>

    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>Input saturation</title>
      <para>
        The input saturation is a saturation correction applied before the color balance.
        It can be used to dampen colors before adjusting the balance, to make difficult
        pictures easier to process.
        When you desaturate entirely the image, it creates a luminance-based monochrome
        picture that can be used as a luminance mask, to create color filters with the
        color balance settings, like split-toning or sepia effect
        (you might want to use blending modes then).
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>Output saturation</title>
      <para>
        The output saturation is a saturation correction applied just after the color balance.
        It is useful once you have found a proper hue balance but find the
        effect too heavy, so you can adjust the global saturation at once instead of editing
        each channel saturation separately at the expense of possibly messing the colors.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>Contrast and Contrast fulcrum</title>
      <para>
        The contrast slider allows to increase the luminance separation. The fulcrum value
        defines the luminance value that will not be affected by the contrast correction,
        so the contrast will roll over the fulcrum. Luminance values above the fulcrum
        will be amplified almost linearly. Luminance values below the fulcrum value will
        be compressed with a power function (creating a toe). This correction comes after
        the output saturation and is applied on all RGB channels separately, so hues and saturations
        might not be preserved in case of dramatic settings (shadows might be resaturated,
        highlights might be desaturated, and some color shift is to be expected).
      </para>
    </sect5>


    <sect5>
      <title>Shadows, Mid-tones, Highlights</title>
      <para>
        Depending on the mode set, the shadows settings will control either the lift or the offset,
        the mid-tones ones will control either the gamma or the power, and the highlights
        ones will control either the gain or the slope. Parameters are transferred as is
        when you change the mode.
      </para>

      <para>
        In RGBL mode, the RGB sliders range is limited to [-0.5; 0.5]. In HSL mode, the
        saturation sliders range is limited to [0%; 25%]. Values outside of these bounds
        can be defined from keyboard input after right-click on the slider.
      </para>
    </sect5>


    <sect5>
      <title>Optimize luma</title>
      <para>
        The color-picker close to the <emphasis>optimize luma</emphasis> label will
        select the whole image and optimize the <emphasis>factors</emphasis> for shadows,
        mid-tones and highlights so the average luminance of the picture is 50% Lab,
        the maximum is 100% and the minimum is 0%, at the output of this module. This
        is essentially an histogram normalization, similar to what the levels module can
        achieve. The optimizer is accurate only when used in <emphasis>slope, offset, power</emphasis>
        mode. It works only fairly in the other modes.
      </para>

      <para>
        In case you want more control, you can define three control patches using the color-pickers
        in front of each factor slider, to sample luminance in selected areas. The shadows
        color-picker samples the minimum luminance, the mid-tones one samples the average,
        and the highlights one samples the maximum luminance.
        The most sensitive parameter is the mid-tones factor,
        since selecting a slightly different area can lead to dramatic parameter changes.
        Using the factors color-pickers alone, without triggering the luma optimization,
        will allow to perform adjustments without general optimization, but each parameter is always
        computed accounting from the two others. Once patches are selected, the label becomes
        <quote>optimize luma from patches</quote>. To reset one patch, you can just redo the
        selection. Patches are not saved in the parameters and are kept only during the current
        session.
      </para>

      <para>
        It is important no note that the luminance adjustment performed targets only the
        output of the color balance module and does not account for other luminance adjustments
        performed in modules coming later in the pixelpipe (filmic, tone curve, color zones,
        levels, global tonemapping, etc.). Using the color balance to remap the luminance
        globally on the image is not recommended because it does not preserve the original colors,
        and modules such as tone curves or filmic are better suited for this purpose.
        Luminance adjustments in color balance are better suited for local correction,
        in combination with color adjustments, for color-grading with masks.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>Neutralize colors</title>
      <para>
        In an image where some areas are exposed to direct sunlight and some areas are
        exposed to reflected light (shadows), or when several artificial light sources are present
        simultaneously, shadows and highlights often have different color temperatures.
        These images are particularly difficult to correct since no general white balance will
        match all the colors at once. The color neutralization optimizer aims at helping you find
        the complementary color for shadows, midtones, and highlights so all the color casts
        are reverted, and the average color of the picture is a neutral grey.
      </para>

      <para>
        Similarly to the luma optimization, the color-picker next to the <emphasis>neutralize colors</emphasis>
        label will trigger a general optimization over the whole picture. This works fairly in
        landscape photography, or any photography with a full spectrum of colors and
        luminances. For night and events photography, this will most likely fail and you will
        need to input manually the sampling areas with the color-pickers in front of each hue slider.
        For the highlights sample, use a color exposed to spotlights that should be neutral
        white or light grey. For the shadows sample, use a color exposed to ambient light
        that should be neutral black or dark grey. For the mid-tones sample, use a color exposed
        by both ambient and spot lights.
      </para>

      <para>
        The success of the optimization depends on the quality of the samples. Not every
        set of samples will converge to a good solution, you need to ensure the color
        patches you choose are really neutral color in real life. In many cases the optimizer
        will output the correct hue but an excessive saturation that will need some extra tweaking.
        In some cases, no valid optimization will be delivered and you will need to reset
        the saturation parameters and start over, or simply stop after the patches selection.
        Notice that in the auto-optimization the maximum saturation is 25% which might
        not be enough in very few cases but will avoid inconsistent results in most.
      </para>

      <para>
        If you select color patches from the hues color-pickers, without triggering the optimization,
        the software will only perform one round of optimization and stop so it allows you
        to control each luminance range separately and avoid divergence of the solution in corner cases.
        The hue and saturation corrections are computed accounting for the two other
        luminance ranges and the three factors, and will always output the complementary color
        of the selected area. If you want to reinforce the color of the area instead, you can then add 180°
        to the computed hue. Once patches are selected the label becomes
        <quote>neutralize colors from patches</quote>. To reset one patch you can just redo the
        selection. Patches are not saved in the parameters and are kept only during the current
        session. The parameters found by the automatic neutralization are accurate only in
        <emphasis>slope, offset, power</emphasis> mode, but can work to some extent in
        <emphasis>lift, gamma, gain</emphasis> too.
      </para>
    </sect5>

  </sect4>

  <sect4>
    <title>Examples</title>

    <para>
      Several presets are provided in the module to help you understand how it can be used.
    </para>

    <para>
      The teal/orange color-grading preset is a very popular look in cinema and a good showcase model.
      It is meant to be used with two instances and masks: the first instance will exclude
      skin tones and will shift neutral colors toward teal blue. The second will partially revert
      the first one and add more vibrance on skin tones only. Together they will help creating
      separation between subjects and backgrounds. The masking and blending parameters will
      need to be tweaked to suit every picture, though.
    </para>

    <para>
      Other presets provide Kodak film emulations. In the same way you can recreate any film
      look you like with color balance.
    </para>

  </sect4>

</sect3>
