<!DOCTYPE sect3 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect3 status="final" id="color_zones">

  <title>Color zones</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>modules</primary>
    <secondary>color zones</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>color zones</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect4>

    <title>Overview</title>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              This module selectively modifies the colors in your image. It is highly versatile
              and allows every transformation possible in the LCh colorspace.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/colorzones.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

  </sect4>

  <sect4>

    <title>Usage</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>color picker</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>
      The horizontal axis represents the range of values you can work on. The vertical axis
      shows the modifications you can apply by designing a curve. For both horizontal and
      vertical axes you can work on lightness, saturation or hue.
    </para>

    <para>
      You can click on any of the eight nodes on the curve and drag to adjust it vertically. A
      circle indicates how strong adjacent nodes will be affected. Use the scroll wheel of your
      mouse to change the circle diameter. You can also use the eight controlpoints (triangles
      which define the vertical value of the nodes) at the bottom to adjust the curve.
    </para>

    <para>
      A color picker is activated by pressing
      <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_module_picker;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center" />
      and will show the picked values in the diagram. You can use an
      area sampling mode by using <emphasis>Ctrl+Click</emphasis>.
    </para>

    <para>
      A second color picker can be used to directly change the curve
      based on the sampled area. A <emphasis>Click</emphasis> on
      <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_module_action_picker;"
                     scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center" /> will
      activate the action picker. Then, on the picture, a
      <emphasis>Ctrl+Click+Drag</emphasis> will create a positive curve for
      the sampled area and a <emphasis>Shift+Click+Drag</emphasis> a negative curve.
    </para>

    <sect5>
      <title>tabbed controls</title>
      <para>
        You can define curves for each of the three channels <quote>lightness</quote>,
        <quote>saturation</quote>, and <quote>hue</quote> individually.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>edit by area</title>
      <para>
        Control the interaction mode with the curve. When <emphasis>edit by area</emphasis>
        is selected the nodes' axis coordinates are fixed. This is the
        default mode up to darktable version 2.6.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>mask display</title>
      <para>
        By clicking <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_module_mask;"
        scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center" /> the pixels affected
        by the curve are displayed directly on center area.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>select by</title>
      <para>
        Defines the horizontal axis, i.e. the range of values you work on. You can choose
        between <quote>lightness</quote>, <quote>saturation</quote>, and <quote>hue</quote>
        (default). Changing this parameter resets any defined curve to a straight horizontal
        line.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>process mode</title>
      <para>
        Choose between a <quote>smooth</quote> (default) or
        <quote>strong</quote> processing mode which alter the final effect.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>mix</title>
      <para>
        Use this parameter to tune the strength of the overall effect.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>interpolation method</title>
      <para>
        The interpolation is the process by which a continuous curve is derived from a few
        punctual nodes. As this process is never perfect, several methods are offered that
        can alleviate the potential issues you may encounter with some nodes setups.
      </para>
      <para>
        Arguably, the most visually pleasing method is the <quote>cubic spline</quote>. Since
        it gives smooth curves, the contrast in the image is better enhanced. However, this
        method is very sensitive to the nodes position, and can produce cusps and oscillations
        when the nodes are too close to each other, or when there are too many of them.
        This method works best when there are only 4 to 5 nodes, evenly spaced.
      </para>
      <para>
        The <quote>centripetal spline</quote> is a method designed specifically to avoid
        cusps and oscillations, but as a drawback it will follow the nodes more loosely.
        It is very robust, no matter the number of nodes and their spacing, but will produce
        a more faded and dull contrast.
      </para>
      <para>
        The <quote>monotonic spline</quote> is a method designed specifically to give a monotonic
        interpolation, meaning that there will be none of the oscillations the cubic spline may
        produce. This method is very suitable when you try to build an analytical function
        from a node interpolation (for example: exponential, logarithm, power, etc.). Such
        functions are provided as presets. It is a good trade-off between the two
        aforementioned methods.
      </para>
    </sect5>

  </sect4>

</sect3>
