<!DOCTYPE sect3 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect3 status="final" id="input_color_profile">

  <title>Input color profile</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>modules</primary>
    <secondary>input color profile</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>input color profile</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>color management</primary>
    <secondary>input color profile</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>artifact mitigation</primary>
    <secondary>blue light sources</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>artifact mitigation</primary>
    <secondary>black pixels</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>gamut clipping</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect4>

    <title>Overview</title>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              This module can be used to override darktable's automatic allocation of input
              color profile if there is an alternative that more closely matches your original
              image's color space.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/inputcolorprofile.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

  </sect4>

  <sect4>

    <title>Usage</title>

    <para>
      In this module you define the input color profile, i.e. how colors of your input image are
      to be interpreted. You also have an option to have colors confined to a certain gamut in
      order to mitigate some (infrequent) color artifacts.
    </para>

    <sect5>
      <title>profile</title>
      <para>
        Choose the profile or color matrix to apply, darktable offers many widespread matrices
        along with an enhanced matrix for some camera models. The enhanced matrices were
        processed by the darktable team in order to provide a look closer to the manufacturer's.
      </para>
      <para>
        You can also supply your own input ICC profiles and put them into
        $DARKTABLE/share/darktable/color/in or $HOME/.config/darktable/color/in. $DARKTABLE is
        used here to represent darktable's installation directory and $HOME your home directory.
        One common source of ICC profiles is the software that is shipped with your camera; it
        often contains profiles specific to your camera model. You may need to activate module
        <emphasis>unbreak input profile</emphasis> (see <xref linkend="unbreak_input_profile"/>)
        to use your extra profiles.
      </para>
      <para>
        If your input image is a low dynamic range file like JPEG, or a raw in DNG format, it
        might already contain an embedded ICC profile which darktable will use as a default. You
        can always overrule darktable and select a different profile. Select <quote>embedded icc
        profile</quote> to restore the default.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>gamut clipping</title>
      <para>
        This combobox lets you activate a color clipping mechanism. In most cases you can leave
        it at its default <quote>off</quote> state. However, if your image shows some specific
        features like highly saturated blue light sources, gamut clipping might be useful to
        avoid black pixel artifacts. See <xref linkend="possible_color_artifacts"/> for more
        background information.
      </para>
      <para>
        You can select from a list of RGB profiles. Input colors with a saturation that exceeds
        the permissible range of the selected profile get clipped to a maximum value.
        <quote>linear Rec2020 RGB</quote> and <quote>Adobe RGB (compatible)</quote> allow for a
        broader range of unclipped colors, while <quote>sRGB</quote> and <quote>linear Rec709
        RGB</quote> produce a tighter clipping. You should select the profile that prevents
        artifacts while still maintaining highest color dynamics.
      </para>
    </sect5>

  </sect4>

  <sect4>

    <title>Examples</title>

    <para>
      <informaltable frame="none">
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
          <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
          <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/inputcolorprofile_ex1.png" scalefit="1" width="90%" align="center" />
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Close-up of a blue light source (LED) with gamut clipping off. The activated
                levels module produces a ring of black pixel artifacts.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/inputcolorprofile_ex2.png" scalefit="1" width="90%" align="center" />
              </entry>
              <entry>
                The same image and processing with gamut clipping set to <quote>linear Rec2020
                RGB </quote>.
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </para>

  </sect4>

</sect3>
