<!DOCTYPE sect3 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect3 status="final" id="output_color_profile">

  <title>Output color profile</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>modules</primary>
    <secondary>output color profile</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>output color profile</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>color management</primary>
    <secondary>output color profile</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect4>

    <title>Overview</title>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>
                This module manages the output profiles for display and export as well as the
                rendering intent to be used when mapping between the different color spaces.
              </para>

              <para>
                darktable comes with pre-defined profiles sRGB, AdobeRGB, XYZ and linear RGB but
                you can provide additional profiles by placing these in
                $DARKTABLE/share/darktable/color/out and $HOME/.config/darktable/color/out.
                $DARKTABLE is used here to represent your chosen darktable installation
                directory and $HOME your home directory.
              </para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/outputcolorprofile.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

  </sect4>

  <sect4>

    <title>Usage</title>

    <para>
      A configuration parameter <quote>always try to use littlecms2</quote> in darktable's
      <emphasis>core options</emphasis> (see <xref linkend="core_options"/>) defines how
      darktable renders colors for display and export. If the configuration parameter is
      disabled darktable uses a simplified and very fast internal rendering algorithm. If the
      option is checked the external library
      <ulink url="http://www.littlecms.com/"><emphasis>littlecms2</emphasis></ulink> with higher
      accuracy and significantly higher processing overhead is used instead.
    </para>

    <sect5>
      <title>output intent</title>
      <para>
        Sets the rendering intent for output/export. You can easily override this setting
        whenever you do exports from lighttable mode.
        <informaltable frame="none" width="80%">
          <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
            <colspec colwidth='4*'/>
            <colspec colwidth='6*'/>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <emphasis>perceptual</emphasis>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  Suited to pictures as it maintains the relative position of colors. This is
                  usually the best choice.
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <emphasis>relative colorimetric</emphasis>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  Out-of-gamut colors are converted to colors having the same lightness, but
                  different saturation. Other colors remain unmodified.
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <emphasis>saturation</emphasis>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  Saturation is kept but lightness is slightly changed.
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <emphasis>absolute colorimetric</emphasis>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  Keep the white point.
                </entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
      </para>
      <para>
        Only rendering with littelcms2 gives you a choice of rendering intent. The option is
        hidden, if darktable's internal rendering routines are used.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>display intent</title>
      <para>
        Sets the rendering intent for your display. See above for available options.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>output profile</title>
      <para>
        Sets the color profile for output/export, causing darktable to render colors with this
        profile. darktable embeds the profile data into the output file if supported 
        by the file format&nbsp;&ndash; this allows other applications reading the file to 
        correctly interpret its colors.
      </para>

      <para>
        Some file formats&nbsp;&ndash; namely PNG&nbsp;&ndash; do not support embedded profiles 
        by their specification. However, there is an established de-facto standard to embed
        profiles which darktable adheres to. Beware that some applications might fail to correctly 
        handle those profiles and render colors incorrectly.
      </para>

      <para>
        As not all applications, e.g. image viewers, are aware of color profiles, a general recommendation 
        is to stick to <emphasis>sRGB</emphasis> as the default output profile. You should only deviate from 
        <emphasis>sRGB</emphasis> if this is really required and if you know what you are doing.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>softproof profile</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>color management</primary>
        <secondary>softproof</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>color management</primary>
        <secondary>gamut check</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>
        Sets the color profile for softproofing.
      </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>softproof</emphasis> allows you to preview your image rendered using a printer
        profile so as to see how colors will end up on the final print and is toggled on and off
        by pressing <emphasis>ctrl-s</emphasis>.
      </para>
      <para>
        Likewise <emphasis>gamut check</emphasis> is toggled on and off by pressing
        <emphasis>ctrl-g</emphasis>; this function highlights in cyan all pixels out of gamut
        with respect to the selected softproof profile.
      </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>softproof</emphasis> and <emphasis>gamut check</emphasis> are mutually
        exclusive modes that can be activated at any place in darkroom mode and when this module
        is in focus the status is displayed below the image.
      </para>
      <para>
        Tip: at other times it may not be obvious if the <emphasis>softproof</emphasis> mode is
        still active or not. If in doubt press <emphasis>ctrl-g</emphasis>, which will switch to
        <emphasis>gamut check</emphasis> and be clearly distinguishable by cyan marked pixels.
        Press <emphasis>ctrl-g</emphasis> again and you are back to normal display mode.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>display profile</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>color management</primary>
        <secondary>display profile</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>monitor profile</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>display profile</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>
        Sets the color profile for the display. The additional option <quote>system display
        profile</quote> is the preferred setting when working with a calibrated display; the
        profile is taken either from your system's color manager or from your X display server.
        In <emphasis>gui options</emphasis> (see <xref linkend="gui_options"/>) you can specify
        which method to use.
      </para>
    </sect5>

  </sect4>

</sect3>
