<sect3 status="draft" id="output color profile"><title>Output color profile</title>
	<sect4><title>Overview</title>
		<informaltable frame="none"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
				<colspec colwidth="6*"/>
				<colspec colwidth="4*"/>
				<tbody>
					<row>						
						<entry>This module manages the output profile both for display and for export.					
						</entry>
						<entry>
							<graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/outputcolorprofile.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
						</entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</informaltable>

	</sect4>

	<sect4><title>Usage</title>
                <sect5><title>output intent</title>
          		<para>Sets the rendering intent for output/export. You can easily override this setting whenever you do exports from lighttable mode.
				<informaltable frame="none" width="80%"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
					<colspec colwidth='4*'/>
                                        <colspec colwidth='6*'/>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry><emphasis>perceptual</emphasis></entry>
							<entry>Suited to pictures. It scales one gamut to fit into the other while maintaining the relative position of colors. 
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><emphasis>relative colorimetric</emphasis></entry>
							<entry>Out-of-gamut colors are converted to colors having the same lightness,
							but different saturation. Other colors remain unmodified. </entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><emphasis>saturation</emphasis></entry>
							<entry> Saturation is kept but lightness is slightly changed.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><emphasis>absolute colorimetric</emphasis></entry>
							<entry>Keep the white point.</entry>
						</row>

					</tbody>
				</tgroup></informaltable></para>
                </sect5>
                <sect5><title>display intent</title>
          		<para>Sets the rendering intent for your display. See above for available options.</para>
                </sect5>
                <sect5><title>output profile</title>
          		<para>Sets the color profile for output/export. darktable comes with pre-defined internal profiles: sRGB, AdobeRGB, XYZ and linear RGB.
                        Additional profiles to be used are picked up from $DARKTABLE/share/darktable/color/out and 
                        $HOME/.config/darktable/color/out.</para>
                        <para>$DARKTABLE is used here as a placeholder for darktable's installation directory and $HOME 
                        is your home directory.</para>
                </sect5>
                <sect5><title>softproof profile</title>
          		<para>Sets the color profile for softproof. Profiles to be used are picked up from $DARKTABLE/share/darktable/color/out and 
                        $HOME/.config/darktable/color/out.</para>

          		<para><quote>softproof</quote> is toggled on/off by pressing <emphasis>s</emphasis>; this function allows you to preview the image rendered using a 
	        	printer profile, to see how colors will end up on the final print.</para>

        		<para>Likewise <quote>gamut check</quote> is toggled on/off by pressing <emphasis>g</emphasis>; this function marks all pixels, which are out of gamut
                        with respect to the selected softproof profile, by showing them in cyan. Softproof and Gamut Check are mutually exclusive 
                        modes.</para>

                        <para>Softproof and Gamut Check can be activated at any place in darkroom mode. Only if module this module is in
                        focus, you will get the status displayed left below the center image. Especially for mode Softproof this may raise doubts,
                        if it is still active or not. If in doubt press <emphasis>g</emphasis>, which will switch to Gamut Check and will be 
                        clearly discernible by cyan marked pixels. Press <emphasis>g</emphasis> again and you are back to normal display without Softproof 
                        or Gamut Check.
                        </para>  
                </sect5>
                <sect5><title>display profile</title>
          		<para>Sets the color profile for the display. Profiles to be used is picked up from $DARKTABLE/share/darktable/color/out and 
                        $HOME/.config/darktable/color/out. The additional option "system display profile" is taken directly from your system's
                        color manager or from your X Server. When working with a calibrated display this is the preferred option to choose.</para>
                </sect5>
	</sect4>
</sect3>
