<chapter id="tethering chapter">
<chapterinfo>
<keywordset>
  <keyword>tethering</keyword>
  <keyword>view</keyword>
</keywordset>
</chapterinfo>
<title>Tethering</title>
<para>The tethering view is where you remote control and capture images from your connected camera directly into darktable.</para>
<screenshot>
  <screeninfo>The tethering view</screeninfo>
  <graphic fileref="tethering/images/tethering_view.png" scalefit="1" width="80%"></graphic>
</screenshot>

<sect1>
  <title>Overview</title>
  <para>To use the tethering feature you need to connect your camera to your PC using an USB cable. Your desktop environment might ask a question of what you want to do.
        In that case <quote>unmount/eject</quote> is the answer. This is required to unlock the camera so darktable can lock it for usage.</para>
  
  <para>When your camera is connected, head over to the import panel in lighttable. If your camera is not visible in this panel, hit the <quote>scan devices</quote> button and it will 
        appear with two functions: <quote>import from camera</quote> and <quote>tethered shoot</quote>, the latter button is the one you should press to enter tethering mode.</para>
  
  <para>darktable uses gphoto2 to interface with your camera. If you have problems to find the connected camera as described above, do check the troubleshoot section in 
        this chapter in order to verify that your camera is supported for use with tethering.</para>  

  <sect2 status="final">
    <title>Tethering</title>
    <informaltable frame="none"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
      <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
      <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
      <tbody>
	<row>						
	  <entry>In the center view images are shown while you capture them. You can get an exposure by either using darktable's userinterface
	  or manually triggering a capture on your camera. If you are using LiveView it will be shown in darktable's center view.
	  </entry>
	  <entry>
	    <graphic fileref="tethering/images/tethering_center_view.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
	  </entry>
	</row>
      </tbody>
    </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

    <para>When entering tethering view, a filmroll will be created using the same structure as defined when you import from the camera. Job code will be predefined as <quote>capture</quote>.</para>

    <para>If you want to group your captures into different filmrolls, you should use the session panel in right side. When entering a new name and hitting enter, a new filmroll 
          will be created and captured images will go into this new filmroll.</para>

    <para>darktable provides some nifty tools to setup a capture using the user interface. You can setup timelapse captures and brackets for HDR creations. The configuration 
          is so dynamic that you can create sequential capture of brackets - go figure... For more information read the documentation about capture panel and the examples
          in this chapter.</para>

  </sect2>
</sect1>

<!-- Panels -->
<xi:include href="panels/panels.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>

<!-- Examples -->
<xi:include href="examples/examples.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>

<!-- Toubleshooting -->
<xi:include href="troubleshoot.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>

</chapter>
