<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<chapter status="final" id="tethering_chapter">

  <chapterinfo>
    <keywordset>
      <keyword>tethering</keyword>
      <keyword>view</keyword>
    </keywordset>
  </chapterinfo>

  <title>Tethering</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>tethering view</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    The tethering view allows you to capture images directly into darktable from your connected
    camera.
  </para>

  <para>
    <screenshot>

      <screeninfo>The tethering view</screeninfo>

      <graphic fileref="images/tethering_view.png" scalefit="1" width="80%"></graphic>

    </screenshot>
  </para>

  <sect1 status="final" id="tethering_overview">

    <title>Overview</title>

    <para>
      To use the tethering feature you need to connect your camera to your PC using a USB cable.
      Your computer might ask to mount or view the connected camera. Do not mount or view the
      camera. If that happens automatically, you will need to <quote>unmount/eject</quote> the
      camera. This is required to unlock the camera so darktable can lock it for usage.
    </para>

    <para>
      After the USB cable is connected, look at the import panel in lighttable mode (see
      <xref linkend="import"/>). If your camera is not visible in this panel, click the
      <quote>scan devices</quote> button and it will appear with two functions: <quote>import
      from camera</quote> and <quote>tethered shoot</quote>. Click <quote>tethered shoot</quote>
      to enter the tethering mode.
    </para>

    <para>
      darktable uses gphoto2 to interface with your camera. If you have problems finding the
      connected camera as described above, check the troubleshoot section in this chapter in
      order to verify your camera has tethering support.
    </para>

    <sect2 status="final" id="tethering_overview_tethering">

      <title>Tethering</title>

      <informaltable frame="none">
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
          <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
          <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                In the center view images are shown while you capture them. You can get an
                exposure by either using darktable's userinterface or manually triggering a
                capture on your camera. If you are using LiveView it will be shown in
                darktable's center view.
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <graphic fileref="tethering/images/tethering_center_view.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>

      <para>
        When entering tethering view, a film roll will be created using the same structure as
        defined when you import from the camera. Job code will be predefined as
        <quote>capture</quote>.
      </para>

      <para>
        If you want to group your captures into different film rolls, you should use the session
        panel in right side. When entering a new name and pressing enter, a new film roll will
        be created and captured images will go into this new film roll.
      </para>

      <para>
        darktable provides some nifty tools to setup a capture in the user interface. You can
        setup timelapse captures and brackets for HDR creations. The configuration is so dynamic
        that you can create sequential capture of brackets&nbsp;&ndash; go figure... For more
        information read the documentation about the capture panel and the examples in this
        chapter.
      </para>

    </sect2>

  </sect1>

<!-- Panels -->

  <xi:include href="panels/panels.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>

<!-- Examples -->

  <xi:include href="examples/examples.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>

<!-- Troubleshooting -->

  <xi:include href="troubleshoot.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>

</chapter>
