<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
                <!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../dtd/darktable.dtd">
                %darktable_dtd;
                ]>
<sect1 status="final" id="tethering_troubleshoot">

  <title>Troubleshoot</title>

  <sect2 status="final" id="tethering_troubleshoot_supported">

    <title>Verify that your camera is supported</title>

    <para>
      This troubleshooting guide will give you steps to verify your camera can be used with
      tethering. This is done using the gphoto2 commandline tools. This is what darktable uses
      to interface with your camera.
    </para>

    <orderedlist>

      <listitem><para>
        Verify that camera is detected
      </para>

      <para>
        The following command will verify a camera that is connected to the computer and
        detected by gphoto2. Find your camera port name to use it in the following tests below.
        Usually port <quote>usb:</quote> will be enough and therefore used in these examples.
      </para>

      <para>
<programlisting>env LANG=C gphoto2 --auto-detect
</programlisting>
      </para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>
        Verify camera driver abilities
      </para>

      <para>
        Execute the following command and verify that the <emphasis>capture choices</emphasis>
        ability supports <quote>Image</quote> and <emphasis>configuration support</emphasis> is
        <quote>yes</quote>. darktable will check these two abilities and decide if
        <quote>tethered shoot</quote> button should be shown or not.
      </para>

      <para>
<programlisting>env LANG=C gphoto2 --port usb: --abilities
</programlisting>
      </para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>
        Verify camera remote capture
      </para>

      <para>
        This step will verify that your camera can be remotely controlled; that it can capture
        an image, download it to your computer and display it within darktable.
      </para>

      <para>
<programlisting>env LANG=C gphoto2 --port usb: --capture-image-and-download
</programlisting>
      </para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>
        Verify camera tethered capture
      </para>

      <para>
        And this last step tests if your camera supports events which darktable heavily relies
        on. Running this command will make the gphoto2 process wait for an image capture event
        which you must manually trigger on your camera. If successful, the image will be
        downloaded to your computer.
      </para>

      <para>
<programlisting>env LANG=C gphoto2 --port usb: --capture-tethered
</programlisting>
      </para></listitem>

    </orderedlist>

  </sect2>

  <sect2 status="final" id="tethering_troubleshoot_now_what">

    <title>So, now what?</title>

    <para>
      If any of the steps above failed, there are problems with your specific camera and driver.
      Please report the issues to gphoto2 mailing list for further help. You can find the
      mailing list at <ulink url="http://www.gphoto.org/mailinglists/">www.gphoto.org</ulink>.
      Add the following flags to the failed command above for better support and attach the log
      output to your mail:
    </para>

    <para>
<programlisting>--debug --debug-file gphoto2_debug.log
</programlisting>
    </para>

    <para>
      If you successfully went through all the tests above, your camera will most likely be
      supported by darktable. Even if successful, if you stumble upon a problem in darktable,
      please file a bug at <ulink url="https://www.darktable.org/redmine">redmine</ulink>.
      Please attach the log outputs from the steps above and the log file output generated after
      starting darktable with the following command.
    </para>

    <para>
<programlisting>darktable -d camctl 2&gt;1 &gt;camctl.log
</programlisting>
    </para>

  </sect2>

</sect1>
