<sect1>
  <title>Troubleshoot</title>
  <sect2>
    <title>Verify that your camera is supported</title>
	<para>This troubleshoting guide will give you steps how to verify that your camera can be used
	with tethering. This is mainly done using the gphoto2 commandline tools as this is what 
	darktable uses to interface with your camera.
	</para>
	
	<orderedlist>
	  <listitem><para>Verify that camera is detected</para>
	    <para>The following command will provide which cameras are detected and connected to the computer.
	    Find your camera port name to use it in the following tests below. Usally port <command>usb:</command> 
	    will be enough and therefore used in these examples.
	    <programlisting>
	      env LANG=C gphoto2 --auto-detect
	    </programlisting>
	    </para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem><para>Verify camera driver abillities</para>
	    <para>Execute the following command and verify that the <emphasis>capture choices</emphasis> ability supports <quote>Image</quote> and 
	    <emphasis>configuration support</emphasis> is <quote>yes</quote>. darktable will check these two abilities and decide if <quote>tethered shoot</quote> button 
	    should be shown or not.
	    <programlisting>
	      env LANG=C gphoto2 --port usb: --abilities
	    </programlisting>
	    </para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem><para>Verify camera remote capture</para>
	    <para>This step will verify that your camera can be remotely controlled; that it can capture an image and then
	    download it to your computer by software.
	    <programlisting>
	      env LANG=C gphoto2 --port usb: --capture-image-and-download
	    </programlisting>
	    </para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem><para>Verify camera tethered capture</para>
	    <para>And this last step tests if your camera supports events which darktable heavily relies on. Running this command will
	    make the gphoto2 process wait for an image capture event which you must manually trigger on your camera. On success an event is 
           fetch and an the image will download.
	    <programlisting>
	      env LANG=C gphoto2 --port usb: --capture-tethered
	    </programlisting>
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</orderedlist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title>Soo now what?</title>
    <para>If any of the steps above failed, there are problems with your specific camera and driver. Please report the issues to 
    gphoto2 mailing list for further help. Add the following flags to the command above that failed for better support and attach the
    log output to your mail:
    <programlisting>
    --debug --debug-file gphoto2_debug.log
    </programlisting>
    </para>

    <para>If you successfully went through all the tests above, your camera will likely be supported by darktable. 
    If you anyway stumble into a problem in darktable please file a bug at <ulink url="http://www.darktable.org/redmine">redmine</ulink>. 
    Please attach outputs of the steps above and the log file output while running darktable with the following command.
    <programlisting>
      darktable -d camctl 2&gt;1 &gt;camctl.log
    </programlisting>
    </para>
  </sect2>

</sect1>
