<!DOCTYPE sect3 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
    <!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
    %darktable_dtd;
    ]>
<sect3 status="final" id="filmic">

  <title>Filmic</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>modules</primary>
    <secondary>filmic</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>filmic</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect4>

    <title>Overview</title>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>
                This module compresses the tonal range of an image by reproducing the tone and
                color response of classic film. Doing so, it will protect the colors and the
                contrast in mid-tones, recover the shadows, and compress bright highlights. It
                is very suitable in portrait photography, especially in back-lighting
                situations, but will need extra care when details need to be preserved in
                highlights (e.g. clouds).
              </para>

              <para>
                The module is derived from the same named module in Blender 3D modeller by T. J.
                Sobotka. While it is primarily intended to recover high-dynamic range from raw
                sensor data, it can be used with any image in replacement of the base curve
                module. A full tutorial with examples and comments on the results can be found
                on
                <ulink url="https://eng.aurelienpierre.com/2018/11/30/filmic-darktable-and-the-quest-of-the-hdr-tone-mapping/"><emphasis>its
                developer's website</emphasis></ulink>.
              </para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/filmic.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

  </sect4>

  <sect4>

    <title>Prerequisites</title>

    <para>
      In order to get the best out of filmic, images need some preparation:
      <itemizedlist>

        <listitem><para>
          In-camera, expose the shot <quote>to the right</quote>. This implies under exposing
          the shot so that the highlights are at the right of the histogram, just on the verge
          of clipping, but not clipped. It does not matter if the picture preview is very dark
          on your camera screen: as long as highlights are unclipped, filmic should be able to
          recover details from the raw data. Beware that clipped data are not recoverable. Some
          cameras have a clipping alert preview to help you diagnose this, and some even have an
          highlight-priority exposure mode.
        </para></listitem>

        <listitem><para>
          In darktable's exposure module, correct the black level and the exposure value to
          avoid any clipping. It is especially important to avoid negative pixels values (in
          black areas), because they will be clipped in filmic. For some cameras models (Canon,
          mainly), rawspeed, the raw decoding library of darktable, may set an exaggerated black
          level, resulting in crushed blacks and negative values. If so, brighten the blacks by
          setting a negative black level value in the exposure module.
        </para></listitem>

        <listitem><para>
          If you plan on using filmic's auto-tuners, use the white balance module first to
          correct any color casts and get neutral colors. In RGB color spaces, luminance and
          chrominance are linked, and filmic's luminance detection relies on accurate measures
          of both. If your picture is very noisy, add an initial step of denoising to help the
          black exposure readings, and use a high quality demosaicing.
        </para></listitem>

        <listitem><para>
          If you plan using filmic's chrominance preservation mode, avoid using any tone mapping
          module as well as the base curve module. These may produce unpredictible color shifts
          that would make the chrominance preservation useless. Neither of these modules is
          usually needed if you use filmic.
        </para></listitem>

      </itemizedlist>
    </para>

  </sect4>

  <sect4>

    <title>Usage</title>

    <para>
      There are 4 steps in the filmic process:
      <itemizedlist>

        <listitem><para>
          Apply a logarithmic shaper to the RGB signal, to raise the midtones luminance in the
          same way human eyes and film respond to lightness. This is similar to what
          <emphasis>unbreak input profile</emphasis> does in its logarithmic mode.
        </para></listitem>

        <listitem><para>
          Apply an S-shaped parametric curve to enhance the contrast and remap the grey value to
          the middle grey of the display. This is similar to what the base curve or tone curve
          modules do.
        </para></listitem>

        <listitem><para>
          Apply a selective desaturation on extreme luminance values so that shadows degrade
          progressively toward pure black and highlights degrade progressively toward pure
          white.
        </para></listitem>

        <listitem><para>
          Apply an inverse gamma transfer function to linearize the output for the display
          gamma. Having a gamma correction applied on top of logarithmically encoded data would
          result in a double-up, with the luminance raised twice.
        </para></listitem>

      </itemizedlist>
    </para>

    <para>
      The sliders' ranges of filmic are limited to usual and safe values, but values are allowed
      out of these ranges by clicking on the sliders with the right button and inputting values
      on the keyboard. Filmic has no neutral parameters resulting in a no-operation: as soon as
      the module is enabled, the image is always at least slightly affected. The default
      parameters are tuned to have minimal impact on most pictures.
    </para>

    <sect5>
      <title>Middle-grey luminance</title>
      <para>
        The middle-grey luminance is the luminance in XYZ space of the scene referred 18% grey.
        Its color picker tool reads the average luminance over the drawn area. If you happen to
        have a grey card or a color chart (IT8 chart or colorchecker) shot in the scene lighting
        conditions, then the grey color picker tool can be used to quickely sample the luminance
        of the grey patch on the picture. In other situations, the color picker can be used to
        sample the average luminance of the subject.
      </para>
      <para>
        This setting has an effect on the picture that is analogous to a lightness correction.
        Values close to 100% will not compress the highlights but will fail to recover shadows.
        Values close to 0% will recover greatly the shadows but will compress the highlights
        more harshely and result in local-contrast losses. The standard middle-grey value for
        linearly encoded camera RGB is 18%. Good values of grey are usually the average
        luminance of the whole picture or of the subject. Values much higher than 18% will make
        the filmic S curve difficult to control. In studio and indoors (low dynamic range
        scenes), proper grey values will be found between 15-18%. In high dynamic range scenes
        (landscapes, back-lit portraits), proper grey values will lie between 1.25 and 9%.
      </para>
      <para>
        When modifying the middle-grey luminance, the white and black exposures are
        automatically slided accordingly, to preserve the dynamic range from clipping and to
        help you set find the righ parameter faster. If you are not happy with the auto
        adjustment performed by the grey slider, you can correct again the white and black
        exposure parameters afterwards.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>White relative exposure</title>
      <para>
        The white relative exposure is the number of stops (EV) between pure white and the
        middle grey. It is the right bound of the dynamic range. It should be adjusted to avoid
        highlight clipping. The white exposure color picker tool reads the maximum luminance in
        XYZ space over the drawn area, assumes it is pure white, and sets the white exposure
        parameter to remap the reading to 100% luminance.
      </para>
      <para>
        When the grey is set at 18%, the white exposure will always be around 2.45EV. When the
        grey is set at 100%, the white exposure should be set at 0EV.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>Black relative exposure</title>
      <para>
        The black relative exposure is the number of stops (EV) between pure black and the
        middle grey. It is the left bound of the dynamic range. The black exposure color-picker
        tool reads the minimum luminance in XYZ space over the drawn area, assumes it is pure
        black, and sets the black exposure parameter to remap the minimum reading to 0%
        luminance. The black color picker measurement is very sensitive to noise, and cannot
        identify if the minimum luminance is pure black (actual data) or just noise. It works
        better on low ISO pictures and with high quality demosaicing. When the color picker puts
        the black exposure at -16EV, it is a sign that the measure failed and you need to adjust
        it manually.
      </para>
      <para>
        The black relative exposure allows you to choose how far you want to recover lowlights.
        On the contrary to the white exposure it will not be possible to completely avoid
        clipping blacks. When the black exposure is very low, the filmic S curve becomes very
        difficult to control and the final contrast is often faded. Every camera sensor has a
        maximum physical dynamic range for each ISO value (you can find them measured on
        <ulink url="https://www.dxomark.com/"><emphasis>DXOmark</emphasis></ulink> or
        <ulink url="https://www.dpreview.com/"><emphasis>DPreview</emphasis></ulink>), the
        software dynamic range in filmic (dynamic range = white exposure - black exposure)
        should generally not be greater than the physical dynamic range of the sensor (10-14EV
        in most cases). For better control of the filmic S curve, the black exposure should be
        kept close to the white exposure in absolute value (and ideally greater, in absolute
        value), so the dynamic range is almost centered in 0EV. Another guide to validate the
        black exposure value is the S curve should always go through the center of the graph
        display (it will not when challenging parameter are set). Notice that the dynamic range
        of the scene car be lower than the camera's one, especially indoors.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>Safety factor and auto-tune</title>
      <para>
        The auto-tune color picker combines all three color pickers above, and will allow to set
        the grey, white and black exposures all at once, using the average of the drawn region
        as the grey estimation, the maximum as the white, and the minimum as the black. This
        gives good results in landscape photography but usually fails for portraits and indoor
        scenes.
      </para>
      <para>
        When no true white and no true black are available on the scene, the maximum and minimum
        XYZ values read on the image are not valid assumptions anymore, so the safety factor
        will allow you to shrink or enlarge symmetrically the detected dynamic range and the
        current parameters. This works with all color pickers.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>Contrast</title>
      <para>
        The filmic S curve is created from the user parameters, by computing the position of
        virtual nodes and interpolating them, similarly to the tone curve module (but here, the
        nodes cannot be moved manually). While this allow a quicker curve parametrization, not
        all the combinations of paramater deliver good curves, and the graph display will give a
        diagnostic interface. Good curves are either graceful S with a linear central portion
        and curved extremities, or lines following the diagonal of the graph.
      </para>
      <para>
        The contrast parameter drives the slope of the central part of the curve. The larger the
        dynamic range is, the greater the contrast should be set, to avoid reversed branches
        that would invert the image contrast. Proper values of contrast lie between 1.4 (at 8EV
        dynamic range) and 1.7 (at 14EV dynamic range). This parameter will mostly affect
        mid-tones.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>Latitude</title>
      <para>
        The latitude is the range between the 2 nodes enclosing the central linear portion of
        the curve. The bigger the latitude is, the more linearly the luminance is affected,
        which is desirable to preserve the chrominance. The latitude defines the range of
        luminances that is not desaturated in the third step of filmic processing. This
        parameter will mostly affect extreme luminances. It is usually better to keep it as
        large as possible, and adjust the contrast to avoid clipping. Proper values lie between
        25% and 50% of the dynamic range, and should be increased by 1EV each time the grey
        value is divided by 2.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>Balance hightlights/shadows</title>
      <para>
        By default, the latitude is distributed toward middle-grey accordingly to the dynamic
        range: when the dynamic range in centered in 0, it means the latitude is centered in
        50%. In real life situations, the dynamic range is often decentered, with a bigger part
        allowed to shadows, and so will be the latitude. However, this can produce clipping in
        blacks. The balance parameter allows to slide the latitude along the slope, toward the
        shadows or toward the highlights. This way, the contrast will be preserved in mid-tones,
        but more room will be allowed to one extremity of the dynamic range so clipping will be
        avoided. This should usually be used to center the latitude at 50%, on the graph
        display.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>Saturation</title>
      <para>
        The saturation parameter is a finetuning control that applies on top of the latitude
        parameter. By default, the picture is desaturated selectively in extreme luminances
        (near white and near black), and untouched in mid-tones. This is how film behaves and is
        also useful to avoid gamut clipping, because very bright and very saturated colours are
        usually out of the sRGB gamut.
      </para>
      <para>
        The desaturation mask is a gaussian window which standard deviation is latitude ×
        saturation, and which is centered on the latitude. As the latitude affects the luminance
        and the saturation, you should set it first, leaving the saturation at 100%. Once you
        are happy with the luminance mapping, you can then finetune the saturation parameter to
        adjust the desaturation.
      </para>
      <para>
        The saturation parameter sets at 100% means the desaturation window standard deviation
        is 100% of the latitude width. To desaturate more aggressively at extreme luminances,
        the saturation should be set lower than 100%. To almost disable the desaturation,
        saturation values can be set as high as 1000%, using right-click and inputting the
        values on the keyboard.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>Intent</title>
      <para>
        The intent parameter controls the interpolation algorithm used to derive the curve from
        the position of the nodes. It is similar to the tone curve module, but the options are
        translated into common language. <emphasis>Contrasted</emphasis> uses a cubic spline
        interpolation that produce a smooth round curve and pleasing contrast, however it can be
        sensible to nodes in close proximity and produce cusps and oscillations in this setup.
        <emphasis>Linear</emphasis> uses a monotonic Hermite interpolation that ensures the
        monotonicity of the curve, but produces a flatter contrast at the extremities.
        <emphasis>Faded</emphasis> uses a Catmul-Rom centripetal interpolation, designed to
        avoid cusps at all cost, but produces even flatter contrast at the extremities, which
        can be used creatively to emulate old faded photographs. <emphasis>Optimized</emphasis>
        is an average between the <emphasis>contrasted</emphasis> and
        <emphasis>linear</emphasis> modes, providing a fair trade-off at the expense of being
        heavier on the CPU.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>Preserve the chrominance</title>
      <para>
        The chrominance preservation mode is an advanced mode that cannot be used <quote>as
        is</quote> and needs extra-corrections. In regular mode, filmic applies its correction
        in ProPhotoRGB space, using the three RGB channels separately. This looks good most of
        the time, but can result in color hue shifts because no consistency between channels in
        ensured.
      </para>
      <para>
        When using the chrominance preservation mode, the RGB ratios are saved before any
        correction in filmic. Only the maximum of the thre RGB channels is used in the
        tone-mapping, as an estimation of the luminance. At the end of the process, the RGB
        ratios are restored as before. This leads to marginally faster runtimes, and links the
        thre RGB channels all along the process, to ensure the hue and the saturation are kept
        untouched, which is desirable when you performed precise color adjustments. However,
        this does not follow the eye response to luminance, so, keeping the saturation as is
        when pushing up the luminance will always look oversaturated. This is why, when using
        this mode, an extra desaturation should be performed, for example, using the output
        saturation in color balance module at 65 to 85%. In that case, color balance should be
        used to adjust the main saturation of the mid-tones, then an additional pass would fix
        the saturation of extreme luminances with the saturation parameter of filmic, set
        between 12 to 33%.
      </para>
      <para>
        It is advised to perform all filmic settings in the regular RGB mode (unlinked
        channels), then enable the chrominance preservation last, and then adjust the
        saturation.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>Black luminance</title>
      <para>
        The destination parameters set the target luminance values used to remap the tones
        through filmic. The default parameters will work 99% of the times, the remaining 1%
        being when you output in linear RGB space (REC709, REC2020) for media handling
        log-encoded data. These settings are then to be used with caution because darktable does
        not allow separate pipelines for diplay preview and for file output.
      </para>
      <para>
        The black luminance parameter allows to set the ground-level black of the target medium.
        Set it greater than 0% if you want raised, faded blacks to achieve a retro look.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>Middle-grey destination</title>
      <para>
        This is the middle-grey of the output medium, that is used as a target for the filmic S
        curve central node. On gamma corrected media, the actual grey is computed with the gamma
        correction (middle-grey^(1/gamma)), so a middle-grey parameter of 18% with a gamma of
        2.2 gives an actual middle-grey target of 45.87%.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>White luminance</title>
      <para>
        The white luminance parameter allows to set the ceiling level white of the target
        medium. Set it lower than 100% if you want dampened, muted whites to achieve a retro
        look.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>Destination power factor</title>
      <para>
        The power of the output transfer function, often improperly called the gamma (only
        screen have a gamma), is the parameter used to raise or compress the mid-tones to
        account for the display non-linearities or to avoid quantization artifacts when encoding
        in 8 bits file formats. This is a common operation when applying ICC color profiles
        (except for linear RGB spaces, like REC 709 or REC 2020, which have a linear
        <quote>gamma</quote> of 1.0). However, at the output of filmic, the signal is
        logarithmically encoded, which is not something ICC color profiles know to handle. As a
        consequence, if we let them apply a gamma 1/2.2 on top, it will result in a double up,
        and the middle-grey will be remapped to 76% instead of 45% as it should.
      </para>
      <para>
        To avoid double ups and washed pictures, filmic applies a <quote>gamma</quote>
        compression reverting the output ICC gamma correction, so the middle-grey is correctely
        remapped at the end. To remove this compression, set the destination power factor to 1.0
        and the middle-grey destination to 45%.
      </para>
    </sect5>

  </sect4>

</sect3>
