<!DOCTYPE sect3 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
    <!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
    %darktable_dtd;
    ]>
<sect3 status="draft" id="filmic">

  <title>Filmic rgb</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>modules</primary>
    <secondary>filmic rgb</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>filmic rgb</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect4>

    <title>Overview</title>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>
                This module compresses the tonal range of an image by reproducing the tone and
                color response of classic film. Doing so, it protects the colors and the
                contrast in mid-tones, recovers the shadows, and compresses bright highlights.
                It is very suitable in portrait photography, especially in back-lighting
                situations, but needs extra care when details need to be preserved in highlights
                (e.g. clouds).
              </para>

              <para>
                The module is derived from the same named module in Blender 3D modeller by T. J.
                Sobotka. While it is primarily intended to recover high-dynamic range from raw
                sensor data, it can be used with any image in replacement of the base curve
                module. The developer provided a detailed explanation of the module in a video
                called
                <ulink
                  url="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zbPj_TqTF88">Filmic
                RGB: remap any dynamic range in darktable 3.0</ulink>.
              </para>

              <para>
                Filmic rgb is the successor of the filmic module provided in darktable 2.6.x.
                While the underlying principles did not change much, users of the previous
                version should not expect a 1:1 translation of their workflow, and may find
                <xref
                  linkend="filmic-rgb-for-26-users"/> useful.
              </para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/filmic.png" scalefit="1" width="80%"
                align="center"/>
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

  </sect4>

  <sect4>

    <title>Prerequisites</title>

    <para>
      In order to get the best out of filmic rgb, images need some preparation:
      <itemizedlist>

        <listitem><para>
          In-camera, expose the shot <quote>to the right</quote>. This implies under exposing
          the shot so that the highlights are at the right of the histogram, just on the verge
          of clipping, but not clipped. It does not matter if the picture preview is very dark
          on your camera screen: as long as highlights are unclipped, filmic rgb should be able
          to recover details from the raw data. Beware that clipped data are not recoverable.
          Some cameras have a clipping alert preview to help you diagnose this, and some even
          have an highlight-priority exposure mode.
        </para></listitem>

        <listitem><para>
          In the <link linkend="exposure"><emphasis>exposure</emphasis></link> module, push the
          exposure until the midtones are clear enough. Do not worry about losing the
          highlights: they will be recovered as part of the filmic rgb processing. However, it
          is important to avoid negative pixels in black areas: the computations done by filmic
          rgb will result in unpredictable results in this case. For some cameras models (Canon,
          mainly), rawspeed (the raw decoding library of darktable), may set an exaggerated
          black level, resulting in crushed blacks and negative values. If so, brighten the
          blacks by setting a negative black level value in the
          <link linkend="exposure"><emphasis>exposure </emphasis></link> module.
        </para></listitem>

        <listitem><para>
          If you plan on using filmic rgb's auto-tuners, use the
          <link linkend="whitebalance"
                ><emphasis>white
          balance</emphasis></link> module first to correct any color casts and get neutral
          colors. In RGB color spaces, luminance and chrominance are linked, and filmic rgb's
          luminance detection relies on accurate measures of both. If your picture is very
          noisy, add an initial step of denoising to help the black exposure readings, and use a
          high quality demosaicing.
        </para></listitem>

        <listitem><para>
          If you plan on using filmic rgb's chrominance preservation mode, avoid using any tone
          mapping module as well as the base curve module. These may produce unpredictable color
          shifts that would make the chrominance preservation useless. Neither of these modules
          is usually needed if you use filmic rgb.
        </para></listitem>

      </itemizedlist>
    </para>

  </sect4>

  <sect4>

    <title>Usage</title>

    <para>
      The filmic rgb module aims at mapping the photographed scene (RAW image) dynamic range to
      the (smaller) display dynamic range. This mapping is defined in three steps, each handled
      in a separate tab in the interface:
      <itemizedlist>

        <listitem><para>
          The
          <guilabel>scene</guilabel>
          tab contains the <quote>input</quote> settings of the scene: what constitutes middle
          grey, white and black in the photographed scene.
        </para></listitem>

        <listitem><para>
          The
          <guilabel>look</guilabel>
          tab contains the parameters of the mapping applied to the input parameters defined in
          the
          <guilabel>scene</guilabel>
          tab. Notably, this part of the module applies an S-shaped parametric curve to enhance
          the contrast and remap the grey value to the middle grey of the display. This is
          similar to what the base curve or tone curve modules do.
        </para></listitem>

        <listitem><para>
          The
          <guilabel>display</guilabel>
          tab defined the output settings to map the transformed image to the display. In
          typical use cases, this tab should only be used very rarely.
        </para></listitem>

      </itemizedlist>
    </para>

    <para>
      The sliders' ranges of filmic rgb are limited to usual and safe values, but values are
      allowed out of these ranges by clicking on the sliders with the right button and inputting
      values on the keyboard. Filmic rgb has no neutral parameters resulting in a no-operation:
      as soon as the module is enabled, the image is always at least slightly affected.
    </para>

    <para>
      The curves at the top of the module are read-only and serve as a guide for the operations
      performed on the sliders. The bright curve is the tone mapping curve, where the abscissa
      represents the scene exposure, and the ordinate represents the display exposure. The dark
      curve is the desaturation curve, representing the percentage of saturation as function of
      the scene exposure.
    </para>

    <sect5>
      <title>Middle-grey luminance (<guilabel>Scene</guilabel> tab)</title>
      <para>
        The middle-grey luminance is the luminance in RGB space of the scene referred 18% grey.
        Its color picker tool reads the average luminance over the drawn area. If you happen to
        have a grey card or a color chart (IT8 chart or colorchecker) shot in the scene lighting
        conditions, then the grey color picker tool can be used to quickly sample the luminance
        of the grey patch on the picture. In other situations, the color picker can be used to
        sample the average luminance of the subject.
      </para>
      <para>
        This setting has an effect on the picture that is analogous to a lightness correction.
        Values close to 100% do not compress the highlights but fail to recover shadows. Values
        close to 0% recover greatly the shadows but compress the highlights more harshly and
        result in local-contrast losses. The standard middle-grey value for linearly encoded
        camera RGB is 18%. Good values of grey are usually the average luminance of the whole
        picture or of the subject. In studio and indoors (low dynamic range scenes), proper grey
        values are found between 15-18%. In high dynamic range scenes (landscapes, back-lit
        portraits), proper grey values lie between 1.25 and 9%.
      </para>
      <para>
        When modifying the middle-grey luminance, the white and black exposures are
        automatically slid accordingly, to preserve the dynamic range from clipping and to help
        you set the right parameter faster. If you are not happy with the auto adjustment
        performed by the grey slider, you can correct again the white and black exposure
        parameters afterwards.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>White relative exposure (<guilabel>Scene</guilabel> tab)</title>
      <para>
        The white relative exposure is the number of stops (EV) between pure white and the
        middle grey. It is the right bound of the dynamic range. It should be adjusted to avoid
        highlight clipping. The white exposure color picker tool reads the maximum luminance in
        RGB space over the drawn area, assumes it is pure white, and sets the white exposure
        parameter to remap the reading to 100% luminance.
      </para>
      <para>
        When the grey is set at 18%, the white exposure will always be around 2.45EV. When the
        grey is set at 100%, the white exposure should be set at 0EV.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>Black relative exposure (<guilabel>Scene</guilabel> tab)</title>
      <para>
        The black relative exposure is the number of stops (EV) between pure black and the
        middle grey. It is the left bound of the dynamic range. The black exposure color-picker
        tool reads the minimum luminance in RGB space over the drawn area, assumes it is pure
        black, and sets the black exposure parameter to remap the minimum reading to 0%
        luminance. The black color picker measurement is very sensitive to noise, and cannot
        identify if the minimum luminance is pure black (actual data) or just noise. It works
        better on low ISO pictures and with high quality demosaicing. When the color picker puts
        the black exposure at -16EV, it is a sign that the measure failed and you need to adjust
        it manually.
<!-- IHU is that still a thing? -->
      </para>
      <para>
        The black relative exposure allows you to choose how far you want to recover lowlights.
        Contrarily to the white exposure, it is not always possible to completely avoid clipping
        blacks. Every camera sensor has a maximum physical dynamic range for each ISO value (you
        can find them measured on
        <ulink url="https://www.dxomark.com/"
          ><emphasis>DXOmark</emphasis></ulink> or
        <ulink url="https://www.dpreview.com/"
            ><emphasis>DPreview</emphasis></ulink>),
        the software dynamic range in filmic rgb (dynamic range = white exposure - black
        exposure) should generally not be greater than the physical dynamic range of the sensor
        (10-14EV in most cases). Note that the dynamic range of the scene can be lower than the
        camera's one, especially indoors.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>Dynamic range scaling and auto-tune (<guilabel>Scene</guilabel> tab)</title>
      <para>
        The auto-tune color picker combines all three color pickers above, and allows to set the
        grey, white and black exposures all at once, using the average of the drawn region as
        the grey estimation, the maximum as the white, and the minimum as the black. This gives
        good results in landscape photography but usually fails for portraits and indoor scenes.
      </para>
      <para>
        When no true white and no true black are available on the scene, the maximum and minimum
        RGB values read on the image are not valid assumptions anymore, so the dynamic range
        scaling symmetrically shrinks or enlarges the detected dynamic range and the current
        parameters. This works with all color pickers, and adjusts the current values of white
        and black relative exposures.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5 id="filmicrgb-contrast">
      <title>Contrast (<guilabel>Look</guilabel> tab)</title>
      <para>
        The filmic rgb S-curve is created from the user parameters, by computing the position of
        virtual nodes and interpolating them, similarly to the tone curve module (but here, the
        nodes cannot be moved manually). The filmic rgb S-curve is split into three parts: a
        middle linear part, and two extremities that transition smoothly from the slope of the
        middle part to the ends of the exposure range.
      </para>
      <para>
        The
        <guilabel>contrast</guilabel>
        slider controls the slope of the middle part of the curve, as illustrated in the graph
        display.
      </para>
      <para>
        The contrast parameter drives the slope of the central part of the curve. The larger the
        dynamic range is, the greater the contrast should be set. This parameter mostly affects
        mid-tones.
      </para>
      <para>
        When the contrast is set to 1, this disables the S-curve.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>Latitude (<guilabel>Look</guilabel> tab)</title>
      <para>
        The latitude is the range between the 2 nodes enclosing the central linear portion of
        the curve, expressed as a percentage of the dynamic range defined in the
        <guilabel>scene</guilabel>
        tab (white-relative exposure minus black-relative-exposure). It is the luminance range
        that is remapped in priority, and it is remapped to the luminance interval defined by
        the <link linkend="filmicrgb-contrast">Contrast</link> parameter. It is usually advised
        to keep the latitude as large as possible, while avoiding clipping. If clipping is
        observed, you can compensate the effects by either decreasing the latitude, shifting the
        latitude interval with the
        <guilabel>shadow/highlights balance</guilabel>
        parameter, or by decreasing the contrast.
      </para>
      <para>
        The latitude also defines the range of luminances that is not desaturated at the
        extremities of the luminance range (see <xref linkend="filmicrgb-saturation"/>).
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>Shadows/highlight balance (<guilabel>Look</guilabel> tab)</title>
      <para>
        By default, the latitude is centered in the middle of the dynamic range. If this
        produces clipping in one part of the other of the curve, the balance parameter allows to
        slide the latitude along the slopes, towards the shadows or towards the highlights. This
        allows more room to be given to one extremity of the dynamic range than to the other, if
        the image properties demand it.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5 id="filmicrgb-saturation">
      <title>Extreme luminance saturation (<guilabel>Look</guilabel> tab)</title>
      <para>
        The darker curve in the graph of the module shows the desaturation of the extremities of
        the luminance range (black and white): since black and white do not have a color, they
        should normally be associated to 0% saturation. The default saturation is set to 100% in
        the range defined by the latitude, and decreases down to 0% outside of that range. One
        of the advantages of this operations is that, since color components do not clip at the
        same rate in the image, desaturating them avoids fringes around the high exposures.
      </para>
      <para>
        If the bright colors feel too desaturated, you should check that the white-relative
        exposure setting does not clip the high luminance spots, and if not, increase the
        extreme luminance saturation parameter.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>Preserve chrominance (<guilabel>Look</guilabel> tab)</title>
      <para>
        The
        <guilabel>preserve chrominance</guilabel>
        setting indicates how the chrominance should be handled by filmic rgb: either not at
        all, or using one of the provided three norms.
      </para>
      <para>
        When applying the S-curve transformation independently on each color, the proportions of
        the colors get modified, which modifies the properties of the underlying spectrum, and
        ultimately the chrominance of the image. This is what happens if you choose
        <emphasis>no</emphasis> in the
        <guilabel>preserve chrominance</guilabel>
        parameter. This value may yield seemingly <quote>better</quote> results than the other
        values, but it may negatively impact later parts of the pipeline, when it comes to
        global saturation for example.
      </para>
      <para>
        The other values of this parameter all work in a similar way. Instead of applying the
        S-curve to the channels R, G and B independently, filmic rgb uses a norm N, divides all
        the three components by that norm, and applies the S-curve to N. This way, the
        relationship between the channels is preserved.
      </para>
      <para>
        The different values of the
        <guilabel>preserve chrominance</guilabel>
        parameter indicate which norm is used (the value used for N):
        <itemizedlist>

          <listitem><para>
            <emphasis>max RGB</emphasis> is the maximum value of the three channels R, G and B.
            It is the behaviour of the previous version of the filmic module. It tends to darken
            the blue, especially skies, and to yield halos/fringes, especially if some channels
            are clipped.
          </para></listitem>

          <listitem><para>
            <emphasis>luminance Y</emphasis> is a linear combination of the three channels R, G
            and B. It tends to darkens the reds, and to increase the local contrast in reds.
          </para></listitem>

          <listitem><para>
            <emphasis>RGB power norm</emphasis> is the sum of the cubes of the three channels R,
            G, and B, divided by the sum of their squares - that is to say, (R³ + G³ +
            B³)/(R² + G² + B²). It is usally a good compromise between the max RGB and the
            luminance Y values.
          </para></listitem>

        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
      <para>
        There is no "right" choice for the norm, depending on the picture to which it applies -
        you should experiment and decide for yourself on case by case basis.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>Target black luminance (<guilabel>Display</guilabel> tab)</title>
      <para>
        The destination parameters set the target luminance values used to remap the tones
        through filmic rgb. The default parameters will work 99% of the times, the remaining 1%
        being when you output in linear RGB space (REC709, REC2020) for media handling
        log-encoded data. These settings are then to be used with caution because darktable does
        not allow separate pipelines for display preview and for file output.
      </para>
      <para>
        The target black luminance parameter allows to set the ground-level black of the target
        medium. Set it greater than 0% if you want raised, faded blacks to achieve a retro look.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>Target middle-grey (<guilabel>Display</guilabel> tab)</title>
      <para>
        This is the middle-grey of the output medium, that is used as a target for the filmic
        rgb S curve central node. On gamma corrected media, the actual grey is computed with the
        gamma correction (middle-grey^(1/gamma)), so a middle-grey parameter of 18% with a gamma
        of 2.2 gives an actual middle-grey target of 45.87%.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>Target white luminance (<guilabel>Display</guilabel> tab)</title>
      <para>
        The target white luminance parameter allows to set the ceiling level white of the target
        medium. Set it lower than 100% if you want dampened, muted whites to achieve a retro
        look.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>Target power factor function</title>
      <para>
        The power of the output transfer function, often improperly called the gamma (only
        screen have a gamma), is the parameter used to raise or compress the mid-tones to
        account for the display non-linearities or to avoid quantization artifacts when encoding
        in 8 bits file formats. This is a common operation when applying ICC color profiles
        (except for linear RGB spaces, like REC 709 or REC 2020, which have a linear
        <quote>gamma</quote> of 1.0). However, at the output of filmic rgb, the signal is
        logarithmically encoded, which is not something ICC color profiles know to handle. As a
        consequence, if we let them apply a gamma 1/2.2 on top, it will result in a double up,
        and the middle-grey will be remapped to 76% instead of 45% as it should.
      </para>
      <para>
        To avoid double ups and washed pictures, filmic rgb applies a <quote>gamma</quote>
        compression reverting the output ICC gamma correction, so the middle-grey is correctly
        remapped at the end. To remove this compression, set the destination power factor to 1.0
        and the middle-grey destination to 45%.
      </para>
    </sect5>

  </sect4>

  <sect4>

    <title>Workflow</title>

    <para>
      The filmic rgb module can seem pretty complex; here is a proposed workflow for processing
      an image with filmic rgb to obtain a well-exposed picture from a RAW file.
    </para>

    <orderedlist>

      <listitem><para>
        Modify the exposure in the
        <link linkend="exposure"
            ><emphasis>exposure</emphasis></link> module so
        that the midtones are clear enough. Do not worry about losing details in the highlights:
        they will be recovered by the next steps of the processing.
      </para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>
        In filmic rgb, start with <quote>neutral</quote> parameters: set the the middle grey
        luminance to 18.45% in the
        <guilabel>scene</guilabel>
        tab, and set the contrast to 1 in the
        <guilabel>look</guilabel>
        tab.
      </para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>
        Adjust the white-relative and black-relative exposures in the
        <guilabel>scene</guilabel>
        tab; set the middle grey luminance as well.
      </para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>
        In the
        <guilabel>look</guilabel>
        tab, experiment with the
        <guilabel>contrast</guilabel>
        parameter. Increase the latitude as much as you can without clipping the curve, slide it
        with the
        <guilabel>shadows/highlights
            balance</guilabel>
        parameter.
      </para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>
        filmic rgb tends to compress the local contrast - you can compensate for that using the
        <link linkend="local_contrast"><emphasis>local contrast</emphasis></link> module.
      </para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>
        You may also want to increase the saturation in the
        <link linkend="color_balance"
              ><emphasis>color balance</emphasis></link>
        module, and adjust settings in the <emphasis>tone equalizer</emphasis> module.
      </para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>
        Do the last adjustments in filmic rgb, and your picture is now ready for creative
        processing.
      </para></listitem>

    </orderedlist>

  </sect4>

  <sect4 id="filmic-rgb-for-26-users">

    <title>Filmic rgb for darktable 2.6 filmic users</title>

    <para>
      Filmic rgb is a reimplementation of the filmic module, and some adjustments are necessary
      to switch from one version to the other. This last section underlines the most important
      differences; a more comprehensive overview is available as a video called
      <ulink
        url="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9awBFYcPgGU">darktable 3.0 filmic
      explained to users of darktable 2.6</ulink>. The major differences points when it comes to
      usage are the following:
      <itemizedlist>

        <listitem><para>
          The default parameters of both modules are not comparable: activating the filmic rgb
          module with default parameters does not yield the same results as the previous filmic
          module with default parameters.
        </para></listitem>

        <listitem><para>
          The latitude is now expressed in percentage of the dynamic range instead of absolute
          EV values.
        </para></listitem>

        <listitem><para>
          The saturation slider that was present in the previous version of filmic to avoid
          oversaturation is not necessary anymore since filmic rgb does a much better job at
          preserving colors.
        </para></listitem>

        <listitem><para>
          The previous version of filmic was always using the prophoto RGB profile; filmic rgb
          respects the working color profile defined in the
          <link
              linkend="input_color_profile"><emphasis>input color
          profile</emphasis></link> module. To keep the same behaviour, you can set the working
          profile to <emphasis>linear prophoto RGB</emphasis>.
        </para></listitem>

      </itemizedlist>
    </para>

    <para>
      To achieve similar results between the previous version of filmic and filmic rgb, the
      following steps are suggested:
      <orderedlist>

        <listitem><para>
          Transfer the parameters from filmic to filmic rgb. The latitude parameter is now given
          in percentage of the input dynamic range: compute that percentage from your filmic
          input values.
        </para></listitem>

        <listitem><para>
          Lower the contrast.
        </para></listitem>

        <listitem><para>
          Set the extreme luminance saturation to 50%, unless you are using the chrominance
          preservation.
        </para></listitem>

        <listitem><para>
          Adjust the shadows/highlights balance to avoid clipping of the curve
        </para></listitem>

        <listitem><para>
          Rais the middle grey luminance a bit, set the dynamic range scaling to approximately
          6%.
        </para></listitem>

        <listitem><para>
          The old <emphasis>preserve chrominance</emphasis> setting corresponds to the
          <emphasis>max RGB</emphasis> mode; in that case, do not modify the extreme luminance
          saturation.
        </para></listitem>

        <listitem><para>
          If you experience weird color shifts, change the working color space to prophoto RGB
          in the <link linkend="input_color_profile"><emphasis>input color
          profile</emphasis></link> module.
        </para></listitem>

      </orderedlist>
    </para>

  </sect4>

</sect3>
