<!DOCTYPE sect3 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect3 status="final" id="global_tonemap">

  <title>Global tonemap</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>modules</primary>
    <secondary>global tonemap</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>global tonemap</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect4>

    <title>Overview</title>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              This module implements another approach to compressing the tonal range of an HDR
              image into the limited tonal range of a typical LDR output file. It offers several
              implementations of global tonemap operators.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/global_tonemap.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

  </sect4>

  <sect4>

    <title>Usage</title>

    <para>
      Global tonemapping processes each pixel of an HDR image, without taking the local
      surrounding into account. This is generally faster than local tonemapping, as implemented
      in the <link linkend="tonemapping"><emphasis>tonemapping</emphasis></link> module but
      might lead to less convincing results with very high dynamic scenes. As an enhancement to
      the original operators, darktable can preserve detail of the input image, and transfer it
      back to the output image.
    </para>

    <sect5>
      <title>operator</title>
      <para>
        Reinhard, Filmic and Drago global tonemap operators are available for use. Depending on
        the selected operator, different parameters can be adjusted. Some operators are fully
        self-adjusting, and do not require specific controls.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>bias</title>
      <para>
        Only offered for the <emphasis>Drago</emphasis> operator. This parameter influences the
        contrast of the output image. It is an essential parameter for adjusting the compression
        of high values and the visibility of details in dark areas. According to the original
        paper, a value of 0.85 is recommended as a starting point.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>target</title>
      <para>
        Only offered for the <emphasis>Drago</emphasis> operator. This is a scale factor to
        adjust the global image brightness to the brightness of the intended display. It is
        measured in cd/m
        <superscript>2</superscript>
        , and should match the according value of your output device. Higher values lead to a
        brighter image, while lower values lead to a darker image.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>detail</title>
      <para>
        Offered as an addition to all operators. This parameter controls how much detail is
        preserved and transferred back into the output image after tonemapping.
      </para>
    </sect5>

  </sect4>

</sect3>
