<!DOCTYPE sect3 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect3 status="final" id="levels">

  <title>Levels</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>modules</primary>
    <secondary>levels</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>levels</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>artifact mitigation</primary>
    <secondary>black pixels</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>artifact mitigation</primary>
    <secondary>blue light sources</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect4>

    <title>Overview</title>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              A tool for adjusting black, white, and mid-gray points. This module is especially
              useful if the histogram of an image does not span the whole horizontal range, from
              pure black to pure white.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/levels.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

  </sect4>

  <sect4>

    <title>Usage</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>color picker</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>
      The levels tool offers two modes of operation: <quote>manual</quote> and
      <quote>automatic</quote>.
    </para>

    <para>
      In <quote>manual</quote> mode the levels tool shows a histogram of the image, and displays
      three bars with handles. Dragging the handles modifies the tones in the image. Those bars
      control the black, middle gray and white points in absolute values of image lightness (the
      L value from Lab).
    </para>

    <para>
      You can move the black and white bars to match the left and right borders of the
      histogram, which will make the output image span the full available tonal range. A
      previously flat looking image will get more contrast and pop.
    </para>

    <para>
      Moving the middle bar will modify the middle gray tones. Shifting it left will make the
      image look brighter, shifting it right will make it darker. This is often referred to as a
      change of image gamma.
    </para>

    <para>
      There are three color pickers in black, gray, and white, available by pressing the
      respectively colored
      <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_module_picker;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center" />
      icon. You can use them to sample the corresponding level directly from the image. You can
      switch between point and area sampling mode from within the global color picker panel (see
      <xref linkend="global_color_picker"/>).
    </para>

    <para>
      The <quote>auto</quote> button autoadjusts the black and white point and puts the gray
      point exactly in the mean between them.
    </para>

    <para>
      In <quote>automatic</quote> mode the module automatically analyses the histogram of the
      image, detects the left and right histogram borders, and lets you define the black point,
      the gray point and the white point in terms of
      <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Percentile">
      <emphasis>percentiles</emphasis></ulink> relative to these borders.
    </para>

    <para>
      Tip: Under certain conditions, especially highly saturated blue light sources in the
      frame, the levels module may produce black pixel artifacts. See the <emphasis>gamut
      clipping</emphasis> option (<xref linkend="input_color_profile"/>) on how to mitigate this
      issue.
    </para>

    <sect5>
      <title>mode</title>
      <para>
        Set the mode of operation of this module. Defaults to <quote>manual</quote>.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>black</title>
      <para>
        Sets the black point in percentiles relative to the left border of the histogram (only
        <quote>automatic</quote> mode).
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>gray</title>
      <para>
        Sets the gray point in percentiles relative to the left and right borders of the
        histogram <emphasis>after</emphasis> having applied the black point and white point
        corrections (only <quote>automatic</quote> mode).
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>white</title>
      <para>
        Sets the white point in percentiles relative to the right border of the histogram (only
        <quote>automatic</quote> mode).
      </para>
    </sect5>

  </sect4>

</sect3>
