<!DOCTYPE sect3 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect3 status="draft" id="levels"><title>Levels</title>
	<sect4><title>Overview</title>
		<informaltable frame="none"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
				<colspec colwidth="6*"/>
				<colspec colwidth="4*"/>
				<tbody>
					<row>						
						<entry>A level tool that most of you will recognize how to use from other imaging softwares.
						</entry>
						<entry>
							<graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/levels.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
						</entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</informaltable>
	</sect4>

	<sect4><title>Usage</title>
		<para>The levels tool shows the histogram of the image and displays three bars with handles for you to drag and correct
		the tone in the image. Those bars represent black, middle gray and white. The button <quote>auto</quote> will autoadjust the black-
		and whitepoint and put the greypoint exactly in the mean between them. There are three color pickers in black, grey, and white,
		available by pressing the respectively colored <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_module_picker;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center" />.
		</para>
		<para>
		This module is especially useful if the histogram of your image does not span the whole horizontal range from pure black
		to pure white. You can either take a chance and press <quote>auto</quote> or define the black and white level yourself. That can be done
		by either using the colorpickers to pick out one of the three levels directly from the image, or by adjusting the left and right bar
		to match the left and right border of the histogram, which will make the output image span the full available tonal range. A previously
		flat looking image will get more contrast and pop.
		</para>
		<para>
		Shifting or picking the middle bar will modify the middle gray tones. Shifting it left will make the image look brighter, shifting
		it right will make it darker. This is often referred to as a change of image gamma.
		</para>
	</sect4>
<!--	
	<sect4><title>Examples</title>
		<para>
			<informaltable frame="none"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
					<colspec colwidth="4*"/>
					<colspec colwidth="6*"/>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/soften_ex1.png" scalefit="1" width="90%" align="center" />
							</entry>						
							<entry><para>This is the original image, use it as reference for the changes below...</para></entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/soften_ex2.png" scalefit="1" width="90%" align="center" />
							</entry>						
							<entry>
								<para>EXAMPLE 2 DESCRIPTION
								</para>
							</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</informaltable>
		</para>	
	</sect4>
-->	
</sect3>
