<!DOCTYPE sect3 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
    <!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
    %darktable_dtd;
    ]>
<sect3 status="final" id="tone_equalizer">

  <title>Tone equalizer</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>modules</primary>
    <secondary>tone equalizer</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>tone equalizer</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect4>

    <title>Overview</title>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              The Tone Equalizer module is designed to replace the
              Base Curve module, the Shadows/Highlights module, and
              the Zone System module.  It allows us to brighten or
              darken up to 9 different ranges of luminosity within our
              image.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic
                  fileref="darkroom/modules/images/toneequalizer_simple.png"
                  scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

  </sect4>

  <sect4>

    <title>Usage</title>

    <para>
      It is recommended that you look at all 3 tabs
      (<quote>Simple</quote>, <quote>Advanced</quote>,
      <quote>Masking</quote>) before attempting to use the Tone
      Equalizer module.
    </para>

    <para>
      The 9 sliders on the <quote>Simple</quote> tab (see screenshot
      above) correlate to the 9 control points
      which appear across the centre of the graph on the
      <quote>Advanced</quote> tab.
    </para>

    <para>
      <informaltable frame="none">
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
          <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
          <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                The histogram which appears on the
                <quote>Advanced</quote> tab does
                <emphasis>not</emphasis> represent your image. It
                represents the <emphasis>mask</emphasis> which the
                Tone Equalizer is creating for your image. This is an
                important distinction to understand.  The aim is to
                get that histogram extended as far as possible to the
                left and right sides of the graph.
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <graphic
                    fileref="darkroom/modules/images/toneequalizer_advanced.png"
                    scalefit="1" width="90%" align="center" />
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </para>

    <para>
      <informaltable frame="none">
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
          <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
          <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                To do that, we go to the <quote>Masking</quote> tab, and adjust the Mask
                Exposure Compensation and Mask Contrast Compensation sliders.
                Selecting each eye dropper will allow the Tone Equalizer module
                to select the most appropriate values for you. Having done that,
                check the histogram in the Advanced tab again. It should now be
                fairly evenly distributed across the graph.
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <graphic
                    fileref="darkroom/modules/images/toneequalizer_masking.png"
                    scalefit="1" width="90%" align="center" />
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </para>

    <para>
      Now, you can <emphasis>Click+drag</emphasis> the control points (on the
      <quote>Advanced</quote> tab) to increase or decrease any part of the tonal
      range of your image.  Adjust control points on the left side to
      brighten/darken shadow tones. Adjust control points on the right
      side to brighten/darken highlight tones.  Alternatively, you can
      use the Simple tab and control the adjustment through the use of
      your mouse wheel over the image.
    </para>

    <sect5>
      <title>the cursor</title>

      <para>
        <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/toneequalizer_cursor.png"
            scalefit="1" width="20%" />
      </para>

      <para>
        The cursor in the Tone Equalizer contains a lot of
        information.  You'll see some cross hairs, with what appears
        to be a single grey circle in the middle.  But it's not a
        single circle. It's 2 concentric circles.  The outer circle
        will <emphasis>always</emphasis> represent the tonal value
        under the mouse pointer, as it was before any adjustment was
        made. The inner circle will show the tonal value under the
        mouse pointer <emphasis>after</emphasis> any adjustment has
        been made.  So if the inner circle is brighter than the outer
        circle, it means a brightening adjustment has been made to
        that part of the tonal range of the image.  If the inner
        circle is darker than the outer circle, then that tonal range
        has been darkened.
      </para>

      <para>
        You will also notice that there is an arc which either climbs, or
        descends, from the left side cross hair. This is another way of
        showing you whether a positive or negative adjustment has been made
        for any given tonal range under the mouse at its current location.
      </para>

      <para>
        There is also a text box near the right side cross hair which also
        shows what adjustments have been made, but in numeric text form.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>display exposure mask</title>

      <para>
        At the bottom of the module, you'll see Display Exposure Mask
        and to the right of that, an icon <inlinegraphic
        fileref="&icon_module_mask;" scalefit="1" width="2%"
        align="center"/>. <emphasis>Click</emphasis> on this icon to
        see the mask which the Tone Equalizer has generated for your
        image.
      </para>

      <para>
        The idea behind this mask is to create smooth transitions
        between tonal ranges, so as to avoid creating halos. Yet, the
        mask is also able to create well defined edges for high
        contrast areas of the image.  Having this mask displayed will
        assist in understanding the follow parameters:
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>filter diffusion</title>

      <para>
        This defaults to a value of 1, meaning there is one instance
        of the mask generated.
      </para>

      <para>
        If you increase this to 2, a second mask is calculated using
        the first mask as an input. As a result, the new mask is more
        fuzzy than when there was only one instance of the mask.
        Progressively higher values will diffuse the mask even
        further.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>smoothing diameter</title>

      <para>
        With lower values, the transition between dark areas of the
        mask and lighter areas of the mask will be more pronounced. As
        this value is increased, those transitions become
        smoother/softer.  It should be noted that setting really large
        values may result in slower display times IF Denoise Profiled
        is also in use.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>edge refinement/feathering</title>

      <para>
        Higher values will force the mask to follow high contrast
        edges more closely.  Lower values will give smoother
        gradients, but may introduce some halos.
      </para>
    </sect5>

  </sect4>

</sect3>
