<!DOCTYPE sect3 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
    <!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
    %darktable_dtd;
    ]>
<sect3 status="final" id="tone_curve">

  <title>Tone curve</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>modules</primary>
    <secondary>tone curve</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>tone curve</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect4>

    <title>Overview</title>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              This module is a classic digital photography tool. darktable's tone curve
              can work in three different color spaces: RGB, XYZ or Lab.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/tonecurve.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

  </sect4>

  <sect4>

    <title>Usage</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>color picker</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>
      In its default state, curves will be straight lines, defined by few anchor nodes. You can
      move the nodes to modify the curve. You can generate new nodes by
      <emphasis>clicking</emphasis> on the curve. With <emphasis>ctrl-click</emphasis> you
      generate a new node at the x-location of the mouse pointer and the corresponding
      y-location of the current curve&nbsp;&ndash; this adds a node without risking to
      accidentally modify the curve. Up to 20 nodes per curve can be defined. To remove a node,
      move it out of the widget area.
    </para>

    <para>
      A color picker is activated by pressing
      <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_module_picker;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center" />
      and will show the picked values in the graph. You can switch between point and area
      sampling mode from within the global color picker panel (see
      <xref linkend="global_color_picker"/>). Numerical Lab values of input and output (see
      below) at the selected spot or area are shown on top left of the widget.
    </para>

    <sect5>
      <title>color spaces</title>
      <para>
        Depending on the desired intent, you can apply the tone curve in three different color spaces:
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem><para>Lab, linked channels,</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>Lab, separated channels,</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>XYZ, linked channels,</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>RGB, linked channels.</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>

      <para>
        Lab is a perceptual color space that is designed to approximate the way human beings
        perceive colors and lightness, and representing the color information independently
        of the the lightness information.
        In <quote>Lab, separated channels</quote>, you get a fullly independent control
        over the chrominance (a/b-channels) and the luminance (L-channel).
        In <quote>Lab, linked channels</quote>, only the luminance (L-channel) control is
        available. The color saturation correction will be automatically computed, for each pixel,
        from the contrast correction applied to the luminance channel.
        This works better in cases where a subtle contrast correction is applied,
        but gives increasingly inaccurate saturation correction as the contrast gets more
        dramatically enhanced.
      </para>

      <para>
        XYZ is a linear technical color space designed to link the physiologic light response
        of human eyes to RGB spaces. As Lab, it separates the lightness from the color
        information, but it does so in a way that does not account for the role of the brain
        correction in human perception.
        The <quote>XYZ, linked channels,</quote> mode offers an alternative for
        <quote>Lab, linked channels</quote>.
        It works by applying the L-channel curve to all three channels in the XYZ
        color space. Look at blend mode <quote>coloradjustment</quote> if you want to tune
        the strength of automatic chroma scaling (see <xref linkend="blending_operators"/>).
        This mode is known to produce a slight hue shift towards yellow.
      </para>

      <para>
        RGB spaces are linear color spaces designed to capture and display images in additive
        synthesis. They are related to capture and display media and do not isolate
        color and lightness information.
        The <quote>RGB, linked channels,</quote> works in ProPhoto RGB and applies the L-channel
        curve to all three channels in the RGB color space. Adding contrast in RGB space
        is known to desaturate highlights and boost saturation in lowlights, but this has proven to
        be the most reliable way to edit contrast, and is the standard way to do it in most
        software. This mode makes the tone curve module behave the same way as the
        basecurve (see <xref linkend="base_curve"/>), except the latter one works in camera RGB space.
      </para>

      <para>
        Notice that the interface is controlled in Lab in all cases. This means that the middle gray
        coordinate is always 50% in the graph, no matter what color space is used. The same applies to
        the inset histogram displayed in the background of the curve. The
        controls are converted to the relevant color space before the corrections are applied&nbsp;&ndash;
        in RGB and XYZ, the middle-gray is therefore remapped from 50% to 18%.
      </para>

    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>L-channel curve</title>
      <para>
        The tone curve in L-channel works on Lightness. For a better overview a lightness
        histogram is displayed in the diagram. When working in <quote>Lab, linked channels</quote>,
        <quote>RGB, linked channels</quote> or <quote>XYZ, linked channels</quote>, the L-channel
        curve is the only one available.
      </para>
      <para>
        The horizontal line represents the input image pixels' lightness. The vertical line
        represents the lightness of the output image pixels. A straight line does not change
        anything. A point above the default diagonal increases the lightness, whereas a point
        under decreases it. Shifting the center of the curve upwards will lighten the image,
        shifting it downwards will darken the image. An S-like curve will enhance the contrast
        of the image.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>a/b-channel curves</title>
      <para>
        The curves in the a and b channels work on color values and are available only in
        <quote>Lab, separated channels</quote> color space.
        The horizontal line represents the color channel value of the
        input image pixels. The vertical line represents the color channel value of the output
        image pixels. Positive a-values correspond to more magenta colors; negative a-values
        correspond to more greenish colors. Positive b-values correspond to more yellowish
        colors; negative b-values correspond to more blueish colors.
      </para>
      <para>
        A straight line does not change anything. Shifting the center of the curve will give the
        image a color tint: shifting a-channel upwards gives a magenta tint; shifting b-channel
        upwards gives a yellow tint; shifting a-channel downwards gives a green tint; shifting
        b-channel downwards gives a blue tint.
      </para>
      <para>
        Increasing/decreasing the steepness of the curves, without shifting its center, will
        increase/decrease the color saturation of the respective channel. With properly defined
        curves you can exert fine control on color saturation, depending on the input pixel's
        colors.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>interpolation method</title>
      <para>
        The interpolation is the process by which a continuous curve is derived from a few
        punctual nodes. As this process is never perfect, several methods are offered that
        can alleviate the potential issues you may encounter with some nodes setups.
      </para>
      <para>
        Arguably, the most visually pleasing method is the <quote>cubic spline</quote>. Since
        it gives smooth curves, the contrast in the image is better enhanced. However, this
        method is very sensitive to the nodes position, and can produce cusps and oscillations
        when the nodes are too close to each other, or when there are too many of them.
        This method works best when there are only 4 to 5 nodes, evenly spaced.
      </para>
      <para>
        The <quote>centripetal spline</quote> is a method designed specifically to avoid
        cusps and oscillations, but as a drawback it will follow the nodes more loosely.
        It is very robust, no matter the number of nodes and their spacing, but will produce
        a more faded and dull contrast.
      </para>
      <para>
        The <quote>monotonic spline</quote> is a method designed specifically to give a monotonic
        interpolation, meaning that there will be none of the oscillations the cubic spline may
        produce. This method is very suitable when you try to build an analytical function
        from a node interpolation (for example: exponential, logarithm, power, etc.). Such
        functions are provided as presets. It is a good trade-off between the two
        aforementioned methods.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>scale</title>
      <para>
        The scale allows you to distort the graph display so that certain graphical
        properties emerge to help you draw meaningful curves. Notice that the scaling
        option only affects the curve display, not the actual parameters.
      </para>
      <para>
        By default, the <quote>linear</quote> scale is used. This scale uses evenly spaced
        abscissa and ordinates axes.
      </para>
      <para>
        The <quote>log-log (x, y)</quote> scale will compress the high values and dilate
        the low values, on both the abcissa and the axis of ordinates, so that the nodes in lowlights
        get more space on the graph and can be controlled more clearly.
      </para>
      <para>
        The <quote>semi-log (x)</quote> is similar to the log-log scale, but the axis of ordinates
        is left linear and only the abcissa is logarithmically scaled. This is useful
        when you want to draw a purely exponential function: in semi-log (x) scale, exponential
        become identity lines.
      </para>
      <para>
        The <quote>semi-log (y)</quote> is similar to the log-log scale, but the abscissa
        axis is left linear and only the axis of ordinates is logarithmically scaled. This is useful
        when you want to draw a purely logarithmic function: in semi-log (y) scale, logarithms
        become identity lines.
      </para>
      <para>
        When using non-linear scales, a <quote>base of the logarithm</quote> slider appears
        that lets you control the amount of compression/dilatation operated by the logarithmic
        scales. If you draw purely exponential or logarithmic functions from identity lines,
        setting this values defines the base of such functions.
      </para>
    </sect5>

  </sect4>

  <sect4>

    <title>Examples</title>

    <para>
      <informaltable frame="none">
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
          <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
          <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/tonecurve_ex1.png" scalefit="1" width="90%" align="center" />
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Original image
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/tonecurve_ex2.png" scalefit="1" width="90%" align="center" />
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Tone curve settings. Please note how the center node of our b-curve was shifted
                down to negative values. This gives the image its blue tint.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/tonecurve_ex3.png" scalefit="1" width="90%" align="center" />
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Resulting image
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </para>

  </sect4>

</sect3>
