<!DOCTYPE sect3 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect3 status="final" id="zone_system">

  <title>Zone system</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>modules</primary>
    <secondary>zone system</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>zone system</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect4>

    <title>Overview</title>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              This module is another way to change the lightness of your image, based on Ansel
              Adams' system. It allows modification of a zone's lightness taking into account
              the effect on the adjacent zones. It divides the lightness range into a
              user-defined number of zones.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/zonesystem.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

  </sect4>

  <sect4>

    <title>Usage</title>

    <para>
      Following the concept of Ansel Adams the lightness (based on the L channel from Lab) is
      divided into a number of zones ranging from pure black to pure white. These zones are
      displayed in a zonebar. The number of zones can be changed by mouse-scrolling on that bar
      (defaults to 10 zones).
    </para>

    <para>
      The zonebar is split horizontally with the upper part showing the zones of the module's
      output and the lower part the according zones of the module's input. In its default state
      both parts are fully aligned. While the output zones are static you can left click and
      drag a control point in the input zones to modify the zonemapping. Shifting a control
      point proportionally expands the zones on one side and compresses the zones on the other
      side. Any already existing control point stays in place, effectively preventing changes to
      the zones beyond. Use right click to remove a control point.
    </para>

    <para>
      The preview shows the image broken down in zones. When hovering above a zone on the
      zonebar, that zone&nbsp;&ndash; either from input or output&nbsp;&ndash; is highlighted on
      the preview.
    </para>

  </sect4>

  <sect4>

    <title>Examples</title>

    <para>
      <informaltable frame="none">
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
          <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
          <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/zonesystem_ex1.png" scalefit="1" width="90%" align="center" />
              </entry>
              <entry>
                The original image.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/zonesystem_ex2.png" scalefit="1" width="90%" align="center" />
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Here, the darker and lighter zones were compressed to increase contrast, then
                the upper parts of darker zones were expanded to increase their visual impact.
                <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/zonesystem_ex2_settings.png" />
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </para>

  </sect4>

</sect3>
