<sect2 status="final" id="cyan_toned_images">

  <title>Cyan toned image</title>

  <sect3 status="final">

    <title>Overview</title>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              Cyan is a nice color touchup for black and white images, this example guides you
              through how to make this with darktable and how to control the tone. You can
              choose any tone of your like for this tutorial...
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="darkroom/examples/images/cyantone.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

  </sect3>

  <sect3 status="final">

    <title>Procedure</title>

    <para>
      This procedure uses monochrome, channel mixer and splittoning modules.
    </para>

    <orderedlist>

      <listitem><para>
        Image preparation
      </para>

      <para>
        Prepare the image for the cyan toned steps by adjusting the base settings such as
        exposure,black level, contrast etc. for a correctly looking image.
      </para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>
        Black and white
      </para>

      <para>
        Enable the <emphasis>monochrome</emphasis> module (<xref linkend="monochrome"/>) to make
        the image black and white.
      </para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>
        Add color tone
      </para>

      <para>
        This step selects the base tone of the image using <emphasis>channel mixer</emphasis>
        (<xref linkend="channel_mixer"/>), we are going for cyan tone but you can choose any
        tone that you like here.
      </para>

      <orderedlist>

        <listitem><para>
          Enable the channel mixer module
        </para></listitem>

        <listitem><para>
          Select the red channel destination and set the red color value to 0.7
        </para></listitem>

        <listitem><para>
          Select the green channel destination and set the green color value to 1.15
        </para></listitem>

        <listitem><para>
          Select the blue channel destination and set the blue color value to 1.15
        </para></listitem>

      </orderedlist>

      <para>
        As you notice we mix blue and green color to get a cyan tone, we substract 0.3 from the
        red channel and add them to blue and green.
      </para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>
        Splittoning
      </para>

      <para>
        The result of the previous step does also add a color cast on highlights that we
        actually want to have white for a prettier result. We also want to add some blue color
        cast to the shadows in order to emphasis them. Module <emphasis>splittoning</emphasis>
        (<xref linkend="splittoning"/>) can accomplish this.
      </para>

      <orderedlist>

        <listitem><para>
          Enable the splittoning module
        </para></listitem>

        <listitem><para>
          Select a blue/cyan tone for shadows and set saturation around 50%
        </para></listitem>

        <listitem><para>
          Set highlights saturation to zero, to remove saturation on highlights
        </para></listitem>

        <listitem><para>
          Set compression to zero
        </para></listitem>

        <listitem><para>
          Use the balance slider to tune the effect, our example uses a balance of 70/30
        </para></listitem>

      </orderedlist></listitem>

    </orderedlist>

  </sect3>

</sect2>
