<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect1 status="final" id="core_options">

  <title>Core options</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>preferences and settings</primary>
    <secondary>core options</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    These options control some of the internals of darktable.
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">memory in megabytes to use for thumbnail cache</bridgehead>

  <para>
    In order to speed-up display of film rolls, darktable stores thumbnails in a cache file on
    disk (primary cache) and loads it into memory at startup. This value controls the cache size
    in megabytes. It needs a restart if changed (default 256MB).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">enable disk backend for thumbnail cache</bridgehead>

  <para>
    If activated darktable stores all thumbnails on disk as a secondary cache, and thereby
    keeping thumbnails accessible in case they get dropped from the primary cache. This needs
    more disk space but speeds up lighttable view as it avoids reprocessing of thumbnails
    (default on).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">color manage cached thumbnails</bridgehead>

  <para>
    If activated darktable generates thumbnails in a general color space (AdobeRGB) in order to
    render them independently of the individual monitor. Conversion to the monitor color space
    is done at display time. If this option is not activated thumbnails are directly stored in
    the specific monitor color space valid at generation time and are subsequently displayed
    without further corrections (default on).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">number of background threads</bridgehead>

  <para>
    This controls how many parallel threads are used to create thumbnails during import. On
    32bit systems it is strongly recommended to set this to 1. Needs a restart if changed
    (default 2).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">host memory limit (in MB) for tiling</bridgehead>

  <para>
    In order to manage large images on systems with limited memory darktable does tile-wise
    processing. This variable controls the <emphasis>maximum</emphasis> amount of memory (in MB)
    a module may use during image processing. Lower values will force memory hungry modules to
    process an image with increasing number of tiles. Setting this to 0 will omit any limits.
    Values below 500 will be treated as 500. On a 32bit system you should set this to 500. Needs
    a restart if changed (default 1500).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">minimum amount of memory (in MB) for a single buffer in tiling</bridgehead>

  <para>
    If set to a positive, non-zero value, this variable defines the <emphasis>minimum</emphasis>
    amount of memory (in MB) that darktable should take for a single tile. On a 32bit system you
    should set this to 8. 64bit systems can live with higher values. Needs a restart if changed
    (default 16).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">write sidecar file for each image</bridgehead>

  <para>
    These redundant XMP files can later be re-imported into a different database, preserving
    your changes to the image. It's strongly recommended to have this option activated so you
    don't lose data in case of a database corruption. Backing up your raw file plus the
    accompanying XMP file will allow you to fully restore your work (default on).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">store xmp tags in compressed format</bridgehead>

  <para>
    Entries in XMP tags can get rather large and may exceed the available space to store the
    history stack in output files on export. This option allows binary XMP tags to be compressed
    in order to save space. Available options are <quote>never</quote>, <quote>always</quote>,
    and <quote>only large entries</quote> (default).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">omit hierarchy in simple tag lists</bridgehead>

  <para>
    When exporting images the hierarchical tags are also added as a simple list of
    non-hierarchical ones to make them visible to some other programs. When this option is
    checked darktable will only include their last part and ignore the rest. So
    <quote>foo|bar|baz</quote> will only add <quote>baz</quote>.
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">activate OpenCL support</bridgehead>

  <para>
    darktable can use your GPU to speed up processing significantly. Interface OpenCL requires
    suitable hardware and matching OpenCL drivers on your system. If one of those is not found
    the option is greyed out. Can be switched on and off at any time and takes immediate effect
    (default on).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">OpenCL scheduling profile</bridgehead>

  <para>
    Defines how preview and full pixelpipe tasks are scheduled on OpenCL enabled systems.
    <quote>default</quote>: the GPU processes the center view pixelpipe and the CPU processes
    the preview pipe; <quote>multiple GPUs</quote>: both pixelpipes are processed in parallel on
    two different GPUs; <quote>very fast GPU</quote>: both pixelipes are processed sequentially
    on the GPU.
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">always use LittleCMS 2 to apply output color profile</bridgehead>

  <para>
    If this option is activated, darktable will use system library LittleCMS 2 instead of its
    own routines. This is significantly slower than the default but might give more accurate
    results in some cases (default off).
  </para>

  <para>
    Note that if the given ICC is LUT-based or contains both, a LUT and a matrix, darktable will
    use LittleCMS 2 to render the colors regardless of this configuration parameter's value.
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">do high quality resampling during export</bridgehead>

  <para>
    The image will first be processed in full resolution, and downscaled at the very end. This
    can result in better quality sometimes, but will always be slower (default off).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">demosaicing for zoomed out darkroom mode</bridgehead>

  <para>
    Interpolation when not viewing 1:1 in darkroom mode: <quote>always bilinear (fast)</quote>
    is fastest, but not as sharp. <quote>at most ppg (reasonable)</quote> is using ppg +
    interpolation modes specified below, <quote>full (possibly slow)</quote> will use exactly
    the settings for full-size export (default <quote>at most ppg (reasonable)</quote>).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">pixel interpolator</bridgehead>

  <para>
    Pixel interpolator used in rotation, lens correction, up-and-down scaling; options are
    <quote>bilinear</quote>, <quote>bicubic</quote>, <quote>lanczos2</quote>,
    <quote>lanczos3</quote> (default).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">password storage backend to use</bridgehead>

  <para>
    The storage backend for password storage. Options: <quote>auto</quote> (default),
    <quote>none</quote>, <quote>libsecret</quote>, <quote>kwallet</quote>.
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">look for updated xmp files on startup</bridgehead>

  <para>
    Check file modification times of all XMP files on startup to find out if any got updated in
    the meantime by some other software. If updated XMP files are found a menu opens for the
    user to decide which of the XMP files to be reloaded&nbsp;&ndash; replacing darktable's
    database entries by the XMP file contents&nbsp;&ndash; and which of the XMP files to be
    overwritten by darktable's database. Activating this option also causes darktable to check
    for text sidecar files that have been added after import time&nbsp;&ndash; see option
    <quote>overlay txt sidecar over zoomed images</quote> in <xref linkend="gui_options"/>
    (default off).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">executable for playing audio files</bridgehead>

  <para>
    Defines an external program which is used in the lighttable view to play audio files that
    some cameras record to keep notes for images (default <quote>aplay</quote>).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">auto-apply per camera basecurve presets</bridgehead>

  <para>
    Use the per-camera basecurve by default instead of the generic manufacturer one if there is
    one available. For more details see <xref linkend="base_curve"/> (default off).
  </para>

<!--
<bridgehead renderas="sect4">run indexer</bridgehead>
<para>This will index images in background, so you can search them by similarity (default off).</para>
-->

</sect1>
