<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect1 status="final" id="darkroom_options">

    <title>Darkroom</title>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect5">pen pressure control for brush masks</bridgehead>

    <para>
      Controls how the pressure reading of a graphics tablet impacts newly generated brush strokes
      (see <xref linkend="drawn_mask"/>). You can control the brush width, its hardness and its
      opacity. <quote>Absolute</quote> control means that the pressure reading directly defines
      the attribute with a value between 0% and 100%. <quote>Relative</quote> means that the
      pressure reading adjusts the attribute between zero and the pre-defined default value
      (default off).
    </para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect5">smoothing of brush strokes</bridgehead>

    <para>
      Sets the level for smoothing of brush strokes. Stronger smoothing leads to less nodes and
      easier editing at the expense of lower accuracy.
    </para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect5">display of individual color channels</bridgehead>

    <para>
      Controls how individual color channels are displayed when activated in the parametric masks
      feature. You can choose between <quote>false color</quote> and <quote>grey scale</quote>
      (default false color).
    </para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect5">pattern for the image infos line</bridgehead>

    <para>
      Defines pattern for the image infos line in darkroom. See <xref linkend="session_options"/>
      for available values.
    </para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect5">position of the image info line</bridgehead>

    <para>
      Controls in which panel we display the image info line. You can choose between
      <quote>top left</quote> <quote>top right</quote> <quote>top center</quote> <quote>bottom</quote>
      and <quote>hidden</quote> (default bottom).
    </para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect5">show search module text entry</bridgehead>

    <para>
      Controls how to determine which modules are shown at the same time in the right panel.
      You can choose between
      <quote>groups icons</quote> <quote>search entry</quote> <quote>both</quote> (default both). (need a restart)
    </para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect5">expand a single darkroom module at a time</bridgehead>

    <para>
      Controls how darkroom modules are expanded. If this option is enabled, expanding a module by
      <emphasis>clicking</emphasis> collapses any other currently expanded module. If you want to expand
      a module without collapsing the others you do so with <emphasis>Shift+click</emphasis>.
      Disabling this option inverts the meaning of <emphasis>click</emphasis> and
      <emphasis>Shift+click</emphasis> (default on).
    </para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect5">only collapse modules in current group</bridgehead>

    <para>
      When choosing to expand a single darkroom module at a time (using the logic defined
      in the previous setting), only collapse other modules in the current visible group.
      Disable this option to ensure that modules in non-visible groups are also collapsed (default on).
    </para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect5">expand the module when it is activated, and collapse it when disabled</bridgehead>

    <para>
      This option allows to expand or collapse automatically modules when they are enabled or disabled.
      (default off)
    </para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect5">scroll to darkroom modules when expanded/collapsed</bridgehead>

    <para>
      With this option enabled the darkroom side panel will scroll a module to the top when it is
      expanded or collapsed (default on).
    </para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect5">border around image in darkroom mode</bridgehead>

    <para>
      Process the image in darkroom mode with a small border of the given number of pixels
      (default 20).
    </para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect5">show scrollbars for central view</bridgehead>

    <para>
      Defines whether scrollbars should be display in central view.
    </para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect5">demosaicing for zoomed out darkroom mode</bridgehead>

    <para>
      Interpolation when not viewing 1:1 in darkroom mode: <quote>always bilinear (fast)</quote>
      is fastest, but not as sharp. <quote>at most ppg (reasonable)</quote> is using ppg +
      interpolation modes specified below, <quote>full (possibly slow)</quote> will use exactly
      the settings for full-size export (default <quote>at most ppg (reasonable)</quote>).
    </para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect5">reduce resolution of preview image</bridgehead>

    <para>
      This reduces the resolution of the preview window at the
      upper-left of the screen. Consequently, calculations for
      re-drawing this window are reduced to 1/4, 1/9 or 1/16 of the
      main window. Sometimes coordinates for handles are borrowed from
      the preview, so it may rarely be useful to return to full scale.
    </para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect5">white balance slider colors</bridgehead>

    <para>
      Select one of the mode (<quote>effect emulation</quote>
      or <quote>illuminant color</quote>) for the white balance slider
      controls or no color at all.
    </para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect5">colorbalance slider block layout</bridgehead>

    <para>
      One of the layout for the colorbalance controls. A vertical
      list, a tabulated or columned view.
    </para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect5">show right-side buttons in darkroom module headers</bridgehead>

    <para>
      Choose whether to show the three buttons on the right-hand side of the module headers.
      The buttons for multi-instance, reset and presets, will always appear when the mouse is on the module itself.
      At other times, they can be hidden in various situations; especially when a narrow panel width
      would otherwise make the module name hard to read.
      Independent of panel width or name length;
      <quote>always</quote> (show), <quote>active</quote> (hide), <quote>dim</quote> (show dimmed).
      Narrow panel:
      <quote>auto</quote>, <quote>fade</quote> (gruadually dim)
      Long name:
      <quote>fit</quote>, <quote>smooth</quote> (gradually dim), <quote>glide</quote> (dim individual buttons)
    </para>

</sect1>
