<sect1 status="final" id="gui_options">

  <title>GUI options</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>preferences and settings</primary>
    <secondary>GUI options</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    These options control the look and feel of darktable.
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">width of the side panels in pixels</bridgehead>

  <para>
    This controls the size of side panels in pixels. Side panels are found left and right to the
    center view (default 300).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">don't use embedded preview jpeg but half-size raw</bridgehead>

  <para>
    Check this option to not use the embedded jpeg from the raw file but process the raw data.
    This is slower but gives you color managed thumbnails (default off).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">ask before removing images from database</bridgehead>

  <para>
    Always ask the user before any image is removed from the database (default on).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">ask before erasing images from disk</bridgehead>

  <para>
    Always ask the user before any image file is deleted (default on).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">ask before moving images from film roll folder</bridgehead>

  <para>
    Always ask the user before any image file is moved (default on).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">ask before copying images to new film roll folder</bridgehead>

  <para>
    Always ask the user before any image file is copied (default on).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">number of folder levels to show in lists</bridgehead>

  <para>
    The number of folder levels to show in film roll names, starting from the right (default 1).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">ignore jpeg images when importing film rolls</bridgehead>

  <para>
    When having RAW+JPEG images together in one directory it makes no sense to import both. With
    this flag one can ignore all jpegs found (default off).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">recursive directory traversal when importing film rolls</bridgehead>

  <para>
    Not only import images from the directory selected but recursively go through all
    subdirectories as well (default off).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">creator to be applied when importing</bridgehead>

  <para>
    If provided, automatically add this string as a creator tag when importing images (default
    none).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">publisher to be applied when importing</bridgehead>

  <para>
    If provided, automatically add this string as a publisher tag when importing images (default
    none).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">rights to be applied when importing</bridgehead>

  <para>
    If provided, automatically add this string as a copyrights tag when importing images
    (default none).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">comma separated tags to be applied when importing</bridgehead>

  <para>
    If you want to add further tags when importing images, you can give them as a comma
    separated list (default none).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">initial import rating</bridgehead>

  <para>
    Initial star rating (from 0 to 5) for all images when importing a film roll (default 1).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">enable filmstrip</bridgehead>

  <para>
    Enable the filmstrip in darkroom, tethering and geomapping modes (default on).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">maximum width of image drawing area</bridgehead>

  <para>
    Maximum width of the image drawing area in darkroom mode - adjust to your screen. Needs a
    restart and will invalidate current thumbnail caches (default 1300).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">maximum height of image drawing area</bridgehead>

  <para>
    Maximum height of the image drawing area in darkroom mode - adjust to your screen. Needs a
    restart and will invalidate current thumbnail caches (default 1000).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">compression of thumbnail images</bridgehead>

  <para>
    Controls the compression of thumbnail images in memory and on disk. Options:
    <quote>off</quote>, <quote>low quality (fast)</quote>, <quote>high quality (slow)</quote>;
    (default off).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">pen pressure control for brush masks</bridgehead>

  <para>
    Controls how the pressure reading of a graphics tablet impacts newly generated brush strokes
    (see <xref linkend="drawn_mask"/>). You can control the brush width, its hardness and its
    opacity. <quote>Absolute</quote> control means that the pressure reading directly defines
    the attribute with a value between 0% and 100%. <quote>Relative</quote> means that the
    pressure reading adjusts the attribute between zero and the pre-defined default value
    (default off).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">ask before deleting a tag</bridgehead>

  <para>
    Always ask user before deleting a tag from an image (default on).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">maximum number of images drawn on map</bridgehead>

  <para>
    The maximum number of geotagged images drawn on the map. Increasing this number can slow
    down the drawing of the map. Needs a restart if changed (default 100).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">pretty print the image location</bridgehead>

  <para>
    Show a more readable representation of the geo location in the image information module
    (default on).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">expand a single lighttable module at a time</bridgehead>

  <para>
    Controls how lighttable panels are expanded. If this option is enabled, expanding a panel by
    <emphasis>clicking</emphasis> collapses any currently expanded panel. If you want to expand
    a panel without collapsing the others you do so with <emphasis>shift+click</emphasis>.
    Disabling this option reverts the meaning of <emphasis>click</emphasis> and
    <emphasis>shift+click</emphasis> (default off).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">expand a single darkroom module at a time</bridgehead>

  <para>
    Controls how darkroom modules are expanded. If this option is enabled, expanding a module by
    <emphasis>clicking</emphasis> collapses any currently expanded module. If you want to expand
    a module without collapsing the others you do so with <emphasis>shift+click</emphasis>.
    Disabling this option reverts the meaning of <emphasis>click</emphasis> and
    <emphasis>shift+click</emphasis> (default on).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">method to use for getting the display profile</bridgehead>

  <para>
    This option allows to force a specific means of getting the current display profile in the
    output color profile module (see <xref linkend="output_color_profile"/>). In the default
    setting <quote>all</quote> darktable will either query the X display server's xatom or the
    <emphasis>colord</emphasis> system service. You can set this option to <quote>xatom</quote>
    or <quote>colord</quote> to enforce a specific method if the alternative gives wrong
    results.
  </para>

</sect1>
