<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect1 status="final" id="gui_options">

  <title>GUI options</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>preferences and settings</primary>
    <secondary>GUI options</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    These options control the look and feel of darktable.
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">width of the side panels in pixels</bridgehead>

  <para>
    This controls the size of side panels in pixels. Side panels are found left and right to the
    center view (default 350).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">don't use embedded preview JPEG but half-size raw</bridgehead>

  <para>
    Check this option to not use the embedded JPEG from the raw file but process the raw data.
    This is slower. (default off).
<!-- but prevents you from getting false impressions from camera-processed thumbnail -->
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">ask before removing images from database</bridgehead>

  <para>
    Always ask the user before any image is removed from the database (default on).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">ask before erasing images from disk</bridgehead>

  <para>
    Always ask the user before any image file is deleted (default on).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">send files to trash when erasing images</bridgehead>

  <para>
    Instead of physically deleting images from disk put them into the system's trash bin
    (default on).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">ask before moving images from film roll folder</bridgehead>

  <para>
    Always ask the user before any image file is moved (default on).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">ask before copying images to new film roll folder</bridgehead>

  <para>
    Always ask the user before any image file is copied (default on).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">number of folder levels to show in lists</bridgehead>

  <para>
    The number of folder levels to show in film roll names, starting from the right (default 1).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">ignore JPEG images when importing film rolls</bridgehead>

  <para>
    When having RAW+JPEG images together in one directory it makes no sense to import both. With
    this flag one can ignore all JPEGs found (default off).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">recursive directory traversal when importing film rolls</bridgehead>

  <para>
    Not only import images from the directory selected but recursively go through all
    subdirectories as well (default off).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">creator to be applied when importing</bridgehead>

  <para>
    If provided, automatically add this string as a creator tag when importing images (default
    none).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">publisher to be applied when importing</bridgehead>

  <para>
    If provided, automatically add this string as a publisher tag when importing images (default
    none).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">rights to be applied when importing</bridgehead>

  <para>
    If provided, automatically add this string as a copyrights tag when importing images
    (default none).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">comma separated tags to be applied when importing</bridgehead>

  <para>
    If you want to add further tags when importing images, you can give them as a comma
    separated list (default none).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">initial import rating</bridgehead>

  <para>
    Initial star rating (from 0 to 5) for all images when importing a film roll (default 1).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">enable filmstrip</bridgehead>

  <para>
    Enable the filmstrip in darkroom, tethering and geomapping modes (default on).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">high quality thumb processing from size</bridgehead>

  <para>
    If the thumbnails size is greater than this value, it will be processed using the full
    quality rendering path which is better but slower (default 720p).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">enable extended thumb overlay</bridgehead>

  <para>
    If enabled adds additional information to the thumbnail under the mouse cursor: image name,
    exposure time, aperture, focal length, ISO value (default off).
  </para>

<!--  
  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">maximum width of image drawing area</bridgehead>

  <para>
    Maximum width of the image drawing area in darkroom mode&nbsp;&ndash; adjust to your screen.
    Needs a restart and will invalidate current thumbnail caches (default 1300).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">maximum height of image drawing area</bridgehead>

  <para>
    Maximum height of the image drawing area in darkroom mode&nbsp;&ndash; adjust to your
    screen. Needs a restart and will invalidate current thumbnail caches (default 1000).
  </para>
  
  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">compression of thumbnail images</bridgehead>

  <para>
    Controls the compression of thumbnail images in memory and on disk. Options:
    <quote>off</quote>, <quote>low quality (fast)</quote>, <quote>high quality (slow)</quote>;
    (default off).
  </para>
-->

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">pen pressure control for brush masks</bridgehead>

  <para>
    Controls how the pressure reading of a graphics tablet impacts newly generated brush strokes
    (see <xref linkend="drawn_mask"/>). You can control the brush width, its hardness and its
    opacity. <quote>Absolute</quote> control means that the pressure reading directly defines
    the attribute with a value between 0% and 100%. <quote>Relative</quote> means that the
    pressure reading adjusts the attribute between zero and the pre-defined default value
    (default off).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">smoothing of brush strokes</bridgehead>

  <para>
    Sets the level for smoothing of brush strokes. Stronger smoothing leads to less nodes and
    easier editing at the expense of lower accuracy.
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">display of individual color channels</bridgehead>

  <para>
    Controls how individual color channels are displayed when activated in the parametric masks
    feature. You can choose between <quote>false color</quote> and <quote>grey scale</quote>
    (default false color).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">ask before deleting a tag</bridgehead>

  <para>
    Always ask user before deleting a tag from an image (default on).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">only draw images on map that are currently collected and filtered</bridgehead>

  <para>
    Use the current filter settings to select the geotagged images drawn in the map view. This
    limits the images drawn to those currently shown in the filmstrip and thus reduces the time
    needed (default off).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">maximum number of images drawn on map</bridgehead>

  <para>
    The maximum number of geotagged images drawn on the map. Increasing this number can slow
    down the drawing of the map. Needs a restart if changed (default 100).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">pretty print the image location</bridgehead>

  <para>
    Show a more readable representation of the geo location in the image information module
    (default on).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">overlay txt sidecar over zoomed images</bridgehead>

  <para>
    When there is a text file next to an image it can be shown as an overlay over zoomed images
    on the lighttable. The text file has the same base name as the image file with file
    extension <quote>.txt</quote>. It either has to be there at import time or the crawler has
    to be enabled&nbsp;&ndash; see option <quote>look for updated xmp files on startup</quote>
    in <xref linkend="core_options"/> (default off).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">expand a single lighttable module at a time</bridgehead>

  <para>
    Controls how lighttable panels are expanded. If this option is enabled, expanding a panel by
    <emphasis>clicking</emphasis> collapses any currently expanded panel. If you want to expand
    a panel without collapsing the others you do so with <emphasis>shift-click</emphasis>.
    Disabling this option reverts the meaning of <emphasis>click</emphasis> and
    <emphasis>shift-click</emphasis> (default off).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">expand a single darkroom module at a time</bridgehead>

  <para>
    Controls how darkroom modules are expanded. If this option is enabled, expanding a module by
    <emphasis>clicking</emphasis> collapses any currently expanded module. If you want to expand
    a module without collapsing the others you do so with <emphasis>shift-click</emphasis>.
    Disabling this option reverts the meaning of <emphasis>click</emphasis> and
    <emphasis>shift-click</emphasis> (default on).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">scroll to lighttable modules when expanded/collapsed</bridgehead>

  <para>
    With this option enabled the lighttable side panels will scroll a module to the top when it
    is expanded or collapsed (default off).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">scroll to darkroom modules when expanded/collapsed</bridgehead>

  <para>
    With this option enabled the darkroom side panel will scroll a module to the top when it is
    expanded or collapsed (default on).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">border around image in darkroom mode</bridgehead>

  <para>
    Process the image in darkroom mode with a small border of the given number of pixels
    (default 20).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">do high quality processing for slideshow</bridgehead>

  <para>
    Controls how images are processed for the slideshow view. It this option is enabled, the
    image will first be processed in full resolution, and downscaled at the very end. This can
    result in better quality sometimes, but will always be slower (default on).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">rating an image one star twice will not zero out the rating</bridgehead>

  <para>
    Normally clicking a one star rating twice will set a zero star rating to that image. When
    checking this option a second click on a one star rating will keep that rating (default
    off).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">method to use for getting the display profile</bridgehead>

  <para>
    This option allows to force a specific way of getting the current display profile for color
    management (see <xref linkend="rendering_method"/>). In the default setting
    <quote>all</quote> darktable will either query the X display server's xatom or the
    <emphasis>colord</emphasis> system service. You can set this option to <quote>xatom</quote>
    or <quote>colord</quote> to enforce a specific method if the alternative gives wrong
    results.
  </para>

</sect1>
