<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect1 status="final" id="shortcuts">

  <title>Shortcuts</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>preferences and settings</primary>
    <secondary>shortcuts</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
     Much of the functionality of darktable can be accessed via shortcuts using the keyboard or 
     keyboard/mouse combinations. These shortcuts are user-configurable via the shortcuts tab of 
     the preferences dialog. Many of the key shortcuts are provided with default values but most 
     must be configured by the user. Any key may be used for a keyboard shortcut, and may be 
     modified with one or more of <emphasis>Shift</emphasis>, <emphasis>Ctrl</emphasis> or 
     <emphasis>Alt</emphasis>.
  </para>

  <sect2 id="shortcuts_adjusting">

     <title>Adjusting Keyboard Shortcuts</title>

     <sect3 id="shortcuts_adjusting_add">

        <title>Add/Amend Shortcut</title>

        <para>
           In order to add or amend shortcut, first navigate to the action you want to change 
           and double-click on it. You will be prompted to press the new key combination to be 
           mapped to the selected action.
        </para>

        <para>
           If a conflict is found you will be given the option to retain the existing shortcut 
           or replace it. Depending on context, it is possible to use the same keyboard shortcut 
           for multiple actions. For example the same key combination may be used for one action 
           in the lighttable view and another in the darkroom view.
        </para>

     </sect3>

     <sect3 id="shortcuts_adjusting_del">

        <title>Remove Shortcut</title>

        <para>
           To remove a keyboard shortcut, single-click on the action you wish to remove and press 
           the backspace key.
        </para>

     </sect3>
        
     <sect3 id="shortcuts_adjusting_search">

        <title>Search</title>

        <para>
           A search field is shown at the bottom of the shortcuts tab. Enter the text you wish to 
           search for and press enter or click the search button. Pressing enter or search multiple 
           times will cycle through all matching actions.
        </para>

     </sect3>

  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="shortcuts_imp_exp_reset">

     <title>Import/Export/Reset</title>

     <para>
           You can export your shortcut mappings to a file or import from a file.
     </para>

     <para>
        Press “default” to reset all shortcuts to their default state. Take care when using this 
        option as it is not possible to restore back to a previous state unless you have first 
        exported existing shortcuts to a file.
     </para>

  </sect2>
        
  <sect2 id="shortcuts_categories">

     <title>Shortcut Categories</title>

     <para>
        Keyboard shortcuts are categorized so that they can easily be found. The following sections 
        summarize these categories and also list some additional options that are specific to certain 
        categories.
     </para>

     <sect3 id="shortcuts_categories_global">

        <title>global</title>

        <para>
           Shortcuts in this section are applicable to all darktable views.
        </para>

     </sect3>

     <sect3 id="shortcuts_categories_views">

        <title>views</title>

        <para>
           A single section is provided for each darktable view. Shortcuts are only applicable to the 
           selected view.
        </para>

     </sect3>

     <sect3 id="shortcuts_categories_iop">

        <title>processing modules</title>

        <para>
           Shortcuts in this section are only applicable to the ‘processing’ modules in the 
           darktable view (i.e. those modules to the right of the edited image below the histogram and 
           above the ‘module order’ module). A section is provided for each processing module.
        </para>

        <bridgehead renderas="sect5">common shortcuts</bridgehead>

        <para>
           Every processing module provides the following shortcuts by default
        </para>

        <itemizedlist>
           <listitem><para>
              <emphasis>enable module</emphasis> - enable or disable the module, regardless of whether it is 
              currently visible
           </para></listitem>
           <listitem><para>
              <emphasis>show module</emphasis> - expand or collapse the module. If the module is not currently 
              displayed on the screen, darktable will switch to an appropriate module group (if applicable) 
              before displaying it
           </para></listitem>
           <listitem><para>
              <emphasis>focus module</emphasis> - cause the module to receive or lose focus
           </para></listitem>
           <listitem><para>
              <emphasis>reset module parameters</emphasis> - reset the module to its default state
           </para></listitem>
           <listitem><para>
              <emphasis>show preset menu</emphasis> - show the presets menu for the module
           </para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>
           Shortcuts may be present for any module operation. For comboboxes and sliders, some standard shortcuts are 
           available, as described in the following sections.
        </para>

        <bridgehead renderas="sect5">sliders</bridgehead>

        <para>
           All sliders in processing modules can be edited via keyboard shortcuts (regardless of whether the 
           module is currently shown or enabled). The following actions are provided:
        </para>

        <itemizedlist>
           <listitem><para>
              <emphasis>increase/decrease</emphasis> - separate shortcuts which allow you to increase or decrease the 
              slider by a single step
           </para></listitem>
           <listitem><para>
              <emphasis>dynamic</emphasis> - a single shortcut that can be used in combination with the mouse scroll 
              wheel to increase and decrease slider values
           </para></listitem>
           <listitem><para>
              <emphasis>edit</emphasis> -a shortcut to bring up the slider edit dialog within which you may key a 
              value directly or modify the slider with the mouse 
           </para></listitem>
           <listitem><para>
              <emphasis>reset</emphasis> - reset the slider to its default value
           </para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>
           In addition, it is possible to modify the coarseness of the increase/decrease operations with a 
           <emphasis>global</emphasis> keyboard shortcut. You can choose between fine, normal and coarse.
        </para>

        <para>
           When performing increase/decrease and dynamic operations on sliders, if the module is not currently 
           shown, a toast message will appear over the image to indicate the current value of the slider being
           adjusted.
        </para>

        <bridgehead renderas="sect5">comboboxes</bridgehead>

        <para>
           As with sliders, all comboboxes in processing modules can be edited via keyboard shortcuts. 
           The following actions are provided:
        </para>

        <itemizedlist>
           <listitem><para>
              <emphasis>next/previous</emphasis> - separate shortcuts which allow you to change to the next 
              or previous entry in the combobox
           </para></listitem>
           <listitem><para>
              <emphasis>dynamic</emphasis> - a single shortcut that can be used in combination with the 
              mouse scroll wheel to change to the next/previous entry in the combobox
           </para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>
           If the end of the combobox values is reached, these shortcuts will cycle back to the beginning 
           of the list. Similarly, if the beginning of values is reached it will cycle to the end.
        </para>

        <para>
           If the module is not currently shown, a toast message will appear over the image to indicate
           the current value of the combobox being adjusted.
        </para>

        <bridgehead renderas="sect5">handling multiple module instances</bridgehead>

        <para>
           It is possible to create multiple instances of many processing modules. In this scenario 
           it is not always obvious which instance should be controlled by keyboard shortcut operations. 
           Some additional options are present in the miscellaneous tab of the preferences dialog. 
           These options control rules that are applied (in order) to decide which module instance keyboard 
           shortcuts will be applied to.
        </para>

        <itemizedlist>
           <listitem><para>
              <emphasis>prefer expanded instances</emphasis> - if instances of the module are expanded, ignore collapsed instances
           </para></listitem>
           <listitem><para>
              <emphasis>prefer enabled instances</emphasis> - after applying the above rule, if instances of the module are active, 
              ignore inactive instances
           </para></listitem>
           <listitem><para>
              <emphasis>prefer unmasked instances</emphasis> - after applying the above rules, if instances of the module are unmasked, 
              ignore masked instances
           </para></listitem>
           <listitem><para>
              <emphasis>selection order</emphasis> - after applying the above rules, apply the shortcut to the first or last instance remaining
           </para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>
           These rules are also used when clicking and dragging on the histogram to change exposure.
        </para>

     </sect3>
  </sect2>
        
  <sect2 id="shortcuts_libs">

     <title>utility modules</title>

     <para>
        Shortcuts in the utility modules section apply to modules that are not used for image processing, may appear on either 
        side of the screen and may apply to one or more views.
     </para>

     <para>
        As with processing modules, some shortcuts are provided by default:
     </para>

     <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>
           <emphasis>show module</emphasis> - expand or collapse the module
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
           <emphasis>reset module parameters</emphasis> - reset the module to its default state
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
           <emphasis>show preset menu</emphasis> - show the presets menu for the module
        </para></listitem>
     </itemizedlist>

     <para>
        Some of the above options may not be applicable to all modules.
     </para>

  </sect2>

</sect1>
