<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect1 status="final" id="lighttable_options">

    <title>Lighttable</title>
    
    <bridgehead renderas="sect5">color manage cached thumbnails</bridgehead>

    <para>
      If activated darktable generates thumbnails in a general color space (AdobeRGB) in order to
      render them independently of the individual monitor. Conversion to the monitor color space
      is done at display time. If this option is not activated thumbnails are directly stored in
      the specific monitor color space valid at generation time and are subsequently displayed
      without further corrections (default on).
    </para>
    
    <bridgehead renderas="sect5">don't use embedded preview JPEG but half-size raw</bridgehead>

    <para>
      Check this option to not use the embedded JPEG from the raw file but process the raw data.
      This is slower. (default off).
    </para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect5">number of folder levels to show in lists</bridgehead>

    <para>
      The number of folder levels to show in film roll names, starting from the right (default 1).
    </para>
    
    <bridgehead renderas="sect5">sort film rolls by</bridgehead>

    <para>
      Set the collection list order for film rolls.
    </para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect5">sort collection recent to older</bridgehead>

    <para>
      Changes the default collections list for folders, times and dates to run from recent to older.
    </para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect5">high quality thumb processing from size</bridgehead>

    <para>
      If the thumbnails size is greater than this value, it will be processed using the full
      quality rendering path which is better but slower (default 720p).
    </para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect5">delimiters for sizes categories</bridgehead>

    <para>
      Sizes categories are used to be able to set different overlays and css values depending of
      the size of the thumbnail. Set here thumbnails sizes delimiters.
    </para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect5">pattern for the thumbnail extended overlay text</bridgehead>

    <para>
      If enabled adds additional information to the thumbnail under the mouse cursor: image name,
      exposure time, aperture, focal length, ISO value (default off).
    </para>
    
    <bridgehead renderas="sect5">pattern for the thumbnail tooltip (empty to disable)</bridgehead>

    <para>
      Define the pattern for the thumbnail tooltip. Empty it to disable thumbnail tooltip. As for
      previous pattern, see <xref linkend="session_options"/> for possible tags to use.
    </para>
    
    <bridgehead renderas="sect5">use single-click in the collect panel</bridgehead>

    <para>
      (default off). In single-click mode, you can select range of value directly with the mouse.
    </para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect5">overlay txt sidecar over zoomed images</bridgehead>

    <para>
      When there is a txt file next to an image, it can be shown as an overlay over zoomed images
      on the lighttable. The txt file either has to be there at import time or the crawler  has to be enabled.
    </para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect5">expand a single lighttable module at a time</bridgehead>

    <para>
      Controls how lighttable panels are expanded. If this option is enabled, expanding a panel by
      <emphasis>clicking</emphasis> collapses any currently expanded panel. If you want to expand
      a panel without collapsing the others you do so with <emphasis>Shift+click</emphasis>.
      Disabling this option reverts the meaning of <emphasis>click</emphasis> and
      <emphasis>Shift+click</emphasis> (default off).
    </para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect5">scroll to lighttable modules when expanded/collapsed</bridgehead>

    <para>
      With this option enabled the lighttable side panels will scroll a module to the top when it
      is expanded or collapsed (default off).
    </para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect5">rating an image one star twice will not zero out the rating</bridgehead>

    <para>
      Normally clicking a one star rating twice will set a zero star rating to that image. When
      checking this option a second click on a one star rating will keep that rating (default
      off).
    </para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect5">show scrollbars for central view</bridgehead>

    <para>
      Defines whether scrollbars should be display in central view.
    </para>

</sect1>
