<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect1 status="final" id="presets">

  <title>Presets</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>preferences and settings</primary>
    <secondary>presets</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>presets</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    This menu gives you an overview of the presets that are defined for darktable's modules. In
    this dialog you can select whether a certain user defined preset shall be auto-applied to
    matching images.
  </para>

  <para>
    darktable already comes with a set of pre-defined presets for several modules. In addition
    you can define your own presets from within each module in darkroom mode (see
    <xref linkend="module_presets"/>).
  </para>

  <para>
    Pre-defined presets are shown with a lock symbol. Their auto-apply properties can not be
    changed.
  </para>

  <para>
    Double clicking on a user-defined preset will open a menu.
  </para>

  <para>
    <graphic fileref="preferences/images/presets.png" scalefit="1" width="60%" align="center" />
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">auto apply this preset to matching images</bridgehead>

  <para>
    activate this checkbutton to automatically apply the preset on newly imported images; a set
    of fields is displayed where you can define patterns to be matched against Exif data.
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">only show this preset for matching images</bridgehead>

  <para>
    activate this checkbutton to hide the preset in darkroom mode if it does not match the
    defined patterns.
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">model</bridgehead>

  <para>
    a pattern to be matched against the Exif field that describes your camera model; use "%" as
    wildcard.
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">maker</bridgehead>

  <para>
    a pattern to be matched against the Exif field that describes the maker of your camera; use
    "%" as wildcard.
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">lens</bridgehead>

  <para>
    a pattern to be matched against the Exif field that describes your lens; use "%" as
    wildcard.
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">iso</bridgehead>

  <para>
    only apply the preset if the ISO value of your image lies within the given range.
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">exposure</bridgehead>

  <para>
    only apply the preset if the exposure time of your image lies within the given range; set
    "+" as the upper value to match arbitrarily long exposures.
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">aperture</bridgehead>

  <para>
    only apply the preset if the aperture of your image lies within the given range; set "f/0"
    as the lower value to match arbitrarily open apertures; set "f/+" as the upper value to
    match arbitrarily closed apertures.
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect4">focal length</bridgehead>

  <para>
    only apply the preset if the focal length of your image lies within the given range (from 0
    to 1000).
  </para>

</sect1>
