<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect1 status="final" id="processing">

  <title>Processing</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>preferences and settings</primary>
    <secondary>processing</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    These options control some of the internals processing of darktable.
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect5">always use LittleCMS 2 to apply output color profile</bridgehead>

  <para>
    If this option is activated, darktable will use system library LittleCMS 2 instead of its
    own routines. This is significantly slower than the default but might give more accurate
    results in some cases (default off).
  </para>

  <para>
    Note that if the given ICC is LUT-based or contains both, a LUT and a matrix, darktable will
    use LittleCMS 2 to render the colors regardless of this configuration parameter's value.
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect5">pixel interpolator</bridgehead>

  <para>
    Pixel interpolator used in rotation, lens correction, up-and-down scaling; options are
    <quote>bilinear</quote>, <quote>bicubic</quote>, <quote>lanczos2</quote>,
    <quote>lanczos3</quote> (default).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect5">3D lut root folder</bridgehead>

  <para>
    Set folder that contains Lut files used by lut 3D module. (need a restart)
  </para>
  
  <bridgehead renderas="sect5">auto-apply pixel workflow defaults</bridgehead>

  <para>
    With that setting, you can define which default workflow to work on. Two workflows are available:
    <itemizedlist>

      <listitem><para><emphasis>Scene-referred workflow</emphasis> is based on linear modules and will auto-apply filmic and exposure.
      This workflow consist of adding, by default, +0,5 EV of exposure (in exposure module), to adjust the global
      brightness and mid-grey to a similar value to that used by most JPEGs produced by SLR cameras.
      The interest of filmic is to apply a tone mapping curve at the end of the pipeline, allowing a physically
      realistic retouching on RGB values encoded linearly before, but also to manage color consistency through the
      tone mapping, in order to preserve hues as much as possible and to avoid gamut overruns.
      </para>

      <para>
      This default +0,5 EV value can be overridden using an auto-apply preset if it is found the images from
      a particular camera are consistently too dark.
      </para>
      
      <para>
      The scene-referred workflow also enables by default the "compensate camera exposure" option in the exposure module,
      to adjust the global brightness appropriately in cases where the camera's exposure compensation dial was used to
      protect highlights in the image or Expose To The Right (ETTR) to optimally make use of the sensor's dynamic range.
      </para></listitem>
      
      <listitem><para><emphasis>Display-referred workflow</emphasis>, used by default, is based on Lab modules and will auto-apply
      base curve and the legacy module pipe order (darktable 2.6 and older). It will apply the non-linear
      transformation at the beginning of the pipeline, and all editing will then be done on non-linear RGB.
      </para></listitem>

    </itemizedlist>
  </para>

  <para>
      A third option is available to not use any workflow and so deactivate all automatic modules. That allow you
      to manage your pipeline manually.
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect5">auto-apply per camera basecurve presets</bridgehead>

  <para>
    Use the per-camera basecurve by default instead of the generic manufacturer one if there is
    one available. For more details see <xref linkend="base_curve"/> (default off).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect5">auto-apply sharpen</bridgehead>

  <para>
   This added sharpen is not recommended on cameras without a low-pass filter.
   The default is to not add any sharpening automatically as most recent cameras have no low-pass filter. (need a restart)
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect5">detect monochrome previews</bridgehead>

  <para>
   If switched on, darktable analyses the preview image available via exif data during import or refreshing exif for being monochrome
   and sets the darktable|mode|monochrome tag accordingly. As this reduces performance it is turned off by default.
   Turn on for better monochrome image workflow support.
  </para>
</sect1>
