<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect1 status="final" id="storage">

  <title>Storage</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>preferences and settings</primary>
    <secondary>storage</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    These options control storage used by darktable.
  </para>
  
  <sect2 id="database">

    <title>database</title>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect5">check for database maintenance</bridgehead>

    <para>
      This option indicates when to check database fragmentation and perform maintenance.
    </para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect5">database fragmentation ratio treshold</bridgehead>

    <para>
      Fragmentation ratio above which to ask or carry out automatically database maintenance.
    </para>

  </sect2>
  
  <sect2 id="xmp">

    <title>xmp</title>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect5">write sidecar file for each image</bridgehead>

    <para>
      These redundant XMP files can later be re-imported into a different database, preserving
      your changes to the image. It's strongly recommended to have this option activated so you
      don't lose data in case of a database corruption. Backing up your raw file plus the
      accompanying XMP file will allow you to fully restore your work (default on).
    </para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect5">store xmp tags in compressed format</bridgehead>

    <para>
      Entries in XMP tags can get rather large and may exceed the available space to store the
      history stack in output files on export. This option allows binary XMP tags to be compressed
      in order to save space. Available options are <quote>never</quote>, <quote>always</quote>,
      and <quote>only large entries</quote> (default).
    </para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect5">look for updated xmp files on startup</bridgehead>

    <para>
      Check file modification times of all XMP files on startup to find out if any got updated in
      the meantime by some other software. If updated XMP files are found a menu opens for the
      user to decide which of the XMP files to be reloaded&nbsp;&ndash; replacing darktable's
      database entries by the XMP file contents&nbsp;&ndash; and which of the XMP files to be
      overwritten by darktable's database. Activating this option also causes darktable to check
      for text sidecar files that have been added after import time&nbsp;&ndash; see option
      <quote>overlay txt sidecar over zoomed images</quote> in <xref linkend="lighttable_options"/>
      (default off).
    </para>

  </sect2>

</sect1>
