<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect2 status="final" id="collect_images">

  <title>Collect images</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>lighttable panels</primary>
    <secondary>collect images</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>collect images</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>collections</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <informaltable frame="none">
    <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
      <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
      <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
      <tbody>
        <row>
          <entry>
            The current view in lighttable is called a collection. The <emphasis>collect
            images</emphasis> panel lets you narrow down the list of visible images to just the
            ones you want to work with.
          </entry>
          <entry>
            <graphic fileref="lighttable/images/panel_collectimages.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
          </entry>
        </row>
      </tbody>
    </tgroup>
  </informaltable>

  <para>
    Information about all images imported into darktable are kept in a database, with various
    attributes describing each image. You define a collection by applying certain filtering
    rules to these attributes, creating a subset of images to display in the lighttable view.
  </para>

  <para>
    The default collection is based on the film roll attribute&nbsp;&ndash; it displays all
    images of the last imported film roll or any other film roll chosen.
  </para>

  <sect3 id="collect_images_usage">

    <title>Usage</title>

    <sect4 id="collect_images_usage_attributes">

      <title>image attributes</title>

      <para>
        The left combobox lets you choose from the available attributes:
        <informaltable frame="none" width="80%">
          <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
            <colspec colwidth='1*'/>
            <colspec colwidth='3*'/>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  film roll
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    the film roll to which the image belongs
                  </para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  folders
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    the disk folder where the input image file is located
                  </para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  camera
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    the Exif data entry describing the camera make and model
                  </para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  tag
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    any tag that is attached to the image; if activated a hierarchical list of
                    known tags is displayed for quick selection
                  </para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  date
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    the date when the photo was taken, in the format
                    <emphasis>YYYY:MM:DD</emphasis>
                  </para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  time
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    the time (date <emphasis>and</emphasis> time of day) when the photo was
                    taken, in the format <emphasis>YYYY:MM:DD hh:mm:ss</emphasis>
                  </para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  history
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    choose images whose history stacks have been altered or not altered
                  </para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  color label
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    any color label that is attached to the image: <quote>red</quote>,
                    <quote>yellow</quote>, <quote>green</quote>, <quote>blue</quote>,
                    <quote>purple</quote>
                  </para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  title
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    the title, as listed in the image's metadata <quote>title</quote> field
                  </para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  description
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    the description, as listed in the image's metadata
                    <quote>description</quote> field
                  </para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  creator
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    the creator, as listed in the image's metadata <quote>creator</quote> field
                  </para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  publisher
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    the publisher, as listed in the image's metadata <quote>publisher</quote>
                    field
                  </para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  rights
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    the copyrights statement, as written in the image's metadata
                    <quote>rights</quote> field
                  </para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  lens
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    the Exif data entry describing the lens
                  </para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  focal length
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    the focal length value, as derived from Exif data
                  </para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  ISO
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    the ISO value, as derived from Exif data
                  </para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  aperture
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    the aperture value, as derived from Exif data
                  </para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  filename
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    the filename of the physical input image
                  </para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  geotagging
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    the geo location of the image
                  </para>
                </entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
      </para>

    </sect4>

    <sect4 id="collect_images_usage_rules">

      <title>search rules</title>

      <para>
        In the text field to the right of the attribute, you write a pattern. The pattern is
        compared against all database entries with the selected attribute. This search detects a
        match if the images' attribute contains the pattern in its full text. You may use
        <emphasis>%</emphasis> as wildcard character. The collection gets limited to those
        images where the query matches. Leaving the text field empty matches all images for that
        attribute.
      </para>

      <para>
        Attributes with numerical values as well as date and time attributes can be used in
        combination with comparative and range operators. Write <emphasis>&lt;</emphasis>,
        <emphasis>&lt;=</emphasis>, <emphasis>&gt;</emphasis>, <emphasis>&gt;=</emphasis>,
        <emphasis>&lt;&gt;</emphasis>, and <emphasis>=</emphasis> to select images with
        attributes less, less or equal, greater, greater or equal, not equal, or equal to the a
        given value, respectively. An expression in the form <emphasis>[from;to]</emphasis>
        selects a range of values.
      </para>

      <para>
        The box below the search rule will list all matching database entries of the query you
        are currently working on. This list gets updated continuously as you type. You may also
        choose sorting criteria by scrolling through the list and double-clicking.
      </para>

      <para>
        Clicking on the triangle button to the right of the text field opens a drop-down menu
        with options to finetune your current collection by adding further rules, or removing
        them:
      </para>

      <sect5 id="collect_images_usage_rules_clear">
        <title>clear this rule</title>
        <para>
          Removes this rule&nbsp;&ndash; or resets to default if this is the only rule defined.
        </para>
      </sect5>

      <sect5 id="collect_images_usage_rules_narrow">
        <title>narrow down search</title>
        <para>
          Adds a new rule which is combined with the previous rule(s) in a logical
          <emphasis>AND</emphasis> operation. An image is only part of the collection if it
          additionally fulfills the added rule.
        </para>
      </sect5>

      <sect5 id="collect_images_usage_rules_more">
        <title>add more images</title>
        <para>
          Adds a new rule which is combined with the previous rule(s) in a logical
          <emphasis>OR</emphasis> operation. Images that fulfill the new rule are added to the
          collection.
        </para>
      </sect5>

      <sect5 id="collect_images_usage_rules_exclude">
        <title>exclude images</title>
        <para>
          Adds a new rule which is combined with the previous rule(s) in a logical
          <emphasis>EXCEPT</emphasis> operation. Images which are selected by the new rule are
          exempted from the collection.
        </para>
      </sect5>

    </sect4>

    <sect4 id="collect_images_usage_combining">

      <title>combining rules</title>

      <para>
        The logical operators defining the combination of rules are displayed to the right of
        the rule: <emphasis>AND</emphasis> by the
        <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_lighttable_and;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center" />
        symbol, <emphasis>OR</emphasis> by the
        <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_lighttable_or;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center" />
        symbol, and <emphasis>EXCEPT</emphasis> by the
        <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_lighttable_except;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center" />
        symbol. Clicking on either symbol gives a choice to change the logical operation.
      </para>

    </sect4>

    <sect4 id="collect_images_usage_update">

      <title>updating folder path</title>

      <para>
        While it is best to not touch imported files behind darktable's back, this module can
        help you recover from situations when you move imported folders after import. The
        collect images module has a feature that allows you to tell darktable about the new
        location of imported folders which have been moved. You set the combobox to
        <emphasis>folders</emphasis> to find the original folder name in the tree. The folder
        name will be displayed striked-out to emphasize that it is no longer there. Then you
        right-click on the folder name, select <quote>search filmroll...</quote>, and then
        select the new location of the folder.
      </para>

    </sect4>

  </sect3>

</sect2>
