<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect2 status="final" id="export_selected">

  <title>Export selected</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>lighttable panels</primary>
    <secondary>export</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>export</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>file export</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <informaltable frame="none">
    <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
      <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
      <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
      <tbody>
        <row>
          <entry>
            Each workflow ends in this panel: the export of your developed images. You can
            export either to a file on disk, or to various on-line storage places. You can also
            use <emphasis>Ctrl + e</emphasis> from within darkroom mode to export.
          </entry>
          <entry>
            <graphic fileref="lighttable/images/panel_exportselected.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
          </entry>
        </row>
      </tbody>
    </tgroup>
  </informaltable>

  <para>
    All settings for this panel can be saved for later reuse. Press the
    <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_module_presets;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center" />
    button to manage your presets.
  </para>

  <sect3>

    <title>Usage</title>

    <sect4>

      <title>target storage</title>

      <para>
        Where to store your selected images. Different back-ends are implemented, including file
        on disk, a LaTeX book template, and various web albums. Depending on the selected target,
        you will be asked to give additional information, like filenames, or account name and
        password.
      </para>

    </sect4>

    <sect4>

      <title>filename template</title>

      <para>
        You can define filenames that darktable generates for export. Several
        variables can be used as placeholders:
      </para>

      <informaltable frame="none" width="80%">
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                $(ROLL_NAME)
              </entry>
              <entry>
                film roll of the RAW input image
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                $(FILE_FOLDER)
              </entry>
              <entry>
                folder containing the RAW input image
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                $(FILE_NAME)
              </entry>
              <entry>
                basename of the RAW input image
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                $(FILE_EXTENSION)
              </entry>
              <entry>
                file extension of the RAW input image
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                $(SEQUENCE)
              </entry>
              <entry>
                a file's number among the sequence of files for the export job
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                $(YEAR)
              </entry>
              <entry>
                year at the date of export
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                $(MONTH)
              </entry>
              <entry>
                month at the date of export
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                $(DAY)
              </entry>
              <entry>
                day at the date of export
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                $(HOUR)
              </entry>
              <entry>
                hour at the time of export
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                $(MINUTE)
              </entry>
              <entry>
                minute at the time of export
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                $(SECOND)
              </entry>
              <entry>
                second at the time of export
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                $(EXIF_YEAR)
              </entry>
              <entry>
                year from the image's EXIF data, i.e., the year the photo was taken
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                $(EXIF_MONTH)
              </entry>
              <entry>
                month from the image's EXIF data, i.e., the month the photo was taken
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                $(EXIF_DAY)
              </entry>
              <entry>
                day from the image's EXIF data, i.e., the day the photo was taken
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                $(EXIF_HOUR)
              </entry>
              <entry>
                hour from the image's EXIF data, i.e., the hour the photo was taken
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                $(EXIF_MINUTE)
              </entry>
              <entry>
                minute from the image's EXIF data, i.e., the minute the photo was taken
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                $(EXIF_SECOND)
              </entry>
              <entry>
                second from the image's EXIF data, i.e., the second the photo was taken
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                $(STARS)
              </entry>
              <entry>
                the number for the image's star rating; so a rating of four stars will show as just <quote>4</quote>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                $(LABELS)
              </entry>
              <entry>
                the image's color label; if there are multiple labels, these are separated by commas without spaces
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                $(PICTURES_FOLDER)
              </entry>
              <entry>
                the desktop user account's default pictures folder
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                $(HOME)
              </entry>
              <entry>
                the desktop user account's home folder
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                $(DESKTOP)
              </entry>
              <entry>
                the desktop user account's <quote>desktop</quote> folder
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>

    </sect4>

    <sect4>

      <title>output directory</title>

      <para>
        Pressing the
        <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_directory;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center" />
        button opens a dialog to select a directory to contain the exported files.
      </para>

    </sect4>

    <sect4>

      <title>overwrite</title>

      <para>
        Enabling the
        <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_general_checkbox;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center" /> overwrite checkbox
        allows darktable to overwrite existing images during export. If this option is not checked,
        in cases of naming conflict, darktable automatically selects a new unique file name (generally adding
        a suffix like <quote>_1</quote> or <quote>_2</quote> before the file extensions). The overwrite
        option gets reset after each export in order to protect you from accidental data loss.
      </para>

    </sect4>

    <sect4>

      <title>file format</title>

      <para>
        darktable can export to various file formats. For some of them you need to define the
        desired bit depth of the exported image. If you export to a JPEG file, you can define an
        output quality, which determines how <quote>lossy</quote> the JPEG compression algorithm will be.
        (PNG and TIFF are lossless image formats.) Higher values for bit depth or JPEG quality
        will lead to larger file sizes.
      </para>

      <para>
        If the file format supports embedded metadata, like JPEG, JPEG2000 and TIFF, darktable
        will also try to store the history stack as XMP tags within the output file. This information
        can later be used to reconstruct your parameters and settings that have produced the
        exported image (see <xref linkend="history_stack"/>).
      </para>

      <para>
        <emphasis>Caution: for various reasons, embedding XMP tags into output files may fail
        without notice, e.g., if certain size limits are exceeded. Users are therefore advised to
        not completely rely on this feature to save the history stack. To backup your data, make sure to save
        your input (RAW) file as well as all of darktable's XMP sidecar files.</emphasis>
      </para>

      <para>
        If you don't want to distribute history stack data with your images, there are various
        tools to delete embedded XMP tags. As an example you can use the program
        <ulink url="http://www.sno.phy.queensu.ca/~phil/exiftool/"><emphasis>exiftool</emphasis></ulink>
        with:
      </para>

      <para>
<programlisting>exiftool -XMP:all=   image.jpg
</programlisting>
      </para>

    </sect4>

    <sect4>

      <title>max size</title>

      <para>
        Set the maximum width and height of the output images in pixels. Set both to a value of
        "0" to export the full image size. darktable currently can only do down-scaling, so the
        maximum output image size is defined by the source image.
      </para>

      <para>
        <emphasis>Caution: Some users accidentally enter low values, like 1 or 10,
        in these fields, causing darktable to produce tiny output files. You might think
        darktable's output is broken, but in fact it only generated what you asked
        for.</emphasis>
      </para>

    </sect4>

    <sect4>

      <title>intent</title>

      <para>
        This option lets you define the intent&nbsp;&ndash; i.e., the way darktable will deal with
        out-of-gamut colors. See <xref linkend="output_color_profile"/> for a more detailed
        description of the available options.
      </para>

    </sect4>

    <sect4>

      <title>profile</title>

      <para>
        This defines the output color profile. Select <quote>image settings</quote> if you want
        the settings in the <emphasis>output color profile</emphasis> (see
        <xref linkend="output_color_profile"/>) of the individual images to take
        precedence.
      </para>

    </sect4>

    <sect4>

      <title>style</title>

      <para>
        This option lets you choose a <emphasis>style</emphasis>: a collection of history stack items, which
        darktable concatenates with the existing history stack to generate the output image.
        These history items are only added temporarily; the original history stack does not
        change. You can use this feature to add extra processing steps and parameters that you
        want to be applied to a particular batch of exported images. For example, you may define a style that
        adds a stronger level of sharpening, and apply it when you produce scaled-down JPEG files for the
        web. Learn more about styles in <xref linkend="styles"/>, and
        <xref linkend="history"/>.
      </para>

    </sect4>

    <sect4>

      <title>export</title>

      <para>
        Pressing this button starts the export process for all selected images; the export will run
        in the background so you can continue work developing other images, if you wish. A bar at the
        bottom of the left side panel displays the export progress. Whenever a file is successfully
        exported, a notification message pops up for a few seconds. You may click on the pop-up
        to make it disappear sooner.
      </para>

    </sect4>

  </sect3>

</sect2>
