<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect2 status="final" id="geotagging">

  <title>Geotagging</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>lighttable panels</primary>
    <secondary>geo tagging</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>geo tagging</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <informaltable frame="none">
    <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
      <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
      <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
      <tbody>
        <row>
          <entry>
            Use this panel to import and apply GPX track data on a selection of images.
            Alternatively, you can manually geotag images within the <emphasis>Map</emphasis>
            view (see <xref linkend="map_chapter"/>).
          </entry>
          <entry>
            <graphic fileref="lighttable/images/panel_geotagging.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
          </entry>
        </row>
      </tbody>
    </tgroup>
  </informaltable>

  <sect3>

    <title>Usage</title>

    <para>
      A GPS receiver calculates its current position based on the information it receives from
      satellites and records them in a GPX file&nbsp;&ndash; together with the current date and
      time. The EXIF data of the images also contains a time stamp defined by the camera
      settings. darktable takes the time stamp of the image, looks-up the position in the GPX
      file at that time, and stores the coordinates (latitude/longitude) in its database and the
      image's XMP sidecar file.
    </para>

    <para>
      There may occur two problems. In contrast to GPS devices, most cameras don't record the
      accurate time. Secondly, the time stored in the EXIF data doesn't contain a time zone.
      Most people set their camera to local time, while the GPS devices store the time in UTC
      (Universal Time, Coordinated), i.e. Greenwich (London) time zone. If the time zones of
      camera and GPX file differs, than the related location will be wrong.
    </para>

    <para>
      If your image already carry the UTC time stamp you can directly apply the GPX track
      without further adjustments.
    </para>

    <para>
      Otherwise we take two steps to correlate the time of camera and GPS tracker, first the
      offset, then the time zone.
    </para>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>
                To fix the drift of the camera time setting you can either enter it manually
                into the offset input field or let darktable calculate it. All you need is a
                picture taken of a reliable time source.
              </para>

              <para>
                This can be any precise clock or even better the time displayed on your GPS
                device (normally it shows the local time, although it stores universal time).
              </para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="lighttable/images/panel_geotagging_ex1.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>
                When you have this image selected you can click on the (looking glass) button
                and darktable will present you an entry box. Just enter the time that is shown
                on the image. As a result you will get the difference between the time you
                entered and the one associated with the image in its EXIF data.
              </para>

              <para>
                Now you can select all the images you want to geotag and click the apply button
                (currently represented by a check mark). This will alter the time in darktable's
                internal database for these pictures&nbsp;&ndash; so you will also see the
                change in the image information module on the left.
              </para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="lighttable/images/panel_geotagging_ex2.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>
                Now you can apply a GPX track. Click the corresponding button and navigate to
                the GPX file. Before confirming that dialog you should select the corresponding
                time zone for your camera in the drop-down-menu.
              </para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="lighttable/images/panel_geotagging_ex3.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

    <para>
      Should you ever make a mistake with the time zone selection you can just come back and
      reapply the GPX file with a different time zone.
    </para>

  </sect3>

</sect2>
