<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
                <!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
                %darktable_dtd;
                ]>
<sect2 status="final" id="history_stack">

  <title>History stack</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>lighttable panels</primary>
    <secondary>history stack</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>history stack</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <informaltable frame="none">
    <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
      <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
      <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
      <tbody>
        <row>
          <entry>
            This panel allows manipulating the history stack (development) of images. For each
            image, development is written in a sidecar file (.xmp), and is fully
            non-destructive.
          </entry>
          <entry>
            <graphic fileref="lighttable/images/panel_historystack.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
          </entry>
        </row>
      </tbody>
    </tgroup>
  </informaltable>

  <sect3 id="history_stack_usage">

    <title>Usage</title>

    <sect4 id="history_stack_usage_copy">

      <title>copy</title>

      <para>
        Copy the history stack of the selected image. You will be prompted for which items are
        to be include. If more than one image is selected, the history stack is taken from the
        image that has been selected first.
      </para>

    </sect4>

    <sect4 id="history_stack_usage_copy_all">

      <title>copy all</title>

      <para>
        Copy the complete history stack of the first selected image; all items will be included.
        If more than one image is selected, the history stack is taken from the image that has
        been selected first.
      </para>

    </sect4>

    <sect4 id="history_stack_usage_discard">

      <title>discard</title>

      <para>
        Physically delete the history stack of the selected images. Beware, this action can not
        be undone!
      </para>

    </sect4>

    <sect4 id="history_stack_usage_paste">

      <title>paste</title>

      <para>
        Paste a previously copied history stack onto all selected images. You will be prompted
        for which items to include. This button is greyed out, until a history stack is copied
        from another image.
      </para>

    </sect4>

    <sect4 id="history_stack_usage_paste_all">

      <title>paste all</title>

      <para>
        Paste all previously copied items of a history history stack onto all selected images.
        This button is greyed out, until a history stack is copied from another image.
      </para>

    </sect4>

    <sect4 id="history_stack_usage_mode">

      <title>mode</title>

      <para>
        This setting defines how a new history stack behaves when pasted on an image that
        already has a history stack. The <quote>overwrite</quote> mode deletes the previous
        history stack, whereas <quote>append</quote> will concatenate the two history stacks.
      </para>

      <para>
        <emphasis>Note: if you use <quote>overwrite</quote> mode to paste history stack entries
        to the images that wasn't opened in darkroom previously, i.e. the automatic module
        presets weren't already applied to the image, next time you open said image in darkroom,
        the automatic presets will be applied to the image. So it may seem as if the
        <quote>overwrite</quote> mode did not actually override the existing history stack, but
        in fact it did override it, and the rest was added later.</emphasis>
      </para>

      <para>
        <emphasis>Caution: only in <quote>append</quote> mode you keep the option to later
        reconstruct your existing history stack whereas in <quote>overwrite</quote> mode your
        previous edit gets irrevocably lost. Beware, the setting of this parameter remains
        effective when you quit darktable.</emphasis>
      </para>

    </sect4>

    <sect4 id="history_stack_usage_load_xmp">

      <title>load sidecar file</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>sidecar files</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>XMP files</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>
        Opens a dialog box to select an XMP file, thus loading a history stack that you can
        paste on images.
      </para>

      <para>
        Files that were exported by darktable typically contain the full history stack if the
        file format supports embedded metadata (see <xref linkend="export_selected"/> about this
        feature and its limitations). You can load an exported image as a sidecar file in the
        same way as you do with an XMP file. This feature allows you to recover all parameter
        settings in case you have accidentally lost or overwritten the XMP file. All you need is
        the source image, typically a raw, and the exported file.
      </para>

    </sect4>

    <sect4 id="history_stack_usage_write_xmp">

      <title>write sidecar files</title>

      <para>
        Write XMP sidecar files for all selected images. The filename is generated by appending
        <quote>.xmp</quote> to the name of the underlying input file.
      </para>

      <para>
        By default darktable generates and updates sidecar files automatically whenever you work
        on an image and change the history stack. You can disable automatic sidecar file
        generation in the preferences dialog (see <xref linkend="core_options"/>). However, this
        is not recommended.
      </para>

    </sect4>

  </sect3>

</sect2>
