		<sect2 status="draft" id="history stack"><title>History stack</title>
			<informaltable frame="none"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
					<colspec colwidth="6*"/>
					<colspec colwidth="4*"/>
					<tbody>
						<row>						
							<entry>This panel allows to manipulate history stack (development) of images.
							For each image, development is written in a sidecar file (.xmp) and is fully 
              						non-destructive.
							</entry>
							<entry>
								<graphic fileref="lighttable/images/panel_historystack.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
							</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</informaltable>
				<sect4><title>copy</title>
					<para>Copy the history stack of the first selected image. You will be prompted for the items to include.
					</para>
				</sect4>
				<sect4><title>copy all</title>
					<para>Copy the complete history stack of the first selected image; all items will be included.
					</para>
				</sect4>
				<sect4><title>discard</title>
					<para>Physically delete the history stack of the selected images.
					Beware, this action can not be undone!
					</para>
				</sect4>
				<sect4><title>overwrite/append</title>
					<para>Describes how a new history stack must behave if pasted on an image having already an
					history stack. <quote>Overwrite</quote> will delete previous history stack whereas <quote>append</quote> will add the
					two history stacks.
					</para>
				</sect4>
				<sect4><title>paste</title>
					<para>Paste a previously copied history stack on all selected images. You will be prompted for the items to include.
                                              This button is greyed out until a history stack is copied from another image.
					</para>
				</sect4>
				<sect4><title>paste all</title>
					<para>Paste all previously copied items of a history history stack on all selected images. 
                                              This button is greyed out until a history stack is copied from another image.
					</para>
				</sect4>
				<sect4><title>load sidecar file</title>
					<para>Prompt a dialog box to allow you to select a .xmp file, thus loading 
					an history stack that you can paste on images.
					</para>
				</sect4>
				<sect4><title>write sidecar files</title>
					<para>Write .xmp sidecar files for all selected images. By default darktable will
                                              do this automatically for you whenever you work on an image and change history stack. You
                                              can deactivate automatic sidecar file generation in the preferences dialog, which is not
                                              recommended.
					</para>
				</sect4>

		</sect2>
