<sect2 status="draft" id="import"><title>Import</title>
		 	 <para>In this panel you import your filmrolls. You can either import a complete folder
      				by pressing <quote>import filmroll</quote> or a single image with <quote>import single image</quote>. You can also import directly from a connected camera.
		  	</para>


			<para>All your filmrolls are available in a list which can be filtered using the editbox to fast find the filmroll of interest.
				Double click on a filmroll in the list and it will open.
				You can also click the items in <emphasis>recently used collections</emphasis> (see <xref linkend="recently used collections"/>) to open the latest 
                                ones you have worked with.
			</para>

			<sect3><title>Import from filesystem</title>
				<para>A filmroll is the same as a folder in the filesystem. You can import a single image or a folder. If a folder is imported the images
	                                in that folder will show up in a filmroll whose name becomes the name of the imported folder. If single images are imported they
	                                will show up in filmroll <emphasis>single images</emphasis>.
				</para>
		
				<graphic fileref="lighttable/images/panel_import.png" scalefit="1" width="60%" align="center"></graphic>

				<para>When you click on <quote>import single image</quote> or <quote>import filmroll</quote> a file selector dialog will pop up. Navigate through your filesystem
                                      and select the item you want to import. On the lower part of the dialog you can define some further import options. 
                                </para>
                                <para>
                                      As the name implies checking <quote>import directories recursively</quote> will recurse from the currently selected directory through all 
                                      subdirectories and import all images found.
                                      It is not recommended and wasting resources to do this on an exhaustive list of images. darktable would generate thumbnails for all of them
                                      but in the end only keep the recent ones in its cache. It is better to import images part by part as separate filmrolls.
                                </para>
                                <para>Checking <quote>ignore jpeg files</quote> is a good choice if there are JPEG images in the same folder that you do not want to process with
                                      darktable; eg. if your camera stores RAW+JPEG you often will only want to work further on your RAWs and let the JPEG images alone. You can
                                      also apply some metadata already on import; see the section on <emphasis>metadata editor</emphasis> (<xref linkend="metadata editor"/>) for more details.
				</para>

				<para status="draft">Importing a folder does not mean that darktable copies your images into another folder.
					It just means that the images are visible in lighttable and thus can be developed. It means that
	     				if you delete an image/a folder after having imported them, darktable will not be able to access them anymore.
		      			Importing an image/folder in darktable is not a backup of your filesystem!
		      			Moreover darktable does not currently watch changes in filesystem. Thus if on your filesystem you add an image
					after having imported that folder in darktable, the new image will not be shown until you explicitely import it.
				</para>

			</sect3>

			<sect3><title>Import from camera</title>
				<para>When a camera is detected, it will show up in the device panel. If you hover your mouse over the camera tab label, a tooltip
					will pop up with some information about the camera such as model, firmware version and a lot more...
				</para>
				<para>Depending on the support of your camera, buttons with actions will be available such as <quote>import images</quote> and <quote>tethering</quote>.
				</para>
				<sect4><title>Import images</title>
					<para>This will bring up an import dialog, showing the images on camera that can be selected for import into a filmroll in
						darktable.
					</para>
				</sect4>
				<sect4><title>Tethering</title>
					<para>Tethering is used to integrate darktable with your camera. While you take images with your camera, they will
						automatically be imported into darktable so you can review the result of the shoot. You can also
						setup remote capture jobs, controlling number of images and time between captures along with camera settings such as exposition time, f-length and more.
					</para>
					<para>If supported by your camera, tethering will take you into capture view for tethered shoot. Read more about tethering in <xref linkend="tethering chapter"/>.
                                        </para>
				</sect4>
			</sect3>

                        <sect3 id="supported file formats"><title>Supported file formats</title>
                               <para>darktable has its main focus on managing and developing camera RAW files. Therefore a huge number of different file formats from various camera manufacturers
                                     is supported. In addition darktable can read specific <emphasis>low dynamic range</emphasis> and <emphasis>high dynamic range</emphasis> images - mainly for 
                                     data exchange between darktable and other software.</para>

                               <para>In order for darktable to consider a file for import it has to come with one of the following extensions (case independent): 3FR, ARW, BAY, BMQ, CAP, CINE, CR2, 
                                     CRW, CS1, DC2, DCR, DNG, ERF, FFF, EXR, IA, IIQ, JPEG, JPG, K25, KC2, KDC, MDC, MEF, MOS, MRW, NEF, NRW, ORF, PEF, PFM, PNG, PXN, QTK, RAW, RAW, RDC,
                                     RW1, RW2, SR2, SRF, SRW, STI, TIF, TIFF, X3F.</para>

                               <para>If darktable was compiled with JPEG2000 support, these extensions come in addition: J2C, J2K, JP2, JPC.</para>

                               <para>If darktable was compiled with GraphicsMagick support the following extensions are added to the standard ones: BMP, DCM, GIF, JNG, JPC, JP2, MIFF, MNG, 
                                     PBM, PGM, PNM, PPM.</para>

				<sect4><title>Camera RAW files</title>
					<para>darktable reads RAW files using two open source libraries: RawSpeed (developed by Klaus Post) and - failing that - with LibRaw. The number of supported 
                                              cameras and file formats is constantly increasing. It would be beyond the scope of this manual to give an exhaustive list. Most modern camera models 
                                              are supported and new ones tend to get in very quickly. darktable does not decode images from cameras with non-Bayer sensors (e.g. Fuji X-Pro1 or 
                                              Sigmas with Foveon X3 sensor).
					</para>
				</sect4>
				<sect4><title>LDR image files</title>
					<para>darktable natively reads <quote>ordinary</quote> images in JPEG, 8-bit/16-bit PNG and 8-bit/16-bit TIFF format. JPEG2000 comes in addition if the 
                                              required libraries
                                              are built into darktable at compile time. If darktable was compiled with GraphicsMagick support there are further import formats like GIF, Dicom DCM, 
                                              additional exotic TIFF formats, and some of Sun's <quote>portable xyz-map</quote> family.
					</para>
				</sect4>
				<sect4><title>HDR image files</title>
					<para>darktable reads high dynamic range images in OpenEXR, RGBE and PFM format.
					</para>
				</sect4>
                        </sect3>


		</sect2>

		

