<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect2 status="final" id="import">

  <title>Import</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>lighttable panels</primary>
    <secondary>import</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>import</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>file import</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>camera import</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <informaltable frame="none">
    <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
      <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
      <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
      <tbody>
        <row>
          <entry>
            This panel is for importing images into film rolls. You can either import a complete
            folder, by pressing <quote>folder</quote>, or a single image with
            <quote>image</quote>. You can also cause darktable to search for connected cameras
            by pressing <quote>scan for devices</quote>. If a supported camera is connected you
            can import directly from that camera or control the camera from within darktable in
            tethering mode.
          </entry>
          <entry>
            <graphic fileref="lighttable/images/panel_import_1.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
          </entry>
        </row>
      </tbody>
    </tgroup>
  </informaltable>

  <para>
    Imported images are organized as film rolls (see <xref linkend="film_rolls"/>). All film
    rolls are accessible through the <emphasis>collect images</emphasis> module (see
    <xref linkend="collect_images"/>). If you set the selection attribute to <quote>film
    roll</quote> you get a list of available film rolls, which can be filtered using the editbox
    to quickly find the one of interest. Double-click on a film roll in the list and it will
    open in the lighttable. You can also click the items in <emphasis>recently used
    collections</emphasis> (see <xref linkend="recently_used_collections"/>) to open the latest
    ones you have worked with.
  </para>

  <sect3 status="final">

    <title>Import from filesystem</title>

    <para>
      You can import either a single image, or a folder. The imported image(s) will show up in a
      film roll with the name of the filesystem folder.
    </para>

    <para>
      <graphic fileref="lighttable/images/panel_import_2.png" scalefit="1" width="60%" align="center"></graphic>
    </para>

    <para>
      Clicking on <quote>image</quote> or <quote>folder</quote> opens a file selector dialog.
      Navigate through the filesystem, and select the item to import. On the lower part of the
      dialog, are some further import options.
    </para>

    <para>
      As the name implies, checking <quote>import directories recursively</quote> will import
      images in the currently selected directory, and all subdirectories. It is not recommended,
      and wastes resources, to do this on an exhaustive list of images. darktable would generate
      thumbnails for all of them, but in the end only keep the recent ones in its cache. It is
      better to import images in smaller chunks, making logical film rolls.
    </para>

    <para>
      Checking <quote>ignore jpeg files</quote> is a good choice if there are JPEG images in the
      same folder that you do not want to process; eg. if the camera stores RAW+JPEG, you often
      only want to work on the RAWs, leaving the JPEG images alone.
    </para>

    <para>
      You can also apply some metadata during import; see <xref linkend="metadata_editor"/> for
      more details.
    </para>

    <para>
      Importing a folder does not mean that darktable copies your images into another folder. It
      just means that the images are visible in lighttable and thus can be developed. If you
      delete an image or a folder from disk after having imported them, darktable cannot access
      them anymore. Importing an image or folder in darktable is not a backup of your
      filesystem! Moreover, darktable does not watch for changes in the filesystem. Thus, if you
      add an image to a folder, after having imported that folder in darktable, the new image
      will not be shown until explicitly imported.
    </para>

  </sect3>

  <sect3 status="final">

    <title>Importing from a connected camera</title>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              When a camera is detected, it will show up in the device panel after pressing
              <quote>scan for devices</quote>. If you hover your mouse over the camera tab
              label, a tooltip will pop up with information about the camera, such as model,
              firmware version, and more. Depending on the camera's support, buttons with
              actions will be available such as <quote>import from camera</quote> and
              <quote>tethered shoot</quote>.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="lighttable/images/panel_import_3.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

    <sect4>

      <title>Import from camera</title>

      <para>
        This will bring up an import dialog, showing the images on camera that can be selected
        for import into a film roll in darktable.
      </para>

      <para>
        You define the base directory for storing imported images and the naming pattern of sub
        directories and individual images in the preferences dialog (see
        <xref linkend="session_options"/>).
      </para>

    </sect4>

    <sect4>

      <title>Tethered shoot</title>

      <para>
        Tethering is used to integrate darktable with your camera. While you take images with
        your camera, they are automatically imported into darktable, so you can review the
        result of the shoot. You can also setup remote capture jobs, controlling the number of
        images and time between captures, along with camera settings such as exposure time,
        aperture and more.
      </para>

      <para>
        If supported by your camera, tethering will take you into the capture view for tethered
        shooting. Read more about tethering in <xref linkend="tethering_chapter"/>.
      </para>

    </sect4>

  </sect3>

  <sect3 status="final" id="supported_file_formats">

    <title>Supported file formats</title>

    <para>
      darktable is focused on managing and developing camera RAW files. It supports a huge
      number of file formats from various camera manufacturers. In addition darktable can read
      specific <emphasis>low dynamic range</emphasis> and <emphasis>high dynamic
      range</emphasis> images&nbsp;&ndash; mainly for data exchange between darktable and other
      software.
    </para>

    <para>
      In order for darktable to consider a file for import, it must have one of the following
      extensions (case independent): 3FR, ARW, BAY, BMQ, CAP, CINE, CR2, CRW, CS1, DC2, DCR,
      DNG, ERF, FFF, EXR, IA, IIQ, JPEG, JPG, K25, KC2, KDC, MDC, MEF, MOS, MRW, NEF, NRW, ORF,
      PEF, PFM, PNG, PXN, QTK, RAF, RAW, RDC, RW1, RW2, SR2, SRF, SRW, STI, TIF, TIFF, X3F.
    </para>

    <para>
      If darktable was compiled with JPEG2000 support, these extensions are also recognized:
      J2C, J2K, JP2, JPC.
    </para>

    <para>
      If darktable was compiled with GraphicsMagick support, the following extensions are
      recognized in addition to the standard ones: BMP, DCM, GIF, JNG, JPC, JP2, MIFF, MNG, PBM,
      PGM, PNM, PPM.
    </para>

    <sect4>

      <title>Camera RAW files</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>import</primary>
        <secondary>RAW files</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>
        darktable reads RAW files using two open source libraries: RawSpeed (developed by Klaus
        Post) and&nbsp;&ndash; failing that&nbsp;&ndash; with LibRaw. The number of supported
        cameras and file formats is constantly increasing. It is beyond the scope of this manual
        to give an exhaustive list. Most modern camera models are supported, and new ones tend
        to get added very quickly. With the exception of Fujifilm X-Trans cameras, darktable
        does not decode images from cameras with non-Bayer sensors (e.g. Sigmas with the Foveon
        X3 sensor).
      </para>

    </sect4>

    <sect4>

      <title>LDR image files</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>import</primary>
        <secondary>LDR files</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>
        darktable natively reads <quote>ordinary</quote> images in JPEG, 8-bit/16-bit PNG and
        8-bit/16-bit TIFF format. JPEG2000 is also supported if the required libraries are built
        into darktable at compile time. Similarly, if darktable was compiled with GraphicsMagick
        support, there are further import formats, like GIF, Dicom DCM, additional exotic TIFF
        formats, and some of Sun's <quote>portable xyz-map</quote> family.
      </para>

    </sect4>

    <sect4>

      <title>HDR image files</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>import</primary>
        <secondary>HDR files</secondary>
      </indexterm>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>HDR images</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>
        darktable reads high dynamic range images in OpenEXR, RGBE and PFM format.
      </para>

    </sect4>

  </sect3>

</sect2>
