<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect2 status="final" id="selected_images">

  <title>Selected image(s)</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>lighttable panels</primary>
    <secondary>selected images</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>selected images</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <informaltable frame="none">
    <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
      <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
      <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
      <tbody>
        <row>
          <entry>
            This panel provides some actions that operate on selected images.
          </entry>
          <entry>
            <graphic fileref="lighttable/images/panel_selectedimages.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
          </entry>
        </row>
      </tbody>
    </tgroup>
  </informaltable>

  <sect3>

    <title>Usage</title>

    <sect4>

      <title>remove</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>remove images</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>
        Remove the selected images from the darktable database. Those images will not be shown
        in lighttable anymore, but remain on the filesystem. As darktable stores XMP files with
        your development parameters on disk, you can later fully reconstruct your work by just
        re-importing the images.
      </para>

      <para>
        When backing up your RAWs make sure to also save the XMP files!
      </para>

    </sect4>

    <sect4>

      <title>delete</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>delete images</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>
        Physically delete selected images from filesystem. See also preference option <quote>ask
        before erasing images from disk</quote> (<xref linkend="gui_options"/>). If this
        configuration option is not active, darktable will delete the file(s) without further
        question! This is irreversible, and will also erase your development work of these
        images.
      </para>

      <para>
        When deleting an image with duplicates, darktable keeps the original input file on disk
        until the last of the duplicates gets deleted.
      </para>

    </sect4>

    <sect4>

      <title>move</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>move images</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>
        Physically move selected images (parent file plus all accompanying XMP sidecar files) to
        another filesystem folder. darktable does not overwrite images in the target folder. If
        an input image with the given filename already exists in the target folder the source
        image is not moved but kept where it is.
      </para>

    </sect4>

    <sect4>

      <title>copy</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>copy images</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>
        Physically copy selected images (parent file plus accompanying XMP sidecar file) to
        another filesystem folder. If an image with the given name already exists in the target
        folder it does not get overwritten&nbsp;&ndash; instead a new duplicate with the given
        history stack is generated.
      </para>

    </sect4>

    <sect4>

      <title>create hdr</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>HDR images</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>
        Create a high dynamic range image from the selected images, and store it as a new source
        file in DNG format. Images need to be properly aligned, which implies that they have
        been taken on a sturdy tripod. You can also generate HDRs with programs like
        <ulink url="http://qtpfsgui.sourceforge.net/"><emphasis>Luminance
        HDR</emphasis></ulink>, and later import them into darktable for further processing (see
        <xref linkend="supported_file_formats"/>). Note that darktable cannot currently create
        HDR files from images made with non-Bayer (e.g. Fujifilm X-Trans) sensors.
      </para>

    </sect4>

    <sect4>

      <title>duplicate</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>create images</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>
        Create a virtual copy of selected images within darktable. It allows testing different
        developments for the same image, for example. Duplicate images share the same parent
        input file, but each have their own XMP sidecar file.
      </para>

    </sect4>

    <sect4>

      <title>rotation</title>

      <para>
        Perform a counter-clockwise or clockwise rotation on selected images. The third button
        resets the image rotation to the value in the EXIF data. This feature is directly linked
        to the orientation module (see <xref linkend="orientation"/>)&nbsp;&ndash; adjustments
        are converted into history stack items of that module.      
      </para>

    </sect4>

    <sect4>

      <title>copy locally</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>local copies</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>
        This action will create local copies of the selected images into the local drive. These
        copies will then be used when the original images are not accessible (see
        <xref linkend="local_copies"/>).
      </para>

    </sect4>

    <sect4>

      <title>resync local copy</title>

      <para>
        This action will synchronize the XMP sidecars of the temporary local copy and the copy
        in external storage, if needed, and will remove the local copies. Note that if a local
        copy has been modified and the external storage is not accessible the local copy won't
        be deleted (see <xref linkend="local_copies"/>).
      </para>

    </sect4>

    <sect4>

      <title>group</title>

      <indexterm>
        <primary>group images</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>
        Create a new group from selected images (see <xref linkend="image_grouping"/>).
      </para>

    </sect4>

    <sect4>

      <title>ungroup</title>

      <para>
        Remove selected images from the group (see <xref linkend="image_grouping"/>).
      </para>

    </sect4>

  </sect3>

</sect2>
