<sect2 status="draft" id="selected images"><title>Selected image(s)</title>
	<informaltable frame="none"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
			<colspec colwidth="6*"/>
			<colspec colwidth="4*"/>
			<tbody>
				<row>						
					<entry>This panel allows to perform some actions on selected images.
					</entry>
					<entry>
						<graphic fileref="lighttable/images/panel_selectedimages.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
					</entry>
				</row>
			</tbody>
		</tgroup>
	</informaltable>
		<sect4><title>remove</title>
			<para>Remove the selected images from the darktable database. Those images will not be shown
			in lighttable anymore, but remain on filesystem. As darktable stores XMP files with your development
                                      parameters on disk, you can later fully reconstruct your work by just re-importing the images. When
                                      backing up your RAWs make sure to also save the XMP files!
			</para>
		</sect4>
		<sect4><title>delete</title>
			<para>Physically delete selected images from filesystem. See also preference option 'ask before erasing images from disk'; if
                                            this option is not active, darktable will delete the file(s) without further question! This is not reversible and will
                                            also erase your development work an these images.
			</para>
		</sect4>
		<sect4><title>move</title>
			<para>Physically move selected images (parent file plus accompanying .xmp sidecar file) to another filesystem folder.
			</para>
		</sect4>
		<sect4><title>copy</title>
			<para>Physically copy selected images (parent file plus accompanying .xmp sidecar file) to another filesystem folder.
			</para>
		</sect4>
		<sect4><title>create hdr</title>
			<para>Create a high dynamic range image from the selected images and store it as a new source file in DNG format. Images
                                            need to be properly aligned.
			</para>
		</sect4>
		<sect4><title>duplicate</title>
			<para>Create a virtual copy of selected images within darktable but not physically on
			your filesystem. It allows to test and try different developments for the same image for example. Duplicate images will
                                      share the same parent input file but each have their own .xmp sidecar file.
			</para>
		</sect4>
		<sect4><title>rotation</title>
			<para>Perform a counter-clock wise/clockwise rotation on selected images. The third button
			allows to reset rotation to EXIF value.
			</para>
		</sect4>
		<sect4><title>group</title>
			<para>Create a new group from selected images.
			</para>
		</sect4>
		<sect4><title>ungroup</title>
			<para>Remove selected images from the group.
			</para>
		</sect4>
</sect2>

