<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
                <!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
                %darktable_dtd;
                ]>
<sect2 status="final" id="styles">

  <title>Styles</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>lighttable panels</primary>
    <secondary>styles</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>styles</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <informaltable frame="none">
    <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
      <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
      <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
      <tbody>
        <row>
          <entry>
            This panel provides a powerful functionality in darktable: storing a history stack
            as a style, and applying it to other images. Styles are created within this panel or
            in the darkroom (see <xref linkend="history"/>). They are managed within this
            lighttable panel, which allows you to create, apply, edit and delete styles.
          </entry>
          <entry>
            <graphic fileref="lighttable/images/panel_styles.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
          </entry>
        </row>
      </tbody>
    </tgroup>
  </informaltable>

  <sect3 id="styles_usage">

    <title>Usage</title>

    <para>
      This panel displays a list of all available styles. A search field above the list allows
      you to input a text string which is compared against the styles' names and descriptions,
      thus limiting the list to the matching ones.
    </para>

    <para>
      Double clicking on a style name applies the style to all selected images.
    </para>

    <sect4 id="styles_usage_duplicate">

      <title>create duplicate</title>

      <para>
        When applying a style to selected images, activating this box creates a duplicate of the
        image before applying the style. Disable this option if you want to try various styles
        without creating multiple duplicates; beware that in this case any existing history
        stack gets overwritten and cannot be recovered.
      </para>

    </sect4>

    <sect4 id="styles_usage_create">

      <title>create</title>

      <para>
        This creates new styles out of the history stacks of the selected images. For each image
        a style creation window pops up. You need to supply a unique name for the new style and
        you can add an additional descriptive text. You have the option to de-select those
        history stack items which you want to not be part of the newly created style.
      </para>

    </sect4>

    <sect4 id="styles_usage_edit">

      <title>edit</title>

      <para>
        Styles are collections of history stack items. After pressing <quote>edit</quote>, you
        are prompted with a dialogue to include or exclude specific items from the stack. Check
        option <quote>duplicate</quote> if you want to create a new style, instead of
        overwriting the existing one; you need to provide a new unique style name in this case.
      </para>

    </sect4>

    <sect4 id="styles_usage_delete">

      <title>delete</title>

      <para>
        This deletes the selected style, without further question.
      </para>

    </sect4>

    <sect4 id="styles_usage_import">

      <title>import</title>

      <para>
        You can import a style which has been previously saved by darktable. darktable stores
        styles as XML files with the extension <quote>.dtstyle</quote>.
      </para>

    </sect4>

    <sect4 id="styles_usage_export">

      <title>export</title>

      <para>
        This option saves a selected style to disk as a <quote>.dtstyle</quote> file. This
        allows publishing styles and sharing styles with other users.
      </para>

    </sect4>

  </sect3>

</sect2>
