<sect2 status="draft" id="styles"><title>Styles</title>
	<informaltable frame="none"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
			<colspec colwidth="6*"/>
			<colspec colwidth="4*"/>
			<tbody>
				<row>						
					<entry>This panel lets you use a powerful functionality of darktable: to store a history stack
                                        as a style and apply it to other images.
					Styles are created in darkroom mode thanks to a button placed below the history panel (see <xref linkend="history"/>).
					Then they are managed within this lighttable panel, that allows you to apply and delete a style.
					</entry>
					<entry>
						<graphic fileref="lighttable/images/panel_styles.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
					</entry>
				</row>
			</tbody>
		</tgroup>
	</informaltable>
		<sect4><title>create duplicate</title>
			<para>When applying a style on selected images, activating this box lets you create a duplicate of the image before applying the styles. 
			      De-activate this option if you want to try various styles; this will avoid that you create multiple duplicates.
			</para>
		</sect4>
		<sect4><title>edit</title>
			<para>Styles are a collection of history stack items. After pressing <quote>edit</quote> you are prompted with a dialog in which you can deselect
                                            specific items. Check option <quote>duplicate</quote> if you want to create a new style instead of overwriting the existing
                                            one; you need to give a new style name in this case.
			</para>
		</sect4>
		<sect4><title>delete</title>
			<para>This will delete the selected style without further question.
			</para>
		</sect4>
		<sect4><title>import</title>
			<para>You can import a style which has been previously saved by darktable. darktable stores its files as xml files with the extension <quote>.dtstyle</quote>.
			</para>
		</sect4>
		<sect4><title>export</title>
			<para>This option saves a selected style to disk as a .dtstyle file. This allows to share styles with other users.
			</para>
		</sect4>
</sect2>
    
