<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
                <!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
                %darktable_dtd;
                ]>
<sect2 status="final" id="tagging">

  <title>Tagging</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>lighttable panels</primary>
    <secondary>tagging</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>tags</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <informaltable frame="none">
    <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
      <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
      <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
      <tbody>
        <row>
          <entry>
            This panel is for managing tags on images. Tags are stored in both sidecar files
            (.xmp) and within the darktable database for a faster access. The panel is divided
            into two parts: the upper part contains the tag(s) currently attached to the image
            under the cursor or the selected image(s) if the mouse is outside the lighttable.
            The lower part contains a list of all available tags in the database, which can be
            filtered in the text box above.
          </entry>
          <entry>
            <graphic fileref="lighttable/images/panel_tagging.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
          </entry>
        </row>
      </tbody>
    </tgroup>
  </informaltable>

  <para>
    New tags get added to the list either by typing into the text box and pressing the
    <quote>new</quote> button, or if an automatically generated tag gets attached to an image,
    or on import of already tagged images. darktable sorts the list of tags by relevance and
    frequency of usage.
  </para>

  <para>
    Hierarchical tags are supported and can be create using the pipe symbol <quote>|</quote>.
  </para>

  <para>
    As you may notice there are automatically created tags like <quote>darktable|
    exported</quote> or <quote>darktable|styles|your style</quote>, which keep track of your
    actions and let you easily find already exported images or images with specific styles
    applied.
  </para>

  <para>
    <emphasis> Tip: ctrl-t opens a small text box at the bottom of the central view for quickly
    tagging your selected images by typing a tag phrase and hitting return. </emphasis>
  </para>

  <sect3 id="tagging_usage">

    <title>Usage</title>

    <sect4 id="tagging_usage_attach">

      <title>attach</title>

      <para>
        Attach the selected tag from the list below to all selected images.
      </para>

    </sect4>

    <sect4 id="tagging_usage_detach">

      <title>detach</title>

      <para>
        Detach the selected tag from all selected images. This also can be done by double
        clicking the specific tag.
      </para>

    </sect4>

    <sect4 id="tagging_usage_new">

      <title>new</title>

      <para>
        Create a new tag for the list.
      </para>

    </sect4>

    <sect4 id="tagging_usage_delete">

      <title>delete</title>

      <para>
        Delete a tag from the list and from all images. A warning will be displayed on how many
        images have this tag attached. Take this warning seriously as there is no way to recover
        or later find the affected images.
      </para>

    </sect4>

  </sect3>

</sect2>
