<chapter>
	<chapterinfo>
		<keywordset>
			<keyword>lighttable</keyword>
			<keyword>view</keyword>
		</keywordset>
	</chapterinfo>
	<title>Lighttable</title>
	<para>The lighttable is where you manage all your images, ratings, exporting and much more...</para>
	<screenshot>
		<screeninfo>The lighttable view</screeninfo>
		<graphic fileref="images/lighttable_view.png" scalefit="1" width="80%"></graphic>
	</screenshot>
	
	<sect1><title>Overview</title>
		<para></para>
		<sect2 status="final"><title>Lighttable</title>
			<informaltable frame="none"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
					<colspec colwidth='70%'/>
					<colspec colwidth='5cm'/>
					<tbody>
						<row>						
							<entry>In this centerview, your images are shown as thumbs; each thumb has a frame and while mouse is over
								an image, the information of rating, colorlabels and if image is altered in darkroom 
								<inlinegraphic  fileref="images/lighttable_thumb_icon_altered.png" scalefit="1" width="3mm"/> is shown.
								Also when mouse hovers over an image frame the specific image metadata is shown in the metadata panel.
							</entry>
							<entry>
								<graphic fileref="images/lighttable_thumb.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
							</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</informaltable>

			<para>In order to locate where you are in your collection, you have read-only sliders at the extreme border of the window : left/right for your vertical position in the collection, 
				top/bottom (when in zoomable lighttable mode, see below) for your zoom level.</para>
							
			<para>While mouse is over an image frame, you have additional actions accessed from keyboard to apply on image; here
				follows a table of key accelerators and assigned actions.
				<informaltable frame="none"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
					<colspec colwidth='3cm'/>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry><emphasis>0 - 5</emphasis></entry>
							<entry>set the rating of the image; if an image has 1 star and you hit the <emphasis>1</emphasis> key, the image will be unrated.
								Pressing <emphasis>del</emphasis> rejects the image.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><emphasis>F1 - F5</emphasis></entry><entry>set a color label for the image</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><emphasis>ctrl-c</emphasis></entry><entry>copy the historystack of the image</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><emphasis>ctrl-v</emphasis></entry><entry>apply the copied historystack on the image</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><emphasis>e</emphasis></entry><entry>open the image in darkroom view for developing</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><emphasis>z</emphasis></entry><entry>show a fullscreen view of the image</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup></informaltable>
			</para>
			<para>At the bottom you have an option to choose between zoomable lighttable view or filemanger view of the thumbnails.
			</para>
			<para>Using the zoomable lighttable view, scroll with your mouse wheel to zoom in and out.
			The <emphasis>hold left-click</emphasis> allows you to navigate through your collection.
			</para>
			<para>While in filemanager you can use <emphasis>ctrl-(mouse wheel)</emphasis> to change the number of thumbs displayed
			in a row. That action is a key accelerator of the counter that can be found beside the filemanager option.
			Use your mouse wheel to navigate through your collection.
			</para>
			<para>While in filemanager, by pressing <emphasis>w/s</emphasis> you can scroll (not select) up and down through your collection. 
				In zoomable lighttable <emphasis>a/d/w/s</emphasis> allow you to move left/right/up/down through your collection.
				Pressing <emphasis>ctrl-g</emphasis> goes top, <emphasis>ctrl-shift-g</emphasis> bottom.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 status="draft"><title>Filtering and sort order</title>
			<para>The filtering and sort order of images on lighttable are accessed and changed in the top bar
				where you can select among a few predefined filters and ordering like date, color labels, rating
				among others.
			</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 status="draft"><title>Panels</title>
		<sect2><title>Devices</title>
			<para>This module shows connected devices; for now only cameras are shown up there, but in future scanners too will.</para>
			<sect3><title>Cameras</title>
				<para>When a camera is detected, it will show up in the device panel; if you hover your mouse over the camera tab label a tooltip
					will pop up with some information about the camera such as model, firmware version and a lot more...
				</para>
				<para>Depending of the support of your camera, buttons with actions will be available such as import images and tethering.
				</para>
				<sect4><title>Import images</title>
					<para>This will bring up an import dialog, showing the images on camera that can be selected for import into a filmroll in
						darktable.
					</para>
				</sect4>
				<sect4><title>Tethering</title>
					<para>Tethering is used to integrate darktable with your camera. While you take images with your camera, they will
						automatically be imported into darktable so you can review the result of the shoot. You can also
						setup remote capture jobs, controlling number of images and time between captures along with camera settings such as exposition time, f-length and more.
					</para>
					<para>If supported by your camera, tethering will take you into capture view for tethered shoot. Read more about tethering in chapter 3.</para>
				</sect4>
			</sect3>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2><title>Library</title>
		 	 <para>In library, you import and remove your filmrolls. You can either import a complete folder
      				by pressing 'import filmroll' or a single image 'import single image'. 
		  	</para>
			<para>A filmroll is the same as a folder in the filesystem, except for 'single images' filmroll that contains images spread among your filesystem.
				You can import a single image or a folder; if a folder is imported, darktable will not recurse down in several folder levels but it will just import the images that resides inside
				the chosen folder into a filmroll whose name becomes the name of the imported folder.
			</para>
			<para status="draft">Importing a folder does not mean that darktable copies your images in another folder.
			It just means that the images are visible in lighttable and thus can be developed. It means that
     			if you delete an image/a folder after having imported them, darktable will not be able to access them anymore.
      			Importing an image/folder in darktable is not a backup of your filesystem!
      			Moreover darktable does not currently watch changes in filesystem. Thus if on your filesystem you add an image
			after having imported that folder in darktable, the new image will not be shown until you explicitely import it.
			</para>
			<para>All your filmrolls are available in a list which can be filtered using the editbox to fast find the filmroll of interest.
					Double click on a filmroll in the list and it will open.
				You can also click the recent filmroll items to open the latest ones you have worked with.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2><title>Metadata</title>
			<informaltable frame="none"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
					<colspec colwidth='70%'/>
					<colspec colwidth='30%'/>
					<tbody>
						<row>						
							<entry>This panel shows embedded metadata of an image, read from EXIF data stored in your pictures files.
							</entry>
							<entry>
								<graphic fileref="lighttable/images/panel_metadata.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
							</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</informaltable>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 status="draft"><title>Select</title>
			<informaltable frame="none"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
					<colspec colwidth='70%'/>
					<colspec colwidth='30%'/>
					<tbody>
						<row>						
							<entry>This panel allows to quickly select images, according to various criterion.
							</entry>
							<entry>
								<graphic fileref="lighttable/images/panel_select.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
							</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</informaltable>
				<sect4><title>select all</title>
					<para>Select all images in the current view (collection), with respect to filters.
					</para>
				</sect4>
				<sect4><title>select none</title>
					<para>Select no image.
					</para>
				</sect4>
				<sect4><title>invert selection</title>
					<para>Select all images that are not currently selected.
					</para>
				</sect4>
				<sect4><title>select film roll</title>
					<para>Select all images that are in the same filmroll as the currently selected images.
					</para>
				</sect4>
				<sect4><title>select untouched</title>
					<para>Select all images that has not been developed yet.
					</para>
				</sect4>
		</sect2>

		<sect2 status="draft"><title>Selected image(s)</title>
			<informaltable frame="none"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
					<colspec colwidth='70%'/>
					<colspec colwidth='30%'/>
					<tbody>
						<row>						
							<entry>This panel allows to perform some actions on selected images.
							</entry>
							<entry>
								<graphic fileref="lighttable/images/panel_selectedimages.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
							</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</informaltable>
				<sect4><title>remove</title>
					<para>Remove the selected images from the darktable database. Those images will not be shown
					in lighttable anymore, but remain on filesystem.
					</para>
				</sect4>
				<sect4><title>delete</title>
					<para>Physically delete selected images from filesystem.
					</para>
				</sect4>
				<sect4><title>write sidecar files</title>
					<para>Write .xmp sidecar files.
					</para>
				</sect4>
				<sect4><title>duplicate</title>
					<para>Create a virtual copy of selected images within darktable but not physically on
					your filesystem. It allows to test and try different developments for the same image for example.
					</para>
				</sect4>
				<sect4><title>rotation</title>
					<para>Perform a counter-clock wise/clockwise rotation on selected images. The third button
					allows to reset rotation to EXIF value.
					</para>
				</sect4>
		</sect2>

		<sect2 status="draft"><title>History stack</title>
			<informaltable frame="none"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
					<colspec colwidth='70%'/>
					<colspec colwidth='30%'/>
					<tbody>
						<row>						
							<entry>This panel allows to manipulate development.
							For each image, development is written in a sidecar file (.xmp) and is fully 
              						non-destructive.
							</entry>
							<entry>
								<graphic fileref="lighttable/images/panel_historystack.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
							</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</informaltable>
				<sect4><title>copy</title>
					<para>Copy the history stack (development) of the first selected image.
					</para>
				</sect4>
				<sect4><title>discard</title>
					<para>Physically delete the history stack (development) of the selected images.
					Beware, this action can not be undone!
					</para>
				</sect4>
				<sect4><title>overwrite/append</title>
					<para>Describes how a new history stack must behave if pasted on an image having already an
					history stack. 'Overwrite' will delete previous history stack whereas 'append' will add the
					two history stacks.
					</para>
				</sect4>
				<sect4><title>paste</title>
					<para>Paste a previously copied history stack on another image.
					</para>
				</sect4>
				<sect4><title>load sidecar file</title>
					<para>Prompt a dialog box to allow you to select a .xmp file, thus loading 
					an history stack that you will past (thanks to 'past' button) on images.
					</para>
				</sect4>
		</sect2>

		<sect2 status="draft"><title>Styles</title>
			<informaltable frame="none"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
					<colspec colwidth='70%'/>
					<colspec colwidth='30%'/>
					<tbody>
						<row>						
							<entry>This panel lets you use a powerful functionality of darktable: to store and apply a history stack.
							Styles are created in darkroom mode thanks to a button placed below the history stack.
							Then they are managed thanks to this panel, that allows you to apply and delete a style.
							</entry>
							<entry>
								<graphic fileref="lighttable/images/panel_styles.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
							</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</informaltable>
				<sect4><title>create duplicate</title>
					<para>When applying a style on selected images, activate this box lets you create a duplicate before applying the styles 
					and thus avoiding you to create multiple duplicates before trying various styles on it.
					</para>
				</sect4>
		</sect2>
    
		<sect2 status="draft"><title>Tagging</title>
			<informaltable frame="none"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
					<colspec colwidth='70%'/>
					<colspec colwidth='30%'/>
					<tbody>
						<row>						
							<entry>This panel allows to manage tags for your images.
							Those tags are currently stored in sidecar files (.xmp) and within the 
							darktable database for a faster access.
							The panel is divided into two parts: the upper part contains the tag(s) currently set for the image 
							either under mouse (if mouse is over an image) or selected (if mouse is outside the lighttable).
							The lower part contains all tags available; those can be filter thanks to the upper text box.
							</entry>
							<entry>
								<graphic fileref="lighttable/images/panel_tagging.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
							</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</informaltable>
				<sect4><title>attach</title>
					<para>Attach the selected tag(s) from the list below to all selected images.
					</para>
				</sect4>
				<sect4><title>detach</title>
					<para>Detach selected tag(s) from the list above from all selected images.
					</para>
				</sect4>
				<sect4><title>new</title>
					<para>Create a new tag for the list.
					</para>
				</sect4>
				<sect4><title>delete</title>
					<para>Delete a tag from the list.
					</para>
				</sect4>
		</sect2>	
    
		<sect2 status="draft"><title>Collect images</title>
			<informaltable frame="none"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
					<colspec colwidth='70%'/>
					<colspec colwidth='30%'/>
					<tbody>
						<row>						
							<entry>Thanks to this panel, you can manage your collection (current view)
							by filtering image thanks to various criterion.
							The left combo box lets you choose from different filters, such a 'filmroll', 'historystack',
							'date', 'camera' and much more. The table belows lists all available data for the selected filter.
							You can then select the data of your choice by double-clicking.						
							</entry>
							<entry>
								<graphic fileref="lighttable/images/panel_collectimages.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
							</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</informaltable>
		</sect2>	
    	
		<sect2 status="draft"><title>Export selected</title>
			<informaltable frame="none"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
					<colspec colwidth='70%'/>
					<colspec colwidth='30%'/>
					<tbody>
						<row>						
							<entry>Each workflow has to end by this panel: the exportation of your developed images.
							Currently, you can export either to a file on your disk, or to various on-line storages.
							<emphasis>TIP</emphasis>: you can use <emphasis>ctrl-alt-e</emphasis> to export.
              </entry>
							<entry>
								<graphic fileref="lighttable/images/panel_exportselected.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
							</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</informaltable>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
		
</chapter>
