<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<chapter status="final" id="lighttable_chapter">

  <chapterinfo>
    <keywordset>
      <keyword>lighttable</keyword>
      <keyword>view</keyword>
    </keywordset>
  </chapterinfo>

  <title>Lighttable</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>lighttable view</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    The lighttable is where you manage all your images, ratings, export and much more.
  </para>

  <para>
    <screenshot>

      <screeninfo>The lighttable view</screeninfo>

      <graphic fileref="images/lighttable_view.png" scalefit="1" width="80%"></graphic>

    </screenshot>
  </para>

  <sect1 status="final" id="lighttable_overview">

    <title>Overview</title>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              In the central view, your images are shown as thumbnails, surrounded by a frame.
              When the mouse is over an image, its rating and color labels are shown in the
              frame, along with an indicator
              <inlinegraphic  fileref="images/lighttable_thumb_icon_altered.png" scalefit="1" width="3mm"/>
              of whether the image has already been altered in darkroom. Also, when the mouse
              hovers over an image frame, image information (EXIF data, metadata) is shown in
              the <link linkend="image_information"><emphasis>image
              information</emphasis></link> panel at the bottom left.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="images/lighttable_thumb.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

    <para>
      While the mouse is over an image frame, there are a number of actions you can perform.
      Here is a table of keyboard shortcuts and assigned actions.
      <informaltable frame="none" width="80%">
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
          <colspec colwidth='1*'/>
          <colspec colwidth='3*'/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis>0&nbsp;&ndash; 5</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                set the rating of the image; if an image has 1 star and you hit the
                <emphasis>1</emphasis> key, the image will be unrated. Pressing
                <emphasis>r</emphasis> rejects the image.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis>F1&nbsp;&ndash; F5</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                set a color label
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis>ctrl-c</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                copy the history stack
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis>ctrl-v</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                paste the copied history stack
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis>d</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                open in darkroom view for developing
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis>z</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                fully zoom into the image while the key is pressed
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis>ctrl-z</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                fully zoom into the image and show areas in focus
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </para>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>overlay</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>
      The overlay button
      <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_general_overlay;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center" />
      located in the upper panel activates the permanent display of star ratings and
      image-changed indicator
      <inlinegraphic fileref="images/lighttable_thumb_icon_altered.png" scalefit="1" width="3mm"/>
      on all thumbnails. By default these overlays are only visible on the thumbnail under the
      mouse cursor. An overlay button is also available in the other views where it affects the
      filmstrip accordingly (see <xref linkend="filmstrip_overview"/> and
      <xref linkend="darkroom_filmstrip"/>).
    </para>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>color management</primary>
      <secondary>display profile</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>monitor profile</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>display profile</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>
      Pressing the
      <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_lighttable_displayprofile;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center" />
      button on the right side of the bottom panel lets you define the color profile of your
      monitor. You can either set this to <quote>system display profile</quote> (default) and
      let darktable enquire the system's display profile, or alternatively set it to one of the
      ICC profiles located in <filename>$DARKTABLE/share/darktable/color/out</filename> and
      <filename>$HOME/.config/darktable/color/out</filename>. <filename>$DARKTABLE</filename> is
      used here to represent your chosen darktable installation directory and
      <filename>$HOME</filename> your home directory. For more details on color management see
      <xref linkend="color_management"/>.
    </para>

    <para>
      In the center of the bottom panel you have an option to choose between zoomable lighttable
      view or filemanager view of the thumbnails. In zoomable lighttable view, scroll with your
      mouse wheel to zoom in and out. Moving the mouse while <emphasis>pressing the left mouse
      button</emphasis> allows you to navigate through your collection. In filemanager view, you
      can can change the number of images in each row, using the slider next to the filemanager
      option, or by using <emphasis>ctrl-(mouse wheel)</emphasis>. Use your mouse wheel to
      navigate through your collection.
    </para>

    <para>
      In both modes you can navigate left/right/up/down through your collection using
      &larr;/&rarr;/&uarr;/&darr;. Pressing <emphasis>g</emphasis> in filemanager mode goes to
      the top, <emphasis>shift-g</emphasis> to the bottom, <emphasis>PageUp</emphasis> brings
      you one page up and <emphasis>PageDown</emphasis> one page down.
    </para>

    <para>
      You can select the image under the pointer by <emphasis>left-clicking</emphasis> on its
      thumbnail or by pressing <emphasis>return</emphasis>. A range of images is selected by
      <emphasis>clicking</emphasis> on the first one and then
      <emphasis>shift-clicking</emphasis> on the last one. Images are added or removed from your
      selection by <emphasis>ctrl-clicking</emphasis> on their thumbnails or pressing
      <emphasis>space</emphasis>.
    </para>

    <para>
      To locate where you are in a collection, there are indicators at the extreme borders of
      the window: left/right for your position when you are in filemanager mode, left/right and
      top/bottom for your vertical and your horizontal position, respectively, when you are in
      the zoomable lighttable view.
    </para>

    <para>
      While holding down the <emphasis>z</emphasis> key a fully zoomed preview of the image
      under the mouse cursor is displayed. You can use this feature for a quick inspection of
      image quality while rating and selecting images.
    </para>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>focus detection</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>
      Holding down the <emphasis>ctlr-z</emphasis> key fully zooms into the image and
      additionally activates an analysis for sharp regions, detecting those parts of the image
      that are in focus. Areas of high sharpness are indicated by a red border&nbsp;&ndash; the
      higher the color intensity the better the sharpness. In case that no area of
      <emphasis>high</emphasis> sharpness is detected darktable indicates areas of
      <emphasis>moderate</emphasis> sharpness with a blue border. For this tool to work the
      input image needs to hold an embedded JPEG thumbnail which is the case for most raw files.
    </para>

    <para>
      Sometimes pressing <emphasis>z</emphasis> or <emphasis>ctrl-z</emphasis> may not reveal an
      immediate effect&nbsp;&ndash; in that case please click into the center area and press the
      corresponding key again.
    </para>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              Fully zoomed-in image view while holding down the <emphasis>ctrl-z</emphasis> key
              with indication of the sharp areas in focus. Sharpness detection is based on an
              embedded JPEG thumbnail of the original raw file independent of any processing
              steps within darktable.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="images/lighttable_focus_detection.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

  </sect1>

<!-- Lighttable concepts -->

  <xi:include href="concepts/concepts.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>

<!-- Panels -->

  <xi:include href="panels/panels.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>

</chapter>
