<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<chapter id="lighttable chapter">
	<chapterinfo>
		<keywordset>
			<keyword>lighttable</keyword>
			<keyword>view</keyword>
		</keywordset>
	</chapterinfo>
	<title>Lighttable</title>
	<para>The lighttable is where you manage all your images, ratings, export and much more&nbsp;&hellip;</para>
	<screenshot>
		<screeninfo>The lighttable view</screeninfo>
		<graphic fileref="images/lighttable_view.png" scalefit="1" width="80%"></graphic>
	</screenshot>

	<sect1><title>Overview</title>
		<para></para>
		<sect2 status="final" id="lighttable"><title>Lighttable</title>
			<informaltable frame="none"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
					<colspec colwidth="6*"/>
					<colspec colwidth="4*"/>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry>In the central view, your images are shown as thumbs; each thumb has a frame and while the mouse is over
								an image, the information of rating, color labels and if image has already been altered in darkroom
								<inlinegraphic  fileref="images/lighttable_thumb_icon_altered.png" scalefit="1" width="3mm"/> is shown.
								Also when the mouse hovers over an image frame the specific image metadata is shown in the metadata panel.
							</entry>
							<entry>
								<graphic fileref="images/lighttable_thumb.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
							</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</informaltable>

			<para>In order to locate where you are in your collection, you have read-only sliders at the extreme border of the window: left/right for your vertical position in the collection,
				top/bottom (when in zoomable lighttable mode, see below) for your zoom level.</para>

			<para>While the mouse is over an image frame, you can access additional actions from your keyboard to apply on the image; here
				follows a table of key accelerators and assigned actions.
				<informaltable frame="none" width="80%"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
					<colspec colwidth='1*'/>
					<colspec colwidth='3*'/>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry><emphasis>0&nbsp;&ndash; 5</emphasis></entry>
							<entry>set the rating of the image; if an image has 1 star and you hit the <emphasis>1</emphasis> key, the image will be unrated.
								Pressing <emphasis>r</emphasis> rejects the image.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><emphasis>F1&nbsp;&ndash; F5</emphasis></entry><entry>set a color label for the image</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><emphasis>ctrl-c</emphasis></entry><entry>copy the history stack of the image</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><emphasis>ctrl-v</emphasis></entry><entry>paste the copied history stack on the image</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><emphasis>d</emphasis></entry><entry>open the image in darkroom view for developing</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><emphasis>z</emphasis></entry><entry>show a fullscreen view of the image</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup></informaltable>
			</para>
			<para>At the bottom you have an option to choose between zoomable lighttable view or filemanger view of the thumbnails.
			</para>
			<para>Using the zoomable lighttable view, scroll with your mouse wheel to zoom in and out.
			Moving the mouse while <emphasis>pressing the left mouse button</emphasis> allows you to navigate through your collection.
			</para>
			<para>While in filemanager you can use <emphasis>ctrl-(mouse wheel)</emphasis> to change the number of thumbs displayed
			in a row. That action is a key accelerator of the counter that can be found beside the filemanager option.
			Use your mouse wheel to navigate through your collection.
			</para>
			<para>While in filemanager mode, by pressing &uarr;/&darr; you can scroll (not select) up and down through your collection.
				In zoomable lighttable &larr;/&rarr;/&uarr;/&darr; allow you to move left/right/up/down through your collection.
				Pressing <emphasis>g</emphasis> goes to the top, <emphasis>shift-g</emphasis> to the bottom.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 status="draft" id="filtering and sort order"><title>Filtering and sort order</title>
			<para>The filtering and sort order of images on lighttable are accessed and changed in the top bar
				where you can select among a few predefined filters and ordering like date, color labels or rating.
			</para>
		</sect2>

		<sect2 status="draft" id="image grouping"><title>Image grouping</title>
			<para>Image grouping helps you to improve structure and clearness of your image collection as 
                              displayed in lighttable view.
			</para>
                        <para>You can combine images into a group by selecting them and then 
                              clicking button "group" in panel <emphasis>selected image(s)</emphasis> (<xref linkend="selected images"/>) or by typing 
                              <emphasis>ctrl-g</emphasis>. Likewise you can remove images from a group by clicking
                              button "ungroup" or typing <emphasis>shift-ctrl-g</emphasis>. Images that you generate by 
                              duplicating an existing one, will automatically constitute an image group. If you import 
                              images from file system or camera, images which have the same base name but different 
                              extensions will form a group (eg. IMG_1234.CR2 and IMG_1234.JPG). Images which are members
                              of a group are labelled with a symbol "G" in their thumbnails. 
                        </para>
                        <para>With button <inlinegraphic  fileref="images/lighttable_icon_group.png" scalefit="1" width="2%"/> 
                              in the top panel of lightroom mode you toggle grouping mode on and off.
                        </para>
                        <para>If grouping is off, each image is displayed as an individual thumb.
                        </para>
                        <para>If grouping is on, images of a group are by default collapsed, which means they are 
                              represented by one thumbnail.
                              The image you see is called the group head. If you press symbol "G" in the thumbnail of a group, only this
                              group gets expanded; if another group was expanded at that time it gets collapsed. To collapse an expanded 
                              group again, just click on symbol "G" of its group head.
                        </para>
                        <para>You can define which image constitutes the group head. When you are in expanded view of a group, 
                              just go to the thumbnail of the desired image and click on the symbol "G" within that thumb.
                        </para>
                        <para>If you are in collapsed view and enter darkroom mode with an image group (eg. by 
                              double-clicking on the thumbnail) only the group head will be opened.
                        </para>
                        <para>his is a convenient way to protect an existing history stack against unintentional changes. Suppose you have 
                              just finalized an image; all you need to do now is generate a duplicate and make sure grouping is
                              switched on and the group is collapsed. Whenever you open the image group again in darkroom and do 
                              further changes, only the group head will be altered. The underlying duplicate remains unchanged. 
                              Please note that duplicating images only means that a second copy of your history stack and a second small 
                              XMP file is generated. There still is only one RAW file, so you don't waste a lot of disk space.
                        </para>
		</sect2>


	</sect1>

	<!-- Panels -->
	<xi:include href="panels/panels.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
</chapter>

