<chapter>
	<chapterinfo>
		<keywordset>
			<keyword>lighttable</keyword>
			<keyword>view</keyword>
		</keywordset>
	</chapterinfo>
	<title>Lighttable</title>
	<para>The lighttable is where you manage all your images, ratings, exporting and much more...</para>
	<screenshot>
		<screeninfo>The lighttable view</screeninfo>
		<graphic fileref="images/lighttable_view.png" scalefit="1" width="80%"></graphic>
	</screenshot>
	
	<sect1><title>Overview</title>
		<para></para>
		<sect2><title>Ligthtable</title>
			<informaltable frame="none"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
					<colspec colwidth='100%'/>
					<colspec colwidth='5cm'/>
					<tbody>
						<row>						
							<entry>In this centerview your images are shown as thumbs, each thumb has a frame and while mouse is over
								an image, information such as rating and if image are altered in darkroom <inlinegraphic  fileref="images/lighttable_thumb_icon_altered.png" scalefit="1" width="3mm"/> is viewed.
								Also when mouse hovers over an imageframe the specific image metadata is shown in the metadata panel.
							</entry>
							<entry>
								<graphic fileref="images/lighttable_thumb.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
							</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</informaltable>
							
			<para>While mouse is over and imageframe you have additional actions accessed from keyboard to apply on image here
				follows an table of key accelerators and assigned actions.
				<informaltable frame="none"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
					<colspec colwidth='3cm'/>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry><emphasis>1 - 4</emphasis></entry>
							<entry>set the rating of the image, if an image has 1 star and you hit the 1 key the image will be unrated
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><emphasis>F1 - F3</emphasis></entry><entry>sets a color label for the image</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><emphasis>ctrl-c</emphasis></entry><entry>copy the historystack of the image</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><emphasis>ctrl-v</emphasis></entry><entry>apply the copied historystack on the image</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><emphasis>e</emphasis></entry><entry>opens the image in darkroom view for developing</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><emphasis>z</emphasis></entry><entry>shows a fullscreen view of the image</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup></informaltable>
			</para>
			<para>At the bottom you have an option to choose a zoomable lighttable view or a filemanger view of the thumbnails.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2><title>Filtering and sort order</title>
			<para>The filtering and sortorder of images on lighttable are accessed and changed in the top bar
				where you can select among a few predefined filters and orderering like date, color labels, rating
				among others.
			</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1><title>Panels</title>
		<sect2><title>Devices</title>
			<para>This plugin show's connected devices, for now this is only cameras but in future scanners would show up here.</para>
			<sect3><title>Cameras</title>
				<para>When a camera is detected it will show up in the device pane, if you hover your mouse over the camera tablabel a tooltip
					will show with some information about the camera such as model,firmware version and alot more..,
				</para>
				<para>Depending of the support for your camera, buttons with actions will be available such as import images and tethering.
				</para>
				<sect4><title>Import images</title>
					<para>This will bring up an import dialog, showing the images on camera that can be selected for import into a filmroll in
						Darktable.
					</para>
				</sect4>
				<sect4><title>Tethering</title>
					<para>Tethering is used to integrate Darktable with your camera, and while you take images on the camera it will
						automatic be imported into darktable and you can review the result of the shoot, you can also infront of computer
						setup remote capture jobs for timelapsed captures and change settings such as shuttertime, f-length and more.
					</para>
					<para>Tethering will take you into capture view with the specific camera for tethered shoot read more about tethering in chapter 3.</para>
				</sect4>
			</sect3>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2><title>Library</title>
			<para>A filmroll is the same as a folder in the filesystem, except for single images filmroll that can contain images spread around on in your filessystem.
				You can import a singel image or a folder, if a folder is imported Darktable will not recurse down in several folderlevels, just import the images that resides at
				choosen folder into a filmroll which name become the name of the folder imported.
			</para>
			<para>All your filmrolls are available in a list which can be filtered using the editbox to fast find the filmroll of interest.
					Double click on a filmroll in the list and it will be opened and viewed.
				You can also click the recent filmroll items to open the latest ones you have worked with.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2><title>Metadata</title>
			<informaltable frame="none"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
					<colspec colwidth='100%'/>
					<colspec colwidth='30%'/>
					<tbody>
						<row>						
							<entry>This panel shows embeded metadata of an image.
							</entry>
							<entry>
								<graphic fileref="lighttable/images/panel_metadata.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
							</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</informaltable>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
		
</chapter>