<chapter>
	<chapterinfo>
		<keywordset>
			<keyword>lighttable</keyword>
			<keyword>view</keyword>
		</keywordset>
	</chapterinfo>
	<title>Lighttable</title>
	<para>The lighttable is where you manage all your images, ratings, exporting and much more...</para>
	<screenshot>
		<screeninfo>The lighttable view</screeninfo>
		<graphic fileref="images/lighttable_view.png" scalefit="1" width="80%"></graphic>
	</screenshot>
	
	<sect1><title>Overview</title>
		<para></para>
		<sect2 status="final"><title>Lighttable</title>
			<informaltable frame="none"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
					<colspec colwidth='70%'/>
					<colspec colwidth='5cm'/>
					<tbody>
						<row>						
							<entry>In this centerview, your images are shown as thumbs; each thumb has a frame and while mouse is over
								an image, the information of rating, colorlabels and if image is altered in darkroom 
								<inlinegraphic  fileref="images/lighttable_thumb_icon_altered.png" scalefit="1" width="3mm"/> is shown.
								Also when mouse hovers over an image frame the specific image metadata is shown in the metadata panel.
							</entry>
							<entry>
								<graphic fileref="images/lighttable_thumb.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
							</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</informaltable>

			<para>In order to locate where you are in your collection, you have read-only sliders at the extreme border of the window : left/right for your vertical position in the collection, 
				top/bottom (when in zoomable lighttable mode, see below) for your zoom level.</para>
							
			<para>While mouse is over an image frame, you have additional actions accessed from keyboard to apply on image; here
				follows a table of key accelerators and assigned actions.
				<informaltable frame="none"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
					<colspec colwidth='3cm'/>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry><emphasis>0 - 5</emphasis></entry>
							<entry>set the rating of the image; if an image has 1 star and you hit the <emphasis>1</emphasis> key, the image will be unrated.
								Pressing <emphasis>del</emphasis> rejects the image.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><emphasis>F1 - F5</emphasis></entry><entry>set a color label for the image</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><emphasis>ctrl-c</emphasis></entry><entry>copy the historystack of the image</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><emphasis>ctrl-v</emphasis></entry><entry>apply the copied historystack on the image</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><emphasis>d</emphasis></entry><entry>open the image in darkroom view for developing</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><emphasis>z</emphasis></entry><entry>show a fullscreen view of the image</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup></informaltable>
			</para>
			<para>At the bottom you have an option to choose between zoomable lighttable view or filemanger view of the thumbnails.
			</para>
			<para>Using the zoomable lighttable view, scroll with your mouse wheel to zoom in and out.
			The <emphasis>hold left-click</emphasis> allows you to navigate through your collection.
			</para>
			<para>While in filemanager you can use <emphasis>ctrl-(mouse wheel)</emphasis> to change the number of thumbs displayed
			in a row. That action is a key accelerator of the counter that can be found beside the filemanager option.
			Use your mouse wheel to navigate through your collection.
			</para>
			<para>While in filemanager, by pressing <emphasis>w/s</emphasis> you can scroll (not select) up and down through your collection. 
				In zoomable lighttable <emphasis>a/d/w/s</emphasis> allow you to move left/right/up/down through your collection.
				Pressing <emphasis>ctrl-g</emphasis> goes top, <emphasis>ctrl-shift-g</emphasis> bottom.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 status="draft"><title>Filtering and sort order</title>
			<para>The filtering and sort order of images on lighttable are accessed and changed in the top bar
				where you can select among a few predefined filters and ordering like date, color labels, rating
				among others.
			</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	
	<!-- Panels -->
	<xi:include href="panels/panels.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
</chapter>
