<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>

	<sect2 status="draft" id="blending operators"><title>Blending operators</title>
		<para>Blending operators are a functionality that works on the incoming image information and 
				the output of the current module. Not all modules support blending because it would not work
				and break the use of the module.
		</para>
		<para>Modules that do support blending, inherit additional controls at the bottom of module's user interface.
		</para>

                <sect3><title>Usage</title>	

		<sect4><title>blend mode</title>
			<para>There are several blend modes implemented and more might be added in future. For now all the common ones are there and
			      you will recognize a few of them from other imaging software. A good introduction on many
        	              common blend modes is given in <ulink url="http://docs.gimp.org/2.8/en/gimp-concepts-layer-modes.html">
                              <emphasis>The Gimp Manual (Chapter 8.2, <quote>Layer Modes</quote>)</emphasis></ulink>. Therefore we only discuss a few blend modes here in more detail.
			</para>

			<sect5><title>off</title>
				<para>If set to <quote>off</quote> no blending will be done and blending related controls are hidden.
			        </para>			
			</sect5>


			<sect5><title>normal</title>
				<para>This will probably be the most used blend mode. It does just mix input and output and will be used
				      to control the amount of a module's effect.
			        </para>			
			</sect5>

		        <sect5><title>inverse</title>
				<para>This blend mode acts similar to blend mode <quote>normal</quote>, only that the role of input and output of the
        	                      current module are reversed. Can be used together with conditional blending (<xref linkend="conditional blending"/>) to
        	                      get the effect of an inversed blend mask.
        	                </para>			
			</sect5>

			<sect5><title>unbounded</title>
				<para>This blend mode acts similar to blend mode <quote>normal</quote>, only that input and output data are not
        	                      clamped to a certain min/max value range. This already tells you that all other blend modes
        	                      clamp their input and output. In some cases (e.g. highly color saturated extreme highlights) it is 
        	                      important to  let unbound values travel through the pixelpipe in order to properly deal with them at 
        	                      the right place (e.g. in module <link linkend="output color profile"><emphasis>output color profile</emphasis></link>).
	                        </para>			
	                </sect5>

			<sect5><title>lightness</title>
				<para>This blend mode mixes lightness from input and output image. Color data (chroma and hue) are
	                              taken unaltered from the input image.
	                        </para>			
	                </sect5>


			<sect5><title>chroma</title>
				<para>This blend mode mixes chroma (saturation) from input and output image. Lightness and hue are
	                              taken unaltered from the input image.
	                        </para>			
	                </sect5>

			<sect5><title>hue</title>
				<para>This blend mode mixes hue (color tint) from input and output image. Lightness and chroma are
	                              taken unaltered from the input image. For modules which drastically modify hue (e.g. generating
	                              complementary colors) this blend mode can result in strong color noise.
	                        </para>			
	                </sect5>

			<sect5><title>color</title>
				<para>This blend mode mixes color (chroma and hue) from input and output image. Lightness is
	                              taken unaltered from the input image. For modules which drastically modify hue (e.g. generating
	                              complementary colors) this blend mode can result in strong color noise.
	                        </para>			
	                </sect5>

			<sect5><title>coloradjustment</title>
				<para>Some modules act predominantly on the tonal values of an image but involve some adjustment of color saturation
                                      as well, e.g. module <link linkend="levels"><emphasis>levels</emphasis></link> and <link linkend="tonecurve">
                                      <emphasis>tonecurve</emphasis></link>. This blend mode takes the 
                                      lightness only from output data and mixes colors from input and output. This way you can control the module's automatic 
                                      color adjustment.
	                        </para>			
	                </sect5>


		</sect4> 
		
		<sect4><title>opacity</title>
			<para>This slider controls the amount of blending. A value of 100% gives the module's full effect into the
        	              pixelpipe; a value of 0% means no effect of this module. With blend mode <quote>normal</quote> and a proper selection
        	              of opacity you can therefore control the strength of a module's effect.
			</para>

	        </sect4>

	        <sect4><title>blend</title>
        	        <para>Most modules offer additional control on blending by a user-defined blend mask. In order to activate these
        	              controls you need to switch from <quote>blend uniformily</quote> to <quote>blend only, if..</quote>. More details on conditional blending
        	              are given in a separate chapter (<xref linkend="conditional blending"/>).
        	        </para>
	        </sect4>
                </sect3>

		<sect3><title>Examples</title>
			<sect4 status="draft"><title>Texturing an image</title>
				<para>The watermark module supports SVG files with embedded images and thanks to it we can easily texture an 
						image using the watermark module in conjunction with a blending operator.
				</para>
			</sect4>
		
			<sect4 status="draft"><title>Gritty details</title>
				<informaltable frame="none"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
						<colspec colwidth="6*"/>
						<colspec colwidth="4*"/>
						<tbody>
							<row>						
								<entry>When blending operators were introduced into darktable, a new module named <emphasis>highpass</emphasis>
                                                                       (see <xref linkend="highpass"/>) was added. It produces a highpass filter of the image to be implicitly 
                                                                        used with blending. It allows to produce a gritty detailed image and
										is a widely used workflow with other imaging softwares.				
								</entry>
								<entry>
									<graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/blendop_highpass.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
								</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</informaltable>
			
				<para>
					<informaltable frame="none"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
							<colspec colwidth="4*"/>
							<colspec colwidth="6*"/>
							<tbody>
								<row>
									<entry>
										<graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/blendop_highpass_ex1_1.png" scalefit="1" width="90%" align="center" />
									</entry>						
									<entry>
										<para>This is the original image, pretty heavy processed: first <link linkend="monochrome">
                                                                                      <emphasis>monochrome</emphasis></link>, then some blue <link linkend="splittoning">
                                                                                      <emphasis>splittoning</emphasis></link> but as you see
											it lacks pop in details and is a bit out of focus...
										</para>
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										<graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/blendop_highpass_ex1_2.png" scalefit="1" width="90%" align="center" />
									</entry>						
									<entry>
										<para>Here we applied the highpass filter with the values shown in the images above of the module userinterface; 
											you can now see that the details are very boosted and we got a really gritty detailed image.
										</para>
									</entry>
								</row>
							</tbody>
						</tgroup>
					</informaltable>
				</para>
			</sect4>
		
		</sect3>
     </sect2>

