<sect2 status="final"><title>Crop and rotate</title>
	<sect3 status="final"><title>Overview</title>
		<informaltable frame="none"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
				<colspec colwidth='100%'/>
				<colspec colwidth='30%'/>
				<tbody>
					<row>						
						<entry>This tool is used for crop, rotate and prespective correction of you image, it does
							also include many helpful guidelines that assists you using the tool.
						</entry>
						<entry>
							<graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/croprotate.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
						</entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</informaltable>
	
		<para>First off select what aspect ratio you want and size the crop bounds by dragging border and corner handles,
			use ctrl-x to swap potrait/landscape rotation of the crop rectangle.
			You can move around the crop rectangle by holding down left mouse button and move around...
			When you finished and want to execute the crop, hit enter key or double click in crop rectangle.
		</para>
	</sect3>

	<sect3 status="draft"><title>Usage</title>
		<para>...</para>
		<sect4><title>Flip image</title>
			<para>Use these toggle buttons to flip image horizontal and veritcal</para>
		</sect4>
		<sect4><title>Angle</title>
			<para>This is the angle for rotation, used for correctiion for example a non straight horizontal horizon, use 
				your left mouse button holding it down and drawing a line along the horizon and the image are rotated to match
				the angle of your line.
			</para>
		</sect4>
		<sect4><title>Perspective</title>
			<para>This tool is used for correcting any perspective distortions in you image, like example when you shoot 
				an high building from ground and aiming upwards with camera with short focal length...
			</para>
			<para>You can also choose which direction (righ and up) the correction should be applied on.
			</para>
		</sect4>
		<sect4><title>Aspect</title>
			<para>Here you can change what aspect ratio you want to have on the result, constraining the ability to drag an crop 
				rectangle out of the aspect ratio of your choice..
			</para>
			<para>
				<informaltable frame="none"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
					<colspec colwidth='3cm'/>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry><emphasis>free</emphasis></entry><entry>free forming the rectangle without any ratio restrictions</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><emphasis>image</emphasis></entry><entry>this option constrains the ratio to be equal to image ratio</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup></informaltable>
			</para>
		</sect4>

	</sect3>
</sect2>