<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>

	<sect2 status="final" id="multiple instances"><title>Multiple instances</title>
		    <para>Many of darktable's modules can have multiple instances. Each instance behaves like an individual module, taking its input from the module
                          below in pixelpipe and delivering its output to the module above.</para>

		    <sect3><title>Typical use cases</title>
                           <para>There are many occasions where it makes sense to have an operation act more than once in pixelpipe. Here are a few use cases.</para>

                           <para>Most of our modules are highly versatile and depending on parameters can deliver quite varying effects.
                                 Take for example module <emphasis>fill light</emphasis> (<xref linkend="fill light"/>) which allows a local modification of lightness based on pixel values. You might
                                 want to do two lightness corrections in your image at the same time - one for dark tones and another one for lighter tones.</para>

                           <para>You might want to apply a denoising module like <emphasis>denoise (profile)</emphasis> (<xref linkend="denoise profiled"/>) with two different parameter sets. 
                                 One to do luma denoising and another set of parameters to do chroma denoising. You could do so by generating two instances and let the first one only act on luma 
                                 by activating blend mode <quote>lightness</quote> and the second one only act on chroma by activating blend mode <quote>color</quote> 
                                 (see <xref linkend="blending operators"/>).</para>

                           <para>In an even more elaborate case you could have a module act on different parts of your image. As an example you might want to apply a certain gradation
                                 curve with module <emphasis>tonecurve</emphasis> (<xref linkend="tonecurve"/>) to your complete image and have a second curve being applied specifically to skin tones. 
                                 All the controls offered by <emphasis>conditional blending</emphasis> (<xref linkend="conditional blending"/>) are at your hand to select those parts of an image where
                                 each of the module instances is applied.</para>

                           <para>Please be aware that of course each instance also adds to the workload of your pixelpipe. Generating too many instances - especially of the more demanding
                                 modules - will certainly cause some noticable slow-down.</para>
                    </sect3>

		    <sect3><title>Managing instances</title>
                           <para>When clicking on icon <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_module_instances;"  scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center"/> a drop-down menu will appear.</para>

                           <para>If you select <quote>new</quote> a new module instance will be generated below the already existing ones. Each new instance gets its own complete set of GUI controls.
                                 To keep instances apart each new instance receives an ascending number, which is appended to the module name.</para>

                           <para>To delete an instance just press <quote>delete</quote> from the drop-down menu.</para>

                           <para>darktable applies all modules in a defined order in its pixelpipe; instances of a module are treated like individual modules. However, you can decide
                                 on the relative order in which the different instances of a module are applied. Selecting <quote>move up</quote> or <quote>move down</quote> will shift the position of the
                                 instance among its peers.</para>
                    </sect3>
        </sect2>
