<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect1 status="final" id="modules"><title>Modules</title>
	<para>Each correction, enhancement or effect is implemented as a module.
        </para>
        <para>
               This section includes documentation of each module and its specific parameters.
               A module consists of an expander bar <inlinegraphic fileref="&img_module_expander;" scalefit="1" width="30%" align="center"/>  
               where the <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_module_enable;" scalefit="1" width="2%"  align="center"/> icon is used to turn the module
               on or off. Then there is the name of the module; press this to expand the module to see the user interface with all parameters.
               Icon <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_module_presets;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center" /> is the preset icon to access the available presets stored for the module or to create new ones. 
               The <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_module_reset;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center"/> icon is used to reset the module parameters to their default values. Many of darktable's
               modules can have multiple instances; click on icon <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_module_instances;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center"/> to generate new instances and control
               existing ones.
	</para>
	<sect2 status="draft"><title>Interacting with modules</title>
           <para>The most frequently used control elements are sliders, comboboxes and curves.
           </para>
	   <para>For each slider, you can interact in four different ways, depending on the level of control you need.
	   </para>
	    <orderedlist>
			   <listitem>
			     <para>Triangular marker</para>
			     <para>You left-click with your mouse on the triangular marker and move it around.
			     </para>
			   </listitem>
			   <listitem>
			     <para>Mouse wheel</para>
			     <para>Hover a slider with your mouse, then use your mouse wheel to adjust by step the value.
			     </para>
			   </listitem>
   			   <listitem>
			     <para>Right-click</para>
                             <para>Your mouse being over a slider, right click gives you a multi-functional pop-up below the slider for fine control
                                   with your mouse and for entering numerical values with your keyboard. A bent line that extends from the
                                   triangular marker moves as you move your mouse. The closer your mouse pointer is to the triangular marker the
                                   coarser the control; the further away from the triangular marker the finer is your control. Left-click with your
                                   mouse to accept the current value and go back to normal control. You can also directly type in the desired value
                                   with your keyboard; there is no cursor, you just start typing.
                             </para>
	                     <informaltable frame="none"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
				<colspec colwidth="6*"/>
				<colspec colwidth="4*"/>
				<tbody>
					<row>						
						<entry>darktable's innovative way of value input: coarse and fine value adjustments in one single control element.
						</entry>
						<entry>
							<graphic fileref="darkroom/images/darkroom_bauhaus.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
						</entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
                                </tgroup>
                           </informaltable>
			   </listitem>		
   			   <listitem>
			     <para>Double-click on parameter label</para>
			     <para>In some modules, you can double-click on a parameter label to reset its value to default.
			     </para>
			   </listitem>		   
			</orderedlist>
          <para>Clicking on a combobox will open a list of available options. Click on the item you want to select
          </para>

          <para>Some modules are controlled by adjusting curves. More detail is given later in this chapter when the respective
                modules are explained.
          </para>
	</sect2>
	

	<!-- Blending sections -->
	<xi:include href="blend_operators.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>

	<!-- Conditional blending  -->
	<xi:include href="blend_conditional.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>

	<!-- Presets -->
	<xi:include href="presets.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>

	<!-- Multiple instances -->
	<xi:include href="instances.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
	
	<!-- Modules groups -->
	<xi:include href="basic/group_basic.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
	<xi:include href="tone/group_tone.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
	<xi:include href="color/group_color.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
	<xi:include href="correction/group_correction.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
	<xi:include href="effect/group_effect.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>

</sect1>
