<sect1 status="final"><title>Modules</title>
	<para>Each correction, enhancement or effect is implemented as modules, and this section includes documentation
			of each module and its specific parameters.
			A module consists of an expander bar <inlinegraphic fileref="&img_module_expander;"/>  where the <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_module_enable;"/> icon  is used to turn then module
			on or off, then there are a title of the module press this to expand the module to see the parameters user interface.
			<inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_module_presets;"/> icon is the preset icon to access the available presets stored for the module or to create new ones. The <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_module_reset;"/>  icon is 				used to reset the module parameters to their default values.
	</para>
	<sect2 status="draft"><title>Interacting with modules</title>
	   <para>For each slider, you can interact in three different ways, depending on the level of control you need.
	   </para>
	    <orderedlist>
			   <listitem>
			     <para>Arrows</para>
			     <para> You can use the arrows around the slider to control precisely the increase/decrease of the value.
			     </para>
			   </listitem>
			   <listitem>
			     <para>Mouse wheel</para>
			     <para>Hover a slider with your mouse, then use your mouse wheel to adjust by step the value.
			     </para>
			   </listitem>
   			   <listitem>
			     <para>Right-click</para>
			     <para>Your mouse being over a slider, right-click gives you numerical access the slider values.
			     Note that the numerical value needed to be entered is sometimes different from the one displayed.
			     For example, the percentage repartition is displayed as X/Y (eg 70/30) but numerical value to be entered
			     is -1 for 0/100, 0 for 50/50 and 1 for 0/100.
			     </para>
			   </listitem>			   
			</orderedlist>
	</sect2>
	<sect2 status="final"><title>Presets</title>
		<para>
			Presets are stored configurations for the module parameters both internal and user-defined is available
				through clicking the <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_module_presets;"/> icon and a list of available presets are shown for your choice, the activated preset is in bold text.
		</para>
		<para>
			The preset system does also support automatic preset selection based on image data such as focal length, iso,  
				camera model and much more fields.
		</para>
		<sect3><title>Creating a new preset</title>
			<para>
				Configure the specific module of choice as you like then you click the <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_module_presets;"/> icon and select
				store new preset menu choice.
				Following dialog will be shown to configure the preset:
			</para>
			<graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/new_preset.png" scalefit="1" width="60%" align="center" />
			<para>
				The first two fields are used for setting a name and a description of the preset.
			</para>
			<para>
				In the example i have also checked the auto apply option which brings up the image selection fields where you can define a filter
				that is used to decide if the preset should be applied the image or not.
				The example dialog above does set up following rules, if lens name matches and aperture is >= 8 and focal length is in range 24 - 35mm the preset will be automatically applied, 
				it will also only show in the preset list if the image does match this rule.
			</para>
			<para>
				The data used is the EXIF information so if you want a preset to be applied to all images from a specific camera, then leave all fields at default values,
				lookup model string in metadata panel and enter it into the model field.
			</para>
			
		</sect3>
	</sect2>

	&darkroom_module_rawimport;	
	&darkroom_module_denoise;
	&darkroom_module_exposure;
	&darkroom_module_whitebalance;
	&darkroom_module_highlightreconstruction;
	&darkroom_module_basecurve;
	&darkroom_module_unbreakinputprofile;
	&darkroom_module_inputcolorprofile;
	&darkroom_module_colortransfer;
	&darkroom_module_equalizer;
	&darkroom_module_monochrome;
	&darkroom_module_tonecurve;
	&darkroom_module_colorzones;
	&darkroom_module_colorcorrection;
	&darkroom_module_outputcolorprofile;
	&darkroom_module_lenscorrection;
	&darkroom_module_clipping;
	&darkroom_module_channelmixer;
	&darkroom_module_localcontrast;
	&darkroom_module_velvia;
	&darkroom_module_sharpen;
	&darkroom_module_grain;
	&darkroom_module_vignetting;
	&darkroom_module_splittoning;
</sect1>
