<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>

	<sect2 status="final" id="module presets"><title>Module Presets</title>
		    <para>
			    Presets are stored configurations for the module parameters. Some modules come with internal, pre-defined presets. You can also define your own ones. Both internal 
                            and user-defined presets are accessible through clicking the <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_module_presets;"  scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center"/> icon. A list of available 
                            presets is shown for your choice; the activated preset is in bold text.
		    </para>
		    <para>
			    The preset system does also support automatic preset selection based on image data such as focal length, iso,  
				    camera model and many more fields.
                    </para>
		    <sect3><title>Creating a new preset</title>
			    <para>Configure the specific module of choice as you like then you click the <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_module_presets;"  scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center"/> 
                            icon and select store new preset menu choice. Following dialog will be shown to configure the preset:
			    </para>
			    <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/new_preset.png" scalefit="1" width="60%" align="center" />
			    <para>
				    The first two fields are used for setting a name and a description of the preset.
			    </para>
			    <para>
			    In the example above we have also checked the auto apply option. This brings up additional selection fields where you can define a filter, that is used to decide if the 
                            preset should be applied the image or not. The example dialog above does set up following rules, if lens name matches and aperture is greater or equal to 8 and focal length 
                            is in range of 24 to 35mm the preset will be automatically applied. Also the second checkbox is clicked, so that this preset will only show in the preset list, if the 
                            image does matches this rule.
			    </para>
			    <para>
 			    darktable finds these data in the EXIF information of your images. If you want a preset to be applied to all images from a specific camera, then leave all fields at default 
                            values, only lookup model string in metadata panel and enter it into the model field.
			    </para>

	            </sect3>
                    <sect3><title>Managing Presets</title>
                           <para>Pre-defined and user-defined presets can be viewed and managed from within the presets menu (<xref linkend="presets"/>) in preferences dialog 
                                 (see <xref linkend="preferences chapter"/>).
                           </para>
                    </sect3>
        </sect2>
