<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>

	<sect2 status="final"><title>Presets</title>
		    <para>
			    Presets are stored configurations for the module parameters both internal and user-defined is available	through clicking the <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_module_presets;"  scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center"/> icon and a list of available presets are shown for your choice, the activated preset is in bold text.
		    </para>
		    <para>
			    The preset system does also support automatic preset selection based on image data such as focal length, iso,  
				    camera model and much more fields.
    </para>
		    <sect3><title>Creating a new preset</title>
			    <para>
				    Configure the specific module of choice as you like then you click the <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_module_presets;"  scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center"/> icon and select store new preset menu choice. Following dialog will be shown to configure the preset:
			    </para>
			    <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/new_preset.png" scalefit="1" width="60%" align="center" />
			    <para>
				    The first two fields are used for setting a name and a description of the preset.
			    </para>
			    <para>
			    In the example i have also checked the auto apply option which brings up the image selection fields where you can define a filter that is used to decide if the preset should be applied the image or not.	The example dialog above does set up following rules, if lens name matches and aperture is >= 8 and focal length is in range 24 - 35mm the preset will be automatically applied, it will also only show in the preset list if the image does match this rule.
			    </para>
			    <para>
				    The data used is the EXIF information so if you want a preset to be applied to all images from a specific camera, then leave all fields at default values,	lookup model string in metadata panel and enter it into the model field.
			    </para>
            </sect3>
        </sect2>
