<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
                <!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
                %darktable_dtd;
                ]>
<sect1 id="tethering_examples">

  <title>Examples</title>

  <para>
    This section contains examples of typical usages of tethering.
  </para>

  <sect2 id="tethering_examples_studio">

    <title>Studio setup with screening</title>

    <para>
      This is a pretty common use case. You have your studio and subject set up, the camera is
      connected to your computer and tethering view is active in darktable. You work at the
      camera and take images. Whenever you want, you can screen the image directly on your
      computer monitor instead of using the camera LCD for validation.
    </para>

    <para>
      This workflow is efficient and effective, since you can immediately review your captures
      instead of waiting until after the shoot when everyone is gone. If you're shooting a model
      this is a pretty nice way to pre-view the captures with the client instead of fumbling
      around with your camera.
    </para>

    <para>
      Working in the tethered mode can save you time and aggravation. Set a session name, shoot
      your images and they will save in the correct film roll for the session for easy on-site
      review.
    </para>

  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="tethering_examples_timelapse">

    <title>Capturing a timelapse</title>

    <para>
      A timelapse is a video clip composed of images taken in a time sequence. A typical example
      is to take a timelapse of cityscapes where you capture clouds and traffic etc.
    </para>

    <para>
      To setup a timelapse capture, create a new session as described previously. Now decide if
      you want to shoot in manual or auto mode. Only use auto in situations were the ambient
      light will change significantly during the time of the shoot, eg. shooting a timelapse
      over 24 hours might give you easier control of light in that kind of captured sequence.
    </para>

    <para>
      The camera settings panel is where you define delay and sequence. Sequence will give you
      the opportunity to choose how many images you want to capture and delay will set the time
      in seconds between captures.
    </para>

    <para>
      To start the capture click the capture button in the same panel and watch the filmstrip
      fill up with images. The latest captured image is always displayed in center view.
    </para>

  </sect2>

</sect1>
