<sect1 id="tethering examples"><title>Examples</title>
	<para>This section contains examples of typical usages of tethering.
	</para>

	<sect2>
	  <title>Studio setup with screening</title>

	  <para>This is a pretty common use case. You have your studio and subject rigged, camera
	  is connected to your computer and tethering view is active in darktable. You work behind the camera and take images.
          Whenever you want you can screen the image directly on your computer monitor instead of using the camera LCD for validation.
          </para>

	  <para>This workflow is effective, as you don't need to take 20 captures and then later - while out 
	  of the rigg - review them and hope that you got <emphasis>the one</emphasis>. Just do it up front. If you're shooting a model
	  this is a pretty nice way to pre-show the captures to the client instead of fumbling around with your camera.
          </para>

	  <para>This workflow is kind of out-of-the-box when entering tethering view. You just need to set a session 
	  name - preferable subject name of the shoot - then just start to take images. They will fall into 
	  the right filmroll for the session for easy review on-site.</para>

	</sect2>

	<sect2>
	  <title>Capturing a timelapse</title>

	  <para>A timelapse is a video clip composed out of images taken on a interval of X seconds. A typical example
	  is to take a timelapse of cityscapes where you capture clouds and traffic etc.</para>

	  <para>To setup a timelapse capture you should as always create a new session as descibed before. Then you need
	  to decide if you want to shoot in manual or auto mode. Only go for auto in situations were the ambient light will
	  strongly change over time of the timelapse. Eg. shooting a timelapse over 24 hours might give you easier control of lights
	  in that kind of captured sequence.</para>

	  <para>Head over to the camera settings panel where you define delay and sequence. Sequence will give you the oppertunity to 
          choose how many images you want to capture and delay will set the time in seconds between capture.</para>

	  <para>To start the capture just hit the capture button in the same panel and watch the filmstrip fill up with 
	  images. The latest captured image is always previewed in center view.</para>
	</sect2>

</sect1>
