<sect1><title>Examples</title>
	<para>This section contains examples of usages and how to perform them in using tethering.
	</para>

	<sect2>
	  <title>Studio setup with screening</title>

	  <para>This is a pretty common use case, you have your studio and subject rigged an while camera
	  is connected and tethering view is active in darktable, you work behind the camera and when ever
	  you want you can screen the image taken directly on your monitor instead of using the camera LCD 
	  for validating an image to be captured as yuo wanted.</para>

	  <para>This workflow is effective, due to you dont need to take 20 captures and then later while out 
	  of the rigg review them and hope that you got "the one", just do it up front. If you shooting a model
	  this is pretty nice way to preshow the captures to the client instead of fumbling around with your camera
	  buttons and viewing them on camera screen.</para>

	  <para>This workflow is kind of out-of-the-box when entering tethering view, you just need to set a session 
	  name, preferable subject name of the shoot for example, the just start take images and they will fall into 
	  right filmroll for the session for easily review on-site.</para>

	</sect2>

	<sect2>
	  <title>Capturing a timelapse</title>

	  <para>A timelapse is a video clip composed out of images taken on a interval of X seconds, a typical examples
	  is to take a timelapse of cityscapes wher you capture clouds and traffic etc.</para>

	  <para>To setup a timelapse capture you should as always create a new session as descibed before, then you need
	  to decide if you want to shoot in manual or auto mode, only go for auto in situations were the ambient light will
	  change over time of the timelapse eg. shooting a timelapse over 24 hours might give you easier control of  lights
	  in that kind of captured sequence.</para>

	  <para>Then head over to the camera settings panel, where you enables the buttons, delay and sequence, and you are 
	  now ready to setup a timelapse captuer, sequence will give you the oppertunity to choose how many images you want 
	  to capture and delay will set the time in seconds between capture.</para>

	  <para>To start the capture just hit the capture button in the same panel and watch the filmstrip fill up with 
	  images and were the latest captured on is previewd in center view.</para>
	</sect2>

</sect1>
