<sect1><title>Overview</title>
	<para>Original splittoning method creates a two color linear toning effect where the 
			shadows and highlights are represented by two different colors.
			In the example image below you can see an original black and white image and one where
			a splittoning effect are applied with blue in shadows and yellow-ish color in highlights.
	</para>
	<para>Darktable splittoning plugin has more parameters that impacts on the default above behavior, 
			we have balance which offsets the 50% gray level in image and compression that does compress
			toning in the shadows and highlights which  leaves a gap which are untouched by the effect.
			Read more and see examples of these additional parameters to splittoning module in Parameters section.
	</para>
	<para>The splittoning module does not convert image to black and white and works extensible nice on color images,
			soo if you want to do traditional splittoning, use the monochrome module to make the image black and white
			before playing around with splittoning effect.
	</para>
</sect1>

<sect1><title>Parameters</title>
	<para>...</para>
	<sect2><title>Shadows and Hilights color</title>
		<para>These controls are used to set the color of the splittoning effect, you select the desire color and 
				saturation for both shadows and highlights, you can also click the color preview box too bring up a
				common color picker dialog.</para>
	</sect2>
	<sect2><title>Balance</title>
		<para>The balance is presented as an ratio bar and default value is 50/50 which means that 50% of lightness 
		range in image are used for shadows toning and the other 50% for highlights toning.
		</para>
	</sect2>
	<sect2><title>Compression</title>
		<para>Compression is a percentage of total lightness range that not is affected by color toning, default value is
			set to 33% which not is the default behaviour of a original splittoning which would be 0% compression.
			The choice of 33% as default is to invite you exprimenting with these parameters and how it extends the original 
			splittoning method...
		</para>
	</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1><title>Examples</title>
	<para>Here follows some examples</para>
	<sect2>
		<title>Sepia</title>
		<para>Sepia is an darkbrown dye and was early used for contrast color instead of black in old black and white images,
				we can use the splittoning plugin to simulate this effect.
				What we need is a black and white image, and thint the shadows in brownscales instead of grayscales,
				enable the monochrome module to make image black and white, then enable splittoning module.
				Choose a brown color for shadows with about 50% saturation and enshure that highlights saturation slider is 0%,
				then change compression to 0% to disable it.
				Now drag the balance slider to the right for expanding the range of the shadows and the toning that suits your image.
		</para>
	</sect2>
	<sect2>
		<title>Crossdevelop</title>
		<para>Cross developing is an effect archived by using wrong chemicals with wrong film type when developing the film, 
				the results is and higher contrast image with bluish shadows and a green/yellow tone of the image.
				So we need an image, let it be in color, then go into tonecurve and apply "medium contrast" from presets.
				Enable splittoning and choose an blue color for shadows and boost saturation up to 80%, choose a geenishyellow 
				color for highlights and put saturation around 60%.
				Set compression to 0% to allow toning over all lightnesslevels.
				Depending on image, motives, exposure tune with balance, to empahse the effect apply vignetting with a small
				size and long fall off value to fade out to the borders..
		</para>
	</sect2>
</sect1>
