<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect2 status="final" id="image_grouping">

  <title>Image grouping</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>group images</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    Grouping images helps improve structure and clarity of your image collection when displayed
    in lighttable view.
  </para>

  <para>
    You can combine images into a group by selecting them, and clicking the <quote>group</quote>
    button in the <emphasis>selected image(s)</emphasis> panel
    (<xref linkend="selected_images"/>), or by typing <emphasis>ctrl-g</emphasis>. Likewise, you
    can remove selected images from a group by clicking the <quote>ungroup</quote> button, or
    typing <emphasis>shift-ctrl-g</emphasis>. Images generated by duplicating an existing one,
    are automatically grouped. If you import images from the file system or camera, images with
    the same base name, but different extensions (eg. IMG_1234.CR2 and IMG_1234.JPG), will form
    a group.
  </para>

  <para>
    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>
                Images which are members of a group are labeled with a <quote>G</quote> symbol
                in their thumbnails.
              </para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="lighttable/concepts/images/grouping_1.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
  </para>

  <para>
    The group button
    <inlinegraphic  fileref="images/lighttable_icon_group.png" scalefit="1" width="2%"/>
    in the top panel of the lightroom view toggles grouping mode on and off. If grouping is off,
    each image is displayed as an individual thumb. If grouping is on, images of a group are
    collapsed, which means they are represented by a single thumbnail. This thumbnail you see is
    called the group head. If you press the <quote>G</quote> symbol in the group's thumbnail,
    only this group gets expanded; if you then expand another group, the first group collapses.
    To collapse an expanded group again, just click on the <quote>G</quote> symbol of its group
    head.
  </para>

  <para>
    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>
                An expanded group in the filemanager mode of lighttable view is indicated by an
                orange frame which appears as soon as your mouse pointer hovers over one of the
                images.
              </para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="lighttable/concepts/images/grouping_2.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
  </para>

  <para>
    You can define which image constitutes the group head, while in an expanded view of a group,
    clicking on the <quote>G</quote> symbol of the desired image. That symbol is shown only if 
    grouping mode is enabled, so to change the group head, you need to first enable group mode,
    then expand the group you want to change and then click the <quote>G</quote> symbol on the
    desired image.
  </para>

  <para>
    If you collapse an image group and then enter darkroom mode (e.g., by double-clicking on the
    thumbnail), the <emphasis>group head</emphasis> will be opened for developing.
  </para>

  <para>
    Image groups are a convenient way to protect an existing history stack against unintentional
    changes. Suppose you have just finalized an image and want to protect its current version:
    all you need to do is select the image, click <quote>duplicate</quote> in the
    <emphasis>selected images</emphasis> panel, and make sure that grouping is switched on and
    that the group is collapsed. Now, whenever you open the image group again in darkroom, only
    the group head will be altered. The underlying duplicate remains unchanged.
  </para>

  <para>
    Please note that <quote>duplicating images</quote> here only generates a copy of your
    history stack, stored in another small XMP file. There is still only one raw file, so you
    don't waste a lot of disk space.
  </para>

</sect2>
