<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect2 status="final" id="local_copies">

  <title>Local copies</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>local copies</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    Many users have huge image collections which they store on extra hard drives in their
    desktop computer, or on an external storage medium like a RAID NAS, etc. So it is a common
    use case to develop some images while travelling using a notebook and then later synchronize
    them to the original storage medium. But copying images manually from the main storage to
    the notebook and back is cumbersome and prone to errors.
  </para>

  <para>
    The <quote>local copies</quote> feature of darktable has been designed to directly support
    those use cases. You can create local copies of selected pictures on your computer's local
    drive. This local copy is always used when present, giving access to the picture if the
    external storage is no longer connected, and having the advantage of being faster than a
    slow external drive. At a later point, when connected again with your main storage medium,
    you can synchronize the XMP sidecar files, deleting the local copy of your input image.
    These operations can be found in the <emphasis>selected images</emphasis> panel (see
    <xref linkend="selected_images"/>).
  </para>

  <para>
    For safety reasons, if local copies exist and the external storage is available, the local
    XMP sidecars are automatically synchronized at start up.
  </para>

  <para>
    The local copies are stored into the $HOME/.cache/darktable directory and named
    <quote>img-&lt;SIGNATURE&gt;.&lt;EXT&gt;</quote>, where:
    <informaltable frame="none" width="80%">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth='1*'/>
        <colspec colwidth='3*'/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <emphasis>SIGNATURE</emphasis>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              is a hash signature (MD5) of the full pathname
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <emphasis>EXT</emphasis>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              is the original filename extension
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
  </para>

  <para>
    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>
                A local copy is identified in the lighttable view with a white marker on the
                right of the thumbnail. In addition all local copies carry the
                <emphasis>darktable|local-copy</emphasis> tag for selecting them easily.
              </para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="lighttable/concepts/images/local_copies_1.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
  </para>

</sect2>
