<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect2 status="final" id="local_copies">

  <title>Local copies</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>local copies</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    Quite commonly users have huge image collections which they store on an external storage
    medium like a RAID NAS. It is a frequent wish to be able to develop some of the images while
    travelling using a notebook and later synchronize them to the external storage. Copying
    images manually from external storage to the notebook and back is prone to errors and
    cumbersome.
  </para>

  <para>
    The local copies feature of darktable has been designed to directly support those use cases.
    With the help of this feature you can create local copies of selected pictures on the local
    drive of your computer. This copy is then used when the original image is not accessible. At
    a later point, when connected again with your external storage medium, you can synchronize
    back the XMP sidecar files, deleting the local copy of your input image. These operations
    can be found in the <quote>selected images</quote> panel (see
    <xref linkend="selected_images"/>).
  </para>

  <para>
    For safety reasons, if local copies exist and the external storage is available the local
    XMP sidecars are automatically synchronized at start up.
  </para>

  <para>
    The local copies are stored into the $HOME/.cache/darktable directory and named
    <quote>img-&lt;N&gt;-&lt;SIGNATURE&gt;.&lt;EXT&gt;</quote>, where:
    <informaltable frame="none" width="80%">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth='1*'/>
        <colspec colwidth='3*'/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <emphasis>N</emphasis>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              is the image number in darktable
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <emphasis>SIGNATURE</emphasis>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              is a hash signature (SHA-1) of the full pathname
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <emphasis>EXT</emphasis>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              is the original filename extension
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
  </para>

  <para>
    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>
                A local copy is identified in the lighttable view with a white marker on the
                right of the thumbnail. In addition all local copies carry the
                <emphasis>darktable|local-copy</emphasis> tag for selecting them easily.
              </para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="lighttable/concepts/images/local_copies_1.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
  </para>

</sect2>
