<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect2 status="final" id="star_ratings_and_color_labels">

  <title>Star ratings and color labels</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>star ratings</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>color labels</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    Star ratings and color labels help you to sort and rank images according to your own
    criteria. An image's star rating and its color labels are displayed in the thumbnail.
  </para>

  <para>
    You can give a rating from zero to five stars to an image. The quality criteria which lead
    to a rating are fully up to you. Whenever you import images, each image receives a default
    rating which you can define in GUI options (see <xref linkend="gui_options"/>). You can
    later revise the rating at any time. You can also mark an image as <quote>rejected</quote>
    by pressing the
    <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_lighttable_reject;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center"/>
    icon or typing the <emphasis>r</emphasis> key. This will remove all stars. You can reverse 
    the rejection by applying a new star rating.
  </para>

  <para>
    There are several ways to change a rating. While hovering the cursor over an image
    thumbnail, you can press a number key <emphasis>0&nbsp;&ndash; 5</emphasis> for the number
    of stars, or type <emphasis>r</emphasis> to <quote>reject</quote> an image; this is probably
    the fastest way when rating your images on first inspection of a film roll.
  </para>

  <para>
    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              You can also directly click on the stars displayed in the thumbnails; click the
              <emphasis>x</emphasis> to reject, click the fifth star to get a rating of five
              stars, etc. Clicking either the <emphasis>x</emphasis> or the first star for a
              second time resets the image rating to unranked, or zero stars.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="lighttable/concepts/images/star_rating_thumbs.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
  </para>

  <para>
    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              To rate one or more images at once, select those images (see
              <xref linkend="select"/>) and then press the key for your rating, or click the
              desired star rating in <emphasis>the bottom panel</emphasis> of the lighttable
              view.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="lighttable/concepts/images/star_rating_panel.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
  </para>

  <para>
    Color labels are another way to sort images, and can be used as an alternative to star
    ratings or work alongside star ratings. Each image can carry any combination of one or more
    color labels in red, yellow, green, blue, and purple.
  </para>

  <para>
    You can set the color labels for a single image by hovering your cursor over the thumbnail
    and pressing the function keys <emphasis>F1&nbsp;&ndash; F5</emphasis>, which correspond
    with the labels in the order given above.
  </para>

  <para>
    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              To toggle the color labels of one or more images, select the desired images (see
              <xref linkend="select"/>) and then press the corresponding color button in the
              bottom panel. To remove all labels from the selected images, press the grey
              button.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="lighttable/concepts/images/color_labels_panel.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
  </para>

</sect2>
