<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect2 status="final" id="sidecar_files">

  <title>Sidecar files</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>sidecar files</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>XMP files</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>save button</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    darktable is a non-destructive image editor. This implies that darktable opens images
    read-only. Any newly added metadata, tags and parameters of image operations (history stack)
    are stored in a separate file, a so called sidecar or XMP file. When you import an image
    into darktable for the first time an XMP file with default settings is generated
    automatically.
  </para>

  <para>
    For a given source image, multiple edits, called duplicates, can co-exist - sharing the same
    input (RAW) data but each having their individual set of metadata, tags and history stack.
    Each duplicate is represented by a separate XMP sidecar file with a filename constructed in
    the form <quote>&lt;basename&gt;<emphasis>_nn</emphasis>.&lt;extension&gt;.xmp</quote>,
    where <emphasis>nn</emphasis> represents the (minimum two digit) version number of that
    edit. The initial edit - the duplicate with version number zero - is represented by sidecar
    file <quote>&lt;basename&gt;.&lt;extension&gt;.xmp</quote>. The version number of a
    duplicate is displayed in the image information panel in each of darktable's views (see for
    example <xref linkend="image_information"/>).
  </para>

  <para>
    Sidecar files get synchronized automatically by darktable without the need to press a
    <quote>save</quote> button. When backing up your data, make sure you also keep the XMP
    files, as these are needed to fully reconstruct your work in case of a disaster.
  </para>

  <para>
    In addition to the sidecar files darktable keeps all image related data in its database for
    fast access. An image can only be viewed and edited from within darktable if its data is
    loaded in that database. This automatically happens when you first import an image or at any
    later time by re-importing it (see <xref linkend="import"/>). In the latter case the
    database gets updated with data that darktable finds in the sidecar files belonging to that
    image.
  </para>

</sect2>
