<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect2 status="final" id="sidecar_files">

  <title>Sidecar files</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>sidecar files</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>XMP files</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>save button</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    darktable is a non-destructive image editor. This means that darktable opens images
    read-only. Any newly added metadata, tags, and parameters of image operations (the
    <quote>history stack</quote>) are stored in separate <emphasis>.xmp</emphasis> files,
    so-called sidecars, allowing you to store information about the images as well as the full
    editing history without touching the original raw files. When you import an image into
    darktable for the first time, an XMP file with default settings is generated automatically.
  </para>

  <para>
    For a given source image, multiple editing versions, called duplicates, can co-exist,
    sharing the same input (raw) data but each having their own metadata, tags and history
    stack. Each duplicate is represented by a separate XMP sidecar file with a filename
    constructed in the form
    <quote>&lt;basename&gt;<emphasis>_nn</emphasis>.&lt;extension&gt;.xmp</quote>, where
    <emphasis>nn</emphasis> represents the (minimum two-digit) version number of that edit.
    Information for the initial edit&nbsp;&ndash; the <quote>duplicate</quote> with version
    number zero &nbsp;&ndash; is stored in the sidecar file
    <quote>&lt;basename&gt;.&lt;extension&gt;.xmp</quote>. The version number of a duplicate is
    displayed in the image information panel in each of darktable's views (see an example in
    <xref linkend="image_information"/>).
  </para>

  <para>
    Sidecar files automatically synchronize with your work without the need to press a
    <quote>save</quote> button. When backing up your data, make sure you also keep the XMP
    files, as these are needed to fully reconstruct your work in case of a disaster.
  </para>

  <para>
    In addition to the sidecar files, darktable keeps all image-related data in its database for
    fast access. An image can only be viewed and edited from within darktable if its data is
    loaded in that database. This automatically happens when you first import an image or at any
    later time by re-importing it (see <xref linkend="import"/>). In the latter case the
    database gets updated with data that darktable finds in the sidecar files belonging to that
    image.
  </para>

  <para>
    Once an image has been imported into darktable the database entries take precedence over the
    XMP file. Subsequent changes to the XMP file by any other software are not visible to
    darktable&nbsp;&ndash; any changes get overwritten the next time darktable synchronizes the
    file. This behavior can be changed in the preferences dialog (see
    <xref linkend="core_options"/>). On request darktable looks for updated XMP files at startup
    and offers a choice whether to update the database or overwrite the XMP file.
  </para>

</sect2>
