<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect2 status="draft" id="thumbnails">

  <title>Thumbnails</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>thumbnails</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    Each image of the current collection is represented by a thumbnail in the lighttable view.
    darktable keeps a cache of thumbnails on disk, a so called mipmap cache, the size of which
    can be adjusted in the core preferences dialog (see <xref linkend="core_options"/>).
  </para>

  <sect3 status="draft" id="thumbnail_creation">

    <title>Thumbnail creation</title>

    <para>
      Thumbnails get created whenever darktable imports an image for the first time, after an
      image has been modified in the darkroom, or when revisiting an <quote>old</quote> image
      whose thumbnail has already been dropped from the cache.
    </para>

    <para>
      When darktable imports an image for the first time there are two possible sources from
      where to take a thumbnail. Either darktable can try to extract an embedded thumbnail out
      of the input image - most raw files contain these kind of thumbnails generated by the
      camera. Alternatively darktable can process the image by itself using default settings.
      You can define how darktable gets its thumbnails in the gui preferences dialog (see
      <xref linkend="gui_options"/>).
    </para>

    <para>
      Extracting an embedded thumbnail from the input image has the advantage of being very
      fast. However, as those thumbnails were generated without knowing your display profile,
      the colors may be rendered in a wrong way. You will notice differences as soon as you open
      the image in the darkroom view, where colors are corrected for your monitor.
    </para>

  </sect3>

  <sect3 status="draft" id="skulls">

    <title>Skulls</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>skulls</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>
      <informaltable frame="none">
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
          <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
          <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  If for some reason darktable is not able to generate a thumbnail it displays a
                  skull. Don't panic!
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <graphic fileref="lighttable/concepts/images/thumbnails_1.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </para>

    <para>
      There are three main reasons for this to happen.
    </para>

    <para>
      It's one possible cause that the input image has been renamed or physically deleted from
      disk. darktable remembers all images ever imported, as long as they have not been removed
      from your database. In case darktable wants to create a thumbnail but is not able to open
      the input file, a skull is displayed instead. Users are advised to remove images from the
      database (see <xref linkend="selected_images"/>) before physically removing them from
      disk. Alternatively you may occasionally run the script
      <filename>purge_non_existing_images.sh</filename> from darktable's toolset to clean-up
      your database.
    </para>

    <para>
      Sometimes darktable is confronted with an input image having an extension that seems valid
      for darktable but having a file format that darktable does not support yet. darktable
      tries to process the image but is not able to get the job done.
    </para>

    <para>
      Another possible cause for getting skulls is memory shortage. If darktable runs out of
      memory while generating a thumbnail it will warn you and display a skull - this can happen
      if darktable is run with suboptimal settings on a 32-bit system. Please consult
      <xref linkend="darktable_and_memory"/> for more information.
    </para>

  </sect3>

</sect2>
