<!DOCTYPE sect4 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect3 status="final" id="blending_operators">

  <title>Blending operators</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>blending operators</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    There are several blend modes implemented and more might be added in future. For now all of
    the most commonly used ones are included and you will recognize a few of them from other
    imaging software. A good introduction on many common blend modes is given in the
    <ulink url="http://docs.gimp.org/2.8/en/gimp-concepts-layer-modes.html"> <emphasis>GIMP
    Manual (Chapter 8.2, <quote>Layer Modes</quote>)</emphasis></ulink>. Therefore we only
    discuss a few blend modes here in more detail.
  </para>

  <sect4 id="blending_operators_modes">

    <title>blend modes</title>

    <sect5 id="blending_operators_modes_normal">
      <title>normal</title>
      <para>
        This will probably be the most used blend mode. It just mixes input and output and,
        depending on the opacity value, it reduces the strength of a module's effect. Generally
        this is also the blend mode of choice if you want to apply a module's effect locally
        using masks.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5 id="blending_operators_modes_bounded">
      <title>normal bounded</title>
      <para>
        This blend mode acts similarly to blend mode <quote>normal</quote>, except that input
        and output data are clamped to a particular min/max value range. Out-of-range values are
        effectively blocked and do not pass to the following modules. Sometimes this helps to
        prevent artifacts. However, in most cases (e.g. highly color saturated extreme
        highlights) it is better to let unbound values travel through the pixelpipe in order to
        properly deal with them at the right place (e.g. in module
        <link linkend="output_color_profile"><emphasis>output color profile</emphasis></link>).
        Blend mode <quote>normal</quote> is most often the preferred choice.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5 id="blending_operators_modes_lightness">
      <title>lightness</title>
      <para>
        This blend mode mixes lightness from the input and output images. Color data (chroma and
        hue) are taken unaltered from the input image.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5 id="blending_operators_modes_chroma">
      <title>chroma</title>
      <para>
        This blend mode mixes chroma (saturation) from the input and output images. Lightness
        and hue are taken unaltered from the input image.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5 id="blending_operators_modes_hue">
      <title>hue</title>
      <para>
        This blend mode mixes hue (color tint) from the input and output images. Lightness and
        chroma are taken unaltered from the input image. Caution: When modules drastically
        modify hue (e.g. when generating complementary colors) this blend mode can result in
        strong color noise.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5 id="blending_operators_modes_color">
      <title>color</title>
      <para>
        This blend mode mixes color (chroma and hue) from the input and output images. Lightness
        is taken unaltered from the input image. Caution: When modules drastically modify hue
        (e.g. when generating complementary colors) this blend mode can result in strong color
        noise.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5 id="blending_operators_modes_lab_lightness">
      <title>Lab lightness</title>
      <para>
        Only available with modules that work in the Lab color space; this blend mode mixes
        lightness from the input and output images, while color data are taken unaltered from
        the input image. In contrast to blend mode <quote>lightness</quote> this blend mode does
        not involve any color space conversion and does not clamp any data. In some cases this
        is less prone to artifacts in comparison to <quote>lightness</quote>.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5 id="blending_operators_modes_lab_color">
      <title>Lab color</title>
      <para>
        Only available with modules that work in the Lab color space; this blend mode mixes Lab
        color channels a and b from the input and output images, while lightness data are taken
        unaltered from the input image. In contrast to blend mode <quote>color</quote> this
        blend mode does not involve any color space conversion and does not clamp any data. In
        some cases this is less prone to artifacts in comparison to <quote>color</quote>.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5 id="blending_operators_modes_hsv_lightness">
      <title>HSV lightness</title>
      <para>
        Only available with modules that work in the RGB color space; this blend mode mixes
        lightness from the input and output images, while color data are taken only from the
        input image. In contrast to blend mode <quote>lightness</quote> this mode does not
        involve clamping.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5 id="blending_operators_modes_hsv_color">
      <title>HSV color</title>
      <para>
        Only available with modules that work in the RGB color space; this blend mode mixes
        color from the input and output images, while lightness data are taken only from the
        input image. In contrast to blend mode <quote>color</quote> this mode does not involve
        clamping.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5 id="blending_operators_modes_color_adjustment">
      <title>color adjustment</title>
      <para>
        Some modules act predominantly on the tonal values of an image but also perform some
        color saturation adjustments, e.g. module
        <link linkend="levels"><emphasis>levels</emphasis></link> and
        <link linkend="tone_curve"> <emphasis>tone curve</emphasis></link>. The color adjustment
        blend mode takes the lightness only from output data and mixes colors from input and
        output enabling control of the module's color adjustments.
      </para>
    </sect5>

  </sect4>

</sect3>
