<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect2 status="final" id="blending">

  <title>Blending</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>blending</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect3 status="final" id="blending_overview">

    <title>Overview</title>

    <para>
      By default a module takes its input from the preceding module, performs its calculations
      and handles its output over to the next module in the pixelpipe. On demand you can
      activate an additional step where a module's output is reprocessed with its input before
      giving the result to the next module. This additional processing step is called blending.
      Input and output can be processed with different algorithms, called blending operators or
      blend modes.
    </para>

    <para>
      Each blend mode is further controlled by a parameter called opacity, which can have a
      value between 0% and 100% and defines how input and output image contribute to the final
      result. Typically an opacity value of 0% gives as a result an image that is identical to
      the input image&nbsp;&ndash; the module remains without effect. An opacity value of 100%
      delivers the maximum effect of the module with the blend mode chosen.
    </para>

    <para>
      The opacity value can be the same for all image pixels. In this case blending acts
      uniformily on the image. Alternatively you can make opacity values to vary between
      different image locations or pixel values. This is called a mask and gives fine control
      over what parts of an image are affected by a module and to what extent. At your choice
      you may activate a drawn mask or a parametric mask or a combination of both.
    </para>

  </sect3>

  <sect3 status="final" id="blending_usage">

    <title>Usage</title>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              Modules with blending support exhibit an additional combobox <quote>blend</quote>
              at the bottom of their GUI.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="darkroom/concepts/images/blending.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

    <sect4 id="blending_usage_blend">

      <title>blend</title>

      <para>
        Blending is activated with this combobox. Depending on the value selected additional
        control elements will show up.
      </para>

      <sect5 id="blending_usage_off">
        <title>off</title>
        <para>
          module's output is passed to the next module in pixelpipe without additional
          reprocessing. No further controls are displayed.
        </para>
      </sect5>

      <sect5 id="blending_usage_uniform">
        <title>uniformily</title>
        <para>
          reprocessing takes place with the chosen blend mode and opacity value&nbsp;&ndash; the
          same for all pixels. Additional controls to select blend mode and opacity value are
          displayed. The default blend mode is <quote>normal</quote> with an opacity of 100%.
        </para>
      </sect5>

      <sect5 id="blending_usage_drawn_mask">
        <title>drawn mask</title>
        <para>
          reprocessing takes place with the chosen blend mode and opacity. Additional controls
          are displayed which allow you to draw a mask. If no mask elements are drawn all pixels
          have the same opacity, defined by the opacity slider. If you draw a mask element, e.g.
          a circle, the inner area of the circle will get maximum opacity, surrounded by a
          transition area or border with a gradual decay of opacity and the remaining image with
          an opacity of 0%. Different graphical shapes can be used. See
          <xref linkend="drawn_mask"/> for further details.
        </para>
      </sect5>

      <sect5 id="blending_usage_parametric_mask">
        <title>parametric mask</title>
        <para>
          reprocessing takes place with the chosen blend mode and opacity. Additional controls
          are displayed which allow you to adjust the opacity on a per-pixel basis determined by
          pixel values. In previous versions of darktable this was called <quote>conditional
          blending</quote>. See <xref linkend="parametric_mask"/> for further details.
        </para>
      </sect5>

      <sect5 id="blending_usage_drawn_parametric_mask">
        <title>drawn and parametric mask</title>
        <para>
          this option combines drawn and parametric masks and shows the full set of both
          controls. See <xref linkend="combined_masks"/> to learn how to best use this
          combination.
        </para>
      </sect5>

    </sect4>

  </sect3>

  <sect3 status="final" id="blending_examples">

    <title>Examples</title>

    <sect4 id="blending_examples_texturing">

      <title>Texturing an image</title>

      <para>
        The watermark module supports SVG files with embedded images that can be used as a
        texture source. Blending operators then allow control of how that texture is expressed.
      </para>

    </sect4>

    <sect4 id="blending_examples_gritty_details">

      <title>Gritty details</title>

      <informaltable frame="none">
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
          <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
          <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                When blending operators were introduced into darktable, a new module named
                <emphasis>highpass</emphasis> (see <xref linkend="highpass"/>) was added. It
                provides a highpass filter of the image to be implicitly used with blending. It
                is used to produce a gritty detailed image and is a method widely used in the
                workflow of other imaging software.
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <graphic fileref="darkroom/concepts/images/blendop_highpass.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>

      <para>
        <informaltable frame="none">
          <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
            <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
            <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <graphic fileref="darkroom/concepts/images/blendop_highpass_ex1_1.png" scalefit="1" width="90%" align="center" />
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    This is the original image, pretty heavily processed: first
                    <link linkend="monochrome"> <emphasis>monochrome</emphasis></link>, then
                    some blue <link linkend="splittoning">
                    <emphasis>splittoning</emphasis></link> but as you see it lacks pop in
                    details and is a bit out of focus...
                  </para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <graphic fileref="darkroom/concepts/images/blendop_highpass_ex1_2.png" scalefit="1" width="90%" align="center" />
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    Here we applied the highpass filter with the values shown above. You can now
                    see that the details are greatly boosted and we now have a really gritty
                    detailed image.
                  </para>
                </entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
      </para>

    </sect4>

  </sect3>

<!-- Blending operators -->

  <xi:include href="blend_operators.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>

<!-- Drawn masks  -->

  <xi:include href="drawn_masks.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>

<!-- Parametric masks  -->

  <xi:include href="parametric_masks.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>

<!-- Combined masks  -->

  <xi:include href="combined_masks.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>

<!-- Mask refinement  -->

  <xi:include href="mask_refinement.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>

</sect2>
