<!DOCTYPE sect3 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect3 status="final" id="combined_masks">

  <title>Combining drawn and parametric masks</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>masks</primary>
    <secondary>combined masks</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    This section describes how darktable combines individual masks to form the final mask of a
    module. Individual masks are the drawn mask and all the single channels of the parametric
    mask. The topic is rather advanced&nbsp;&ndash; if you don't want to go through all the
    theoretical details just jump down where we describe two typical use cases.
  </para>

  <sect4 id="combined_masks_overview">

    <title>Overview</title>

    <para>
      There are two main elements which control how individual masks are combined: the polarity
      setting of each individual mask, defined by the plus or minus buttons, and the setting in
      the <quote>combine masks</quote> combobox (see
      <xref linkend="blending_usage_mask_combination_inversion_combine"/>).
    </para>

    <para>
      Masks can be regarded as grayscale images which take up values between 0 and 1.0 (or from
      0% to 100%) for each pixel.
    </para>

    <para>
      A straightforward way to combine masks is by multiplying the individual pixel values. The
      final mask will have a pixel value of 0 whenever one of the individual masks is 0 at that
      pixel location. The final mask can only reach a maximum pixel value of 1.0 if each and
      every of the individual masks has a value of 1.0 at that location. We call this way of
      combination <quote>exclusive</quote>. Any individual mask can exclude a pixel by setting
      its value to zero, regardless of what the other individual masks do. Once a pixel is
      excluded (its value is 0) by any mask there is no way to include it again by any other
      individual mask.
    </para>

    <para>
      An alternative way to combine masks is the following: we first invert each individual mask
      &nbsp;&ndash; calculating 1.0 minus its value&nbsp;&ndash; then we multiply these inverted
      masks and as a last step invert the final mask again. Now if one of the non-inverted
      individual masks has a value of 1.0 at a pixel location the final will also be 1.0. The
      final mask can only reach a pixel value of 0 if all the individual masks have a value of
      0. We call this way of combination <quote>inclusive</quote>. Any individual mask can
      include a pixel by setting its value to 1.0, regardless of what the other individual masks
      do. Once a pixel is included (its value is 1.0) by any mask there is no way to exclude it
      again by any other individual mask.
    </para>

    <para>
      These two combination methods alone would still be rather limiting. We gain maximum
      flexibility by allowing an additional inversion step for each individual mask. This is
      governed by the polarity buttons
      <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_module_plus;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center"/>
      and
      <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_module_minus;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center"/>
      that you find close to the individual channels. Toggling the polarity button of a mask
      inverts its values, i.e. it recalculates the pixel values to 1.0 minus the original value.
    </para>

    <para>
      Finally within the <quote>combine masks</quote> combobox you may once again invert the
      final result to fit your needs by selecting the <emphasis>exclusive &amp;
      inverted</emphasis> or <emphasis>inclusive &amp; inverted</emphasis> options.
    </para>

  </sect4>

  <sect4 id="combined_masks_usage">

    <title>Usage</title>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              You will typically want to combine drawn and parametric masks to first select a
              certain region of your image&nbsp;&ndash; either by the drawn or the parametric
              mask&nbsp;&ndash; and use the other mask type to finetune your selection.
              Finetuning can either mean that you want to include further parts of the image,
              which are not included in the first place, or you want to exclude parts of the
              image that were previously included.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="darkroom/concepts/images/combined_masks.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

    <para>
      This gives two typical use cases:
    </para>

    <sect5 id="combined_masks_usage_inclusive">
      <title>Inclusive mode</title>
      <para>
        For this mode you set the <quote>combine masks</quote> combobox to
        <emphasis>inclusive</emphasis> and make sure that all polarity buttons of all the
        individual channels and of the drawn mask are set to negative (
        <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_module_minus;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center"/>
        ). Your starting point is a mask where all pixels have a value of zero, i.e. no pixel is
        selected. You now adjust the parametric mask sliders to bring more and more pixels into
        the selection or you draw shapes on the canvas to select specific areas of your image.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5 id="combined_masks_usage_exclusive">
      <title>Exclusive mode</title>
      <para>
        In the opposite case you set the <quote>combine masks</quote> combobox to
        <emphasis>exclusive</emphasis> and make sure that all polarity buttons are set to
        positive (
        <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_module_plus;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center"/>
        ). Your starting point is a mask with all values at 1.0, i.e. all pixels selected. You
        now gradually change the parametric mask sliders to exclude parts of your image as
        needed or you directly draw shapes on the canvas to specifically exclude these areas.
      </para>
      <para>
        For your convenience you find in the parametric masks GUI a
        <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_module_invert;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center" />
        toggle button that inverts all channel polarities and toggles between inclusive and
        exclusive mode in the <quote>combine masks</quote> combobox.
      </para>
      <para>
        For novice users it is recommended to stick to these two use cases. This implies that
        you should decide beforehand how you want to construct your mask. Advanced users will
        find their way to take advantage of the many possible combinations of polarities and
        mask combination modes.
      </para>
    </sect5>

  </sect4>

</sect3>
