<!DOCTYPE sect3 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect3 status="final" id="drawn_mask">

  <title>Drawn mask</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>masks</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>masks</primary>
    <secondary>drawn masks</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>local adjustments</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    Almost all darktable modules have the option to narrow down their effect by a drawn mask and
    thus allowing local adjustments.
  </para>

  <sect4 status="final" id="drawn_mask_overview">

    <title>Overview</title>

    <para>
      With the drawn mask feature you can construct a mask by drawing directly on the image
      base. Different drawing operators, called shapes, are available and can be used alone or
      in combination. A flexible editing feature allows you to change single aspects of a shape,
      remove shapes or import shapes already defined in other modules.
    </para>

    <para>
      Internally shapes are stored as vector graphics and rendered with the needed resolution
      during pixelpipe processing. Shapes are expressed in the coordinate system of the original
      image and transformed with all distorting modules. This way a shape will always work on
      the same image area regardless of warping or other modifications that may be applied.
    </para>

  </sect4>

  <sect4 status="final" id="drawn_mask_usage">

    <title>Usage</title>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              To draw a shape you need to click on one of the shape symbols. You will
              automatically be moved into the edit mode in which you generate a new instance of
              the selected shape and afterwards change its properties.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="darkroom/concepts/images/drawn_masks.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

    <para>
      You leave edit mode by clicking on the
      <inlinegraphic fileref="&shape_edit;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center"/>
      symbol. You can at any time go back to edit mode and do further adjustments by clicking
      the edit symbol again. In edit mode you can also remove a shape by right-clicking on
      it&nbsp;&ndash; the shape is removed from the current mask but it's still in the list of
      defined shapes.
    </para>

    <para>
      Independent of the specific shape you can <emphasis>scroll</emphasis> to change the size
      of the shape, <emphasis>shift+scroll</emphasis> to change the feather of the shape and
      <emphasis>ctrl+scroll</emphasis> to change the opacity of the shape.
    </para>

    <para>
      If you <emphasis>ctrl-click</emphasis> on the edit mode symbol you enter a restricted edit
      mode. Certain actions like dragging a complete shape or changing its size are blocked.
      Only finetuning changes like dragging a node are allowed.
    </para>

    <para>
      Currently five shapes are implemented.
    </para>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>mask shapes</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>shapes</primary>
      <see>mask shapes</see>
    </indexterm>

    <sect5 id="brush_shape">
      <title>brush</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>brush</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>mask shapes</primary>
        <secondary>brush</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>
        Clicking the
        <inlinegraphic fileref="&shape_brush;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center"/>
        symbol adds a brush stroke.
      </para>
      <para>
        Start drawing by <emphasis>left-clicking</emphasis> into the canvas and moving the mouse
        while keeping the button pressed. The brush stroke is finalized once you release the
        mouse button. Brush size, hardness and opacity can be changed by
        <emphasis>scrolling</emphasis>, <emphasis>shift+scrolling</emphasis>, and
        <emphasis>ctrl+scrolling</emphasis>, respectively, either before you start drawing or at
        any time during the operation. Likewise you can use keys
        <emphasis>[&nbsp;|&nbsp;]</emphasis> to decrease/increase brush size,
        <emphasis>{&nbsp;|&nbsp;}</emphasis> to decrease/increase hardness, and
        <emphasis>&lt;&nbsp;|&nbsp;&gt;</emphasis> to decrease/increase opacity.
      </para>
      <para>
        If you have a graphics tablet with pen pressure sensitivity, darktable can apply the
        recorded pen pressure to certain attributes of the brush stroke. See
        <xref linkend="gui_options"/> for more details.
      </para>
      <para>
        On lifting the tablet pen or releasing the left mouse button the drawn figure is
        converted into a number of connected nodes which define the shape. A configuration
        option (see <xref linkend="gui_options"/>) controls how much smoothing is applied. A
        higher level of smoothing leads to less nodes&nbsp;&ndash; this eases subsequent editing
        at the expense of a lower initial accuracy.
      </para>
      <para>
        Nodes and segments of a brush stroke can be modified individually. See the documentation
        on <emphasis>path</emphasis> below for more details.
      </para>
      <para>
        Rendering a complex brush shape can consume a significant number of CPU cycles; consider
        to revert to the circle, ellipse or path shape if possible.
      </para>
      <informaltable frame="none">
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
          <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
          <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                A brush stroke with controls and activated mask display.
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <graphic fileref="darkroom/concepts/images/masks_brush_ex1.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </sect5>

    <sect5 id="circle_shape">
      <title>circle</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>circle</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>mask shapes</primary>
        <secondary>circle</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>
        Clicking the
        <inlinegraphic fileref="&shape_circle;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center"/>
        symbol adds a circle shape.
      </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>Click</emphasis> into the canvas to place the circle.
        <emphasis>Left-click</emphasis> and drag the circle to a different position if needed.
        Use the scroll wheel of your mouse while in the circle to change the diameter;
        <emphasis>scroll</emphasis> within the circle border to adjust the width of the gradual
        decay or <emphasis>shift+scroll</emphasis> anywhere in the shape for the same effect.
        With <emphasis>ctrl+scroll</emphasis> you can adjust the opacity of the
        circle&nbsp;&ndash; this is best observed with the mask displayed by pressing the
        <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_module_mask;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center"/>
        button.
      </para>
      <informaltable frame="none">
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
          <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
          <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                A circle shape with controls and activated mask display.
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <graphic fileref="darkroom/concepts/images/masks_circle_ex1.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </sect5>

    <sect5 id="ellipse_shape">
      <title>ellipse</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>ellipse</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>mask shapes</primary>
        <secondary>ellipse</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>
        Clicking the
        <inlinegraphic fileref="&shape_ellipse;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center"/>
        symbol adds an ellipse shape.
      </para>
      <para>
        The general principle is the same as for the circle shape. In addition you get four
        nodes on the ellipse line. <emphasis>Click</emphasis> on the nodes to adjust the
        ellipse's eccentricity. <emphasis>Ctrl-click</emphasis> on them to rotate the ellipse
        or, alternatively, use <emphasis>shift+ctrl+scroll</emphasis>.
        <emphasis>Shift-click</emphasis> in the shape to toggle the gradual decay between
        equidistant and proportional mode.
      </para>
      <informaltable frame="none">
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
          <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
          <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                An ellipse shape with controls and activated mask display.
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <graphic fileref="darkroom/concepts/images/masks_ellipse_ex1.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </sect5>

    <sect5 id="path_shape">
      <title>path</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>path</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>mask shapes</primary>
        <secondary>path</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>
        Clicking the
        <inlinegraphic fileref="&shape_path;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center"/>
        symbol adds a shape defined by a user defined closed path.
      </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis>Left-click</emphasis> into the canvas to define path nodes; terminate the path
        by <emphasis>right-clicking</emphasis> after having set the last point. Per default
        nodes are connected by smooth lines. If you want a node to define a sharp corner, you
        can do so by creating it with <emphasis>ctrl-click</emphasis>.
      </para>
      <para>
        In the edit mode you can convert existing nodes from smooth to sharp corners and vice
        versa by <emphasis>ctrl-clicking</emphasis> on them. You can insert additional nodes by
        <emphasis>ctrl-clicking</emphasis> on one of the line segments. Single nodes can be
        deleted by <emphasis>right-clicking</emphasis> on them; make sure that the mouse pointer
        is over the desired node and the node is highlighted, or else you might accidentally
        remove the whole path.
      </para>
      <para>
        The size of the complete shape can be modified by
        <emphasis>scrolling</emphasis>&nbsp;&ndash; analogous to the circle shape. The same
        holds true for the width of the border, i.e. the area with a gradual opacity decay,
        which can be changed by <emphasis>scrolling</emphasis> when it is highlighted or by
        <emphasis>shift+scroll</emphasis> from anywhere within the shape. Single nodes as well
        as path segments can be moved by mouse <emphasis>dragging</emphasis>. If a node is
        selected by <emphasis>clicking</emphasis> on it, a further control point
        appears&nbsp;&ndash; you can move it around to modify the curvature of the line and
        reset to default by <emphasis>right-clicking</emphasis>. <emphasis>Dragging</emphasis>
        one of the control points on the border adjusts the border width just in that part of
        the shape.
      </para>
      <para>
        Consider to finetune a path in the restricted edit mode (see above), which allows you to
        adjust single nodes and segments without the risk of accidentally shifting or resizing
        the whole shape.
      </para>
      <informaltable frame="none">
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
          <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
          <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                A path shape with controls and activated mask display.
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <graphic fileref="darkroom/concepts/images/masks_path_ex1.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </sect5>

    <sect5 id="gradient_shape">
      <title>gradient</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>gradient</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>mask shapes</primary>
        <secondary>gradient</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>artifact mitigation</primary>
        <secondary>banding</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>
        Clicking the
        <inlinegraphic fileref="&shape_gradient;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center"/>
        symbol adds a gradient to the mask. This does not generate a confined shape but produces
        a linear gradient extending the whole image.
      </para>
      <para>
        Click into the canvas to define the position of the line where opacity is at 50%. The
        line has two anchor nodes which you can drag to change the rotation of the gradient.
      </para>
      <para>
        Scrolling close to the center line changes the steepness of the gradient. Dotted lines
        indicate the distance beyond which the opacity is 100% and 0%, respectively. Between
        these dotted lines the opacity changes linearly. The gradient is best seen and modified
        when the mask is displayed by pressing the
        <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_module_mask;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center"/>
        button.
      </para>
      <para>
        Depending on the module and the underlying image using a gradient shape might provoke
        banding artifacts. You should consider to activate the <emphasis>dithering</emphasis>
        module (see <xref linkend="dithering"/>)
      </para>
      <informaltable frame="none">
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
          <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
          <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                A gradient with controls and activated mask display.
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <graphic fileref="darkroom/concepts/images/masks_gradient_ex1.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </sect5>

    <sect5 id="drawn_mask_usage_drawn">
      <title>drawn mask</title>
      <para>
        The number of shapes that are used in the current mask is displayed in the <quote>drawn
        mask</quote> field. Clicking on that field opens a dropdown box with all shapes that
        have already been defined in the context of the current image but are not yet used in
        the current mask. You can click on any of these items in order to add it to the current
        mask. The list also contains shapes once generated but no longer in use. This way you
        can even get back a deleted shape.
      </para>
      <para>
        A polarity button (
        <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_module_plus;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center"/>
        and
        <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_module_minus;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center"/>
        , respectively) allows the user to toggle between the normal and the inverted state of
        the drawn mask, i.e. the opacity values get inverted&nbsp;&ndash; 100% becomes 0% and
        vice versa. You need this feature when combining drawn and parametric masks (see
        <xref linkend="combined_masks"/>).
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5 id="blending_usage_mask_combination_inversion_invert">
      <title>invert mask</title>
      <para>
        When <quote>drawn mask</quote> is selected there is an additional combobox to invert the
        mask by switching mask inversion <quote>on</quote> or <quote>off</quote>.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5 id="drawn_mask_usage_manager">
      <title>mask manager</title>
      <para>
        More functionality to control the interaction of multiple shapes within a mask can be
        found in the mask manager panel (see <xref linkend="mask_manager"/>). Here you can give
        individual names to your shapes which will help you to keep track of your shapes. You
        can also select individual shapes for editing&nbsp;&ndash; a helpful feature if your
        masks happens to contain several shapes with overlapping control elements.
      </para>
    </sect5>

  </sect4>


</sect3>
