<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect2 status="final" id="interacting">

  <title>Interacting with modules</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>module usage</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    A module has an expander bar
    <inlinegraphic fileref="&img_module_expander;" scalefit="1" width="30%" align="center"/>
    . Clicking on the name of the module expands the module's GUI with all parameters.
  </para>

  <para>
    In its default setting darktable will only expand one GUI at a time. If you click the
    expander bar of another module, the previous GUI gets collapsed. If you want to see more
    than one GUI expanded, you may expand further modules with <emphasis>shift-click</emphasis>
    &nbsp;&ndash; all previously expanded GUIs remain opened. The expander bar behavior on
    <emphasis>click</emphasis> and <emphasis>shift-click</emphasis>, respectively, is controlled
    by a preference setting in GUI options (see <xref linkend="gui_options"/>).
  </para>

  <para>
    Expanding a module does <emphasis>not</emphasis> activate it. You need to click the
    <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_module_enable;" scalefit="1" width="2%"  align="center"/>
    icon to turn a module on or off.
  </para>

  <para>
    Icon
    <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_module_presets;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center" />
    accesses the module's available presets or creates a new preset from your current settings
    (see <xref linkend="module_presets"/>).
  </para>

  <para>
    The
    <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_module_reset;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center"/>
    icon is used to reset the module parameters to their default values.
  </para>

  <para>
    Many of darktable's modules can have multiple instances, each with different settings. Click
    on the
    <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_module_instances;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center"/>
    icon to generate new instances and control existing ones (see
    <xref linkend="multiple_instances"/>).
  </para>

  <para>
    The most frequently used control elements of modules are sliders, comboboxes and curves.
  </para>

  <sect3 id="interacting_sliders">

    <title>Sliders</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>module usage</primary>
      <secondary>sliders</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>sliders</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>
      Sliders offer five different ways of interaction, depending on the level of control you
      need.
    </para>

    <orderedlist>

      <listitem><para>
        Left-click
      </para>

      <para>
        Click anywhere in the slider area to set the value. You can also click and drag to
        change it. You don't have to aim for the small triangle or even the line, the whole
        height including the label works as the active area.
      </para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>
        Mouse wheel
      </para>

      <para>
        Hover over any place on the slider with your mouse, then use your mouse wheel to adjust
        the value step by step.
      </para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>
        Keyboard arrow keys
      </para>

      <para>
        When the slider has keyboard focus you can hover over any place on the slider with your
        mouse, then use your keyboard's arrow keys (&larr;/&darr; and &rarr;/&uarr;) to adjust
        the value stepwise. In order to give focus to the widget without changing the current
        value you can right-click, then right-click again.
      </para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>
        Right-click
      </para>

      <para>
        When your mouse is over a slider right-click gives you a multi-functional pop-up below
        the slider for fine control with your mouse or numerical entry using the keyboard.
      </para>

      <informaltable frame="none">
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
          <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
          <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                darktable's innovative input method: for both coarse and fine value adjustments
                in a single control element combined with keyboard input.
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <graphic fileref="darkroom/images/darkroom_bauhaus.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>

      <para>
        A bent line extending from the triangular marker moves as you move your mouse. The
        closer your mouse pointer is to the triangular marker the coarser the control; the
        further away from the triangular marker the finer is your control. Left-click with your
        mouse to accept the new value and go back to normal control.
      </para>

      <para>
        Alternatively you can type in a new value using your keyboard and commit by hitting the
        enter key. You may even supply the new value in the form of an arithmetic expressions
        which darktable will calculate for you&nbsp;&ndash; the old value is referenced as
        <quote>x</quote>.
      </para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>
        Double-click
      </para>

      <para>
        You can double-click on a parameter label to reset its value to default.
      </para></listitem>

    </orderedlist>

    <para>
      Additionally, the mouse wheel and keyboard arrow keys support two input modifiers:
      <itemizedlist>

        <listitem><para>
          You can hold down the <emphasis>shift</emphasis> key increasing the stepsize by a
          factor of 10. You can change this multiplier:
<programlisting>darkroom/ui/scale_rough_step_multiplier=10.0
</programlisting>
        </para></listitem>

        <listitem><para>
          You can hold <emphasis>ctrl</emphasis> key decreasing the stepsize by a factor of 10.
          You can change this multiplier:
<programlisting>darkroom/ui/scale_precise_step_multiplier=0.1
</programlisting>
        </para></listitem>

      </itemizedlist>
    </para>

  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="interacting_comboboxes">

    <title>Comboboxes</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>module usage</primary>
      <secondary>comboboxes</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>comboboxes</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>
      Clicking on a combobox will open a list of available options. Click on the item you want
      to select. Sometimes the selection list opens close to the bottom or top of the screen and
      only part of the items are visible; scroll with your mouse wheel to bring up the full
      list. Alternatively, you can also use the mouse wheel and keyboard arrow keys to select an
      option.
    </para>

  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="interacting_curves">

    <title>Curves</title>

    <para>
      Some modules are controlled by adjusting curves. More detail is given later in this
      chapter when the respective modules are explained.
    </para>

  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="interacting_undo_redo">

    <title>Undo/redo</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>undo</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>redo</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>
      During editing darktable records all changes made in the history (see
      <xref linkend="history"/>). This includes modifications of any parameter in a module
      itself but also if a module instance is added or removed. Thanks to this recording it is
      possible to undo changes or redo them to recover a previous editing state. Note that this
      undo/redo facility is unlimited in the number of steps while editing an image but it is
      reset each time the darkroom is switched to a new image.
    </para>

    <para>
      The default key shortcuts are:
      <itemizedlist>

        <listitem><para>
          <emphasis>Ctrl-z</emphasis> : undo last history modification
        </para></listitem>

        <listitem><para>
          <emphasis>Ctrl-y</emphasis> : redo last undo (does nothing if undo has not been used
          yet)
        </para></listitem>

      </itemizedlist>
    </para>

    <para>
      Please note that changes to drawn masks (see <xref linkend="drawn_mask"/>) are not
      recorded and thus cannot be undone.
    </para>

  </sect3>

</sect2>
