<!DOCTYPE sect3 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect3 id="blending_mask_refinement">

  <title>Mask refinement and additional controls</title>

  <sect4 status="final" id="blending_mask_refinement_overview">

    <title>Overview</title>

    <para>
      When a <quote>parametric masks</quote>, a <quote>drawn mask</quote> or a combination of
      both is active several additional sliders are shown that allow for a meticulous refinement
      of the mask.
    </para>

  </sect4>

  <sect4>

    <title>Usage</title>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              When blending with a mask there are some additional options to deal with the final
              mask: you may feather the mask, blur the mask, adjust the mask's brightness and
              contrast, temporarily disable the mask, or display it as an overlay image. The
              latter option is particularly useful for examining the effect of the following
              controls.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="darkroom/concepts/images/mask_refinement.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

    <sect5 id="blending_mask_refinement_feathering_guide">
      <title>feathering guide</title>
      <para>
        Mask feathering smoothens a drawn or parametric mask non-uniformly such that the mask's
        edges are adjusted automatically to match the edges of the image. This mask smoothing is
        guided either by the module's input image or by its output (before blending), depending
        on what is selected in the <quote>feathering guide</quote> combobox. The feathering is
        particularly sensitive to this choice for edge-modifying modules, i.e., modules for
        sharpening or blurring an image.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5 id="blending_mask_refinement_feathering_radius">
      <title>feathering radius</title>
      <para>
        The <quote>feathering radius</quote> slider adjusts the strength of the feathering
        effect. Feathering works best if the drawn and/or parametric mask's edges already match
        approximately some edges in the guiding image. The larger the <quote>feathering
        radius</quote> the better the feathering algorithm can align mask edges to more distant
        edges of the image. If this radius is too large, however, the feathered mask may
        overshoot. This means it cover regions that the user actually wants to exclude.
        Feathering is turned off if the feathering radius is set to&nbsp;0.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5 id="blending_mask_refinement_blur">
      <title>mask blur</title>
      <para>
        Blurring the mask creates a softer transition between blended and unblended parts of an
        image and avoids artifacts. The mask blur slider controls the radius of a gaussian blur
        applied to the final blend mask. The higher the radius, the stronger the
        blur&nbsp;&ndash; or set to 0 for an unblurred mask. Gaussian blur is always applied
        after feathering if both kinds of mask adjustment are activated. This order allows to
        smooth sharp edges or artefacts that may result by feathering.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5 id="blending_mask_refinement_mask_brightness">
      <title>mask opacity</title>
      <para>
        The strength of the module's effect is determined by the mask's local opacity.
        Feathering and blurring the mask may result in a mask with reduced opacity, which
        implies a reduced effect. Therefore, the <quote>mask opacity</quote> slider allows to
        readjust the mask opacity. If the opacity is decreased (negative slider values) least
        opaque parts are affected stronger than most opaque parts. Contrary, if the mask opacity
        is increased (positive slider values) most opaque parts are affected stronger than least
        opaque parts. As a consequence, completely opaque portions of the mask always remain
        opaque and completely transparent portions remain transparent. This is to ensure that
        regions which have been excluded from or included to a module's effect by setting the
        mask's opacity to 0% or 100% remain excluded or included even if the mask opacity is
        adjusted by this slider.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5 id="blending_mask_refinement_mask_contrast">
      <title>mask contrast</title>
      <para>
        This slider increases or decreases the mask contrast. This means it allows to modify the
        transition between opaque and transparent mask parts.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5 id="blending_mask_refinement_temp_off">
      <title>temporarily switch off mask</title>
      <para>
        Sometimes it is useful to visualize the module's effect without the mask taking action.
        You can do so by clicking on the
        <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_module_eye;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center"/>
        symbol, which will temporarily deactivate the mask&nbsp;&ndash; the selected blend mode
        and opacity remain in effect. Switch this button on and off to see if the mask is acting
        on the image as intended.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5 id="blending_mask_refinement_display">
      <title>display mask</title>
      <para>
        Clicking on the
        <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_module_mask;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center"/>
        symbol will display the current mask as a yellow overlay over a black-and-white version
        of your image. Solid yellow indicates an opacity of 100%; a fully visible gray
        background image without yellow overlay indicates an opacity of 0%.
      </para>
    </sect5>

  </sect4>

  <sect4>

    <title>Examples</title>

    <sect5 id="blending_examples_feathering">
      <title>Feathering a drawn mask</title>
      <para>
        <informaltable frame="none">
          <tgroup cols="4" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
            <colspec colwidth="1*"/>
            <colspec colwidth="1*"/>
            <colspec colwidth="1*"/>
            <colspec colwidth="1*"/>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <graphic fileref="darkroom/concepts/images/feathering_1.png" scalefit="1" width="96%" align="center" />
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <graphic fileref="darkroom/concepts/images/feathering_2.png" scalefit="1" width="96%" align="center" />
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <graphic fileref="darkroom/concepts/images/feathering_3.png" scalefit="1" width="96%" align="center" />
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <graphic fileref="darkroom/concepts/images/feathering_4.png" scalefit="1" width="96%" align="center" />
                </entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
      </para>
      <para>
        It can be rather tedious to create a drawn mask by hand, which matches precisely a
        particular object or person in an image. In this example, we want to enhance the color
        contrast of the lion sculpture shown in the left image above without affecting the
        background. For this purpose, a rough selection of the sculpture is created by a drawn
        mask. See the second image above, where the <quote>displays mask</quote> feature is
        active. Note that the mask is rather fuzzy and it does not match precisely the lion
        sculpture. Adjusting the feathering radius, the mask opacity and the mask contrast leads
        to a well matching mask with little effort. In the third image above the feathering
        radius has been adjusted to 50, a blur radius of 5 was chosen to smooth the mask to some
        degree. The mask opacity and the mask contrast have been increased to 0.3 and 0.5,
        respectively, to further enhance the mask. The last image above shows the final result,
        where the color enhancement via the color contrast module (see
        <xref
	linkend="color_contrast"/>) is restricted to the lion sculpture due to the mask.
      </para>
      <para>
        Mask feathering works in this example particularly well because the sculpture in the
        original image is well separated from the blurry background. The distinct edge at the
        border of the sculpture guides the feathering mask adjustment to match the shape of the
        sculpture. Note that feathering can be applied to drawn masks as well as to parametric
        masks.
      </para>
    </sect5>

  </sect4>

</sect3>
