<!DOCTYPE sect3 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect3 status="final" id="parametric_mask">

  <title>Parametric mask</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>masks</primary>
    <secondary>parametric masks</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>conditional blending</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    The parametric mask feature, formerly called <quote>conditional blending</quote>, offers
    fine-grained selective control over how individual pixels are blended. It does so by
    automatically generating an intermediate blend mask from user defined parameters. These
    parameters are color coordinates not the geometrical coordinates used in drawn masks.
  </para>

  <para>
    The parametric mask is a powerful tool with a certain level of complexity.
  </para>

  <sect4 status="final" id="parametric_mask_overview">

    <title>Overview</title>

    <para>
      For each data channel of a module (Lab, RGB) and additionally for several virtual data
      channels (e.g. hue, saturation) users can construct a per-channel opacity function.
      Depending on the pixel's value for this data channel this function determines a blending
      factor between 0 and 1 (or 100%) for that pixel.
    </para>

    <para>
      Each pixel of an image thus has different blending factors for each of its data channels
      (real and virtual). All blending factors are finally pixel-wise multiplied together with
      the value of the global opacity slider (see <xref linkend="blending_operators"/>) to form
      a blend mask for the image.
    </para>

    <para>
      If for a given pixel the blend mask has a value of 0, the input of the module is left
      unchanged. If for a pixel the blend mask has its maximum value of 1 (or 100%), the module
      has full effect.
    </para>

  </sect4>

  <sect4 id="parametric_mask_usage">

    <title>Usage</title>

    <para>
      <informaltable frame="none">
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
          <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
          <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                When <emphasis>parametric mask</emphasis> is activated in combobox
                <quote>blend</quote> an additional set of tabbed controls is shown.
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <graphic fileref="darkroom/concepts/images/blendif_1.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </para>

    <sect5 id="parametric_mask_usage_tabs">
      <title>Channel tabs</title>
      <para>
        Each tab selects a data channel&nbsp;&ndash; real or virtual. Modules acting in Lab
        color space have data channels for L, a, b, C (chroma of LCh) and h (hue of LCh).
        Modules acting in RGB color space have data channels for g (gray), R, G, B, H (hue of
        HSL), S (saturation of HSL), and L (lightness of HSL). Consult for example
        <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Color_space"> Wikipedia's article on color
        spaces</ulink> for a deeper look.
      </para>
      <para>
        Each tab provides two sliders for its data channels: one for the input data that the
        module receives and one for the output data that the module produces prior to blending.
      </para>
      <para>
        You can inspect the image data corresponding to an individual color channel by holding
        down the <emphasis>shift</emphasis> key while entering the respective slider with the
        mouse cursor. The center image changes to display the selected color channel either in
        graycale values or in false colors, depending on the corresponding preference setting in
        <quote>GUI options</quote> (see <xref linkend="gui_options"/>). You may additionally
        hold down the <emphasis>ctrl</emphasis> key which lets you see the resulting mask
        overlaid to the image. When leaving the slider the image goes back to normal after a
        short delay.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5 id="parametric_mask_usage_sliders">
      <title>Color channel sliders</title>
      <para>
        With the color channel slider you construct a trapezoidal opacity function. For this
        purpose there are four markers per slider. Two triangles above the slider mark the range
        of values where opacity is 1. Two triangles below the slider mark the range values where
        opacity is zero. Intermediate points between full and zero opacities are given a
        proportional opacity.
      </para>
      <para>
        The filled triangles, or inside markers, indicate the closed (mostly narrower) edge of
        the trapezoidal function. The open triangles, or outside markers, indicate the open
        (mostly wider) edge of the trapezoidal function. The sequence of the markers always
        remains unchanged: they can touch but they can not switch position.
      </para>
      <para>
        A polarity button (
        <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_module_plus;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center" />
        and
        <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_module_minus;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center" />
        , respectively) to the right of the slider switches between <emphasis>range
        select</emphasis> and <emphasis>range de-select</emphasis> function modes with visual
        confirmation provided by exchanging the upper and the lower triangle markers. These two
        types of trapezoidal functions are represented graphically in the following images.
      </para>
      <para>
        <informaltable frame="none">
          <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
            <colspec colwidth='1*' align='center'/>
            <colspec colwidth='1*' align='center'/>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    Range select function
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    Range de-select function
                  </para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <graphic fileref="darkroom/concepts/images/blendif_2a.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <graphic fileref="darkroom/concepts/images/blendif_3a.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <graphic fileref="darkroom/concepts/images/blendif_2b.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <graphic fileref="darkroom/concepts/images/blendif_3b.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    A trapezoidal function that selects a narrow range of values for blending.
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    A trapezoidal function that de-selects a narrow range of values from
                    blending.
                  </para>
                </entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
      </para>
      <para>
        In their default state all markers are at their extreme positions, maximum left and
        maximum right, respectively. In this state a <emphasis>range select</emphasis> function
        selects the whole range of values giving an <quote>all at 100%</quote> mask. Starting
        from there one can move the sliders inwards to gradually take out more an more parts of
        the image except of the remaining narrow range.
      </para>
      <para>
        A <emphasis>range de-select</emphasis> function per default deselects the whole range of
        values, giving an <quote>all-zero</quote> mask as a starting point. Moving the sliders
        inwards gradually extends the mask more and more except of the remaining narrow range.
      </para>
      <para>
        For more information on the polarity feature read <xref linkend="combined_masks"/>.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5 id="parametric_mask_usage_buttons">
      <title>Control buttons</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>color picker</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>
        Control buttons help you when designing a parametric mask.
      </para>
      <para>
        With the color picker button
        <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_module_picker;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center" />
        you can select a probe from your image. The corresponding values for the real and
        virtual data channels are then displayed within each color channel slider. You can
        switch between point and area sampling mode from within the global color picker panel
        (see <xref linkend="global_color_picker"/>).
      </para>
      <para>
        With the invert button
        <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_module_invert;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center" />
        you can toggle the polarities of all channels (including a potentially activated drawn
        mask) and change the method how channels are combined into the final mask. More on that
        topic can be found in <xref linkend="combined_masks"/>.
      </para>
      <para>
        With the reset button
        <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_module_reset;" scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center" />
        you can put all settings back to their default state.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5 id="blending_usage_mask_combination_inversion_combine">
      <title>combine masks</title>
      <para>
        When either a <quote>parametric masks</quote>, or the combination of <quote>drawn and
        parametric mask</quote> is active an additional combobox is shown that controls how the
        individual masks are combined to form the final mask. This option also allows to invert
        the final mask. Details on the combination of individual masks can be found in
        <xref linkend="combined_masks"/>.
      </para>
    </sect5>

  </sect4>

  <sect4 status="final" id="parametric_mask_examples">

    <title>Example</title>

    <sect5 id="parametric_mask_examples_colorkey">
      <title>Colorkey effect</title>
      <para>
        <informaltable frame="none">
          <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
            <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
            <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    To create a colorkey effect with this poppy blossom in red and the remainder
                    of the image in monochrome, we could apply module
                    <link linkend="monochrome"> <emphasis>monochrome</emphasis></link> to all
                    parts of the image except for of the saturated red petals.
                  </para>

                  <para>
                    We choose the hue channel to control our mask as hue provides good
                    separation between the petals and background.
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <graphic fileref="darkroom/concepts/images/blendif_4.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    These settings in hue channel construct a parametric blend mask that
                    excludes the red petals. The small white bar in the gradient was obtained by
                    using the color picker on one of the petals and the markers then closely
                    centered on the indicated hue to increase the selectivity of our mask.
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <graphic fileref="darkroom/concepts/images/blendif_5.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    The resulting blend mask.
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <graphic fileref="darkroom/concepts/images/blendif_6.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    The final image after module <emphasis>monochrome</emphasis> is applied.
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <graphic fileref="darkroom/concepts/images/blendif_7.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
                </entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
      </para>
    </sect5>

  </sect4>

</sect3>
