<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect2 status="final" id="pixelpipe">

  <title>Pixelpipe, module order, and history stack</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>pixelpipe</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>module processing order</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>history stack</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    darktable processes images&nbsp;&ndash; from input to output&nbsp;&ndash; in a so called
    <quote>pixelpipe</quote>. Within the pixelpipe image processing consists of consecutive
    operations which are implemented as <quote>modules</quote>.
  </para>

  <para>
    Modules are applied in a fixed order. This differentiates darktable, as a non-destructive
    image editor, from classical image manipulation programs like GIMP. As module order is
    fixed, you are free to activate, deactivate or change the parameters of a module at
    arbitrary points in time; the order of activation in your workflow does not have any impact
    on the outcome.
  </para>

  <para>
    Users frequently ask why the module order is fixed and if there are plans to change that
    restriction. There are several reasons why darktable works in the way described:
    <itemizedlist>

      <listitem><para>
        The sequence of modules has been selected with great care in order go give highest
        output quality. Changes to the sequence would generally worsen the result rather than
        improving it.
      </para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>
        Certain image processing steps just don't make sense if they are shifted in the
        pixelpipe. To mention just a few: highlight reconstruction needs to be done on raw data
        before demosaicing and the demosaic step needs to be performed before any input color
        profile can be applied.
      </para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>
        Most of darktable's modules are designed to work within a specific color model (see
        <xref linkend="color_management"/> for more details). Full flexibility would require
        modules to support different parallel algorithms depending on the color space they are
        working in&nbsp;&ndash; this would drastically increase complexity.
      </para></listitem>

    </itemizedlist>
    That said, the fixed sequence of modules is not likely to change in the near future.
  </para>

  <para>
    Whenever you activate or deactivate a module or go back to a module and change the
    parameters, this adds an item on top of the <quote>history stack</quote>.
  </para>

  <para>
    For example, when working on a raw file, the history stack on the left panel might say that
    you first enabled <link linkend="denoise_bilateral"><emphasis>bilateral
    filtering</emphasis></link>, then disabled <link linkend="base_curve"><emphasis>base
    curve</emphasis></link>, then adjusted <link linkend="whitebalance"><emphasis>white
    balance</emphasis></link>. But at any time, the processing took the raw image, adjusted
    <link linkend="whitebalance"><emphasis>white balance</emphasis></link> on it, then
    <link linkend="demosaic"><emphasis>demosaic</emphasis></link>, then
    <link
      linkend="base_curve"><emphasis>base curve</emphasis></link> (if enabled), then
    <link
      linkend="denoise_bilateral"><emphasis>bilateral filtering</emphasis></link> (if
    enabled), as shown bottom to top on the right panel.
  </para>

  <para>
    The history stack records your workflow in the order in which you made changes to the
    pipeline. It allows you to go back to an earlier stage of development if needed. The history
    stack represents your personal workflow and is not to be confused with the sequence in which
    modules are applied in the pixelpipe (see above). For more details on the history stack see
    <xref linkend="history"/>.
  </para>

</sect2>
