<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE sect2 [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_ent SYSTEM "../../darktable.ent">
		%darktable_ent;
]>

<sect2
    version="5.0"
    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" 
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" 
    xml:lang="en"
    status="final"
    xml:id="module_presets">

  <title>Module presets</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>presets</primary>
    <secondary>module presets</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>module presets</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    Presets are stored configurations for a module's parameters. Some modules already have
    internal pre-defined presets but you can also define your own. Both internal and
    user-defined presets are displayed by clicking the
    <inlinemediaobject>
      <imageobject>
	<imagedata fileref="&icon_module_presets;"  scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center"/>
      </imageobject>
    </inlinemediaobject>
    icon with the currently activated preset shown in bold text.
  </para>

  <para>
    The preset system also supports automatic preset selection based on image data such as focal
    length, ISO, camera model and other fields.
  </para>

  <sect3 status="final" xml:id="module_presets_new">

    <title>Creating a new preset</title>

    <para>
      First configure the module's parameters then click the
      <inlinemediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="&icon_module_presets;"  scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center"/>
	</imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject>
      icon and select <quote>store new preset</quote>. The following dialog will be shown for
      configuring the preset:
    </para>

    <para>
      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="darkroom/concepts/images/new_preset.png" scalefit="1" width="60%" align="center" />
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </para>

    <para>
      The first two fields are used to name and describe the preset.
    </para>

    <para>
      In the example above we have also checked the auto apply option. This brings up additional
      selection fields where you can define a filter used to decide if the preset should be
      automatically applied when opening other similar images in darkroom for the first time.
      The example dialog above sets up following rules: if lens name matches and aperture is
      greater or equal to f/8 and focal length is between 24 and 35mm the preset will be
      automatically applied. Also the second checkbox is clicked so this preset will only be
      shown in the preset list if the image matches the rule.
    </para>

    <para>
      darktable finds this data in your image's Exif information. If you want a preset to be
      applied to all images from a specific camera leave all fields at default values except for
      the model field.
    </para>

    <para>
      Tip: The <emphasis>image information</emphasis> panel for your image displays your model
      name, use this to ensure you have the correct spelling (see
      <xref linkend="image_information"/>).
    </para>

  </sect3>

  <sect3 status="final" xml:id="module_presets_managing">

    <title>Managing Presets</title>

    <para>
      Both user created and pre-defined presets can be viewed and managed from within the
      presets menu (<xref linkend="presets"/>) in the preferences dialog (see
      <xref linkend="preferences_chapter"/>).
    </para>

  </sect3>

</sect2>
