<!DOCTYPE sect3 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect3 status="draft" id="raster_mask">

  <title>Raster mask</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>masks</primary>
    <secondary>raster masks</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    When a <quote>drawn mask</quote> or a <quote>parametric mask</quote> is active
    the final mask can be reused in other modules. This works because all the shapes from the drawn mask 
    and all the blend functions from the parametric mask of a module assemble a final mask,
    which internally is stored as a raster image and made accessible to other modules.
  </para>

  <sect4 status="draft" id="raster_mask_overview">

    <title>Overview</title>

    <para>
      Each individual mask selects a set of pixels and how drastically the effect of the module
      is applied to this selection. Several drawn masks and parametric blend functions can be defined 
      and they all together render the final mask, the final settings of how drastically the effect 
      of the module will be. 
    </para>

    <para>
      The selection of these masks can be saved as an alpha map, that is an image
      as big as the input image in which for each pixel an intensity value is being stored between zero
      and the maximum alpha value. If the value for a pixel is zero the input of the module is left unchanged, if the 
      value has the maximum intensity the module has full effect and for each alpha value in-between the 
      minimum and the maximum the effect is applied proportionally at that location.
    </para>

    <para>
      Internally for each module the alpha map is saved and made accessible to other modules in the raster mask button.
      So a mask from any module can be reused from any other module easily.
    </para>

  </sect4>

  <sect4 id="raster_mask_usage">

    <title>Usage</title>

    <sect5 id="raster_mask_usage_dropdown">
      <title>Drop-down menu</title>
      <para>
        If there is a mask in another module it will appear in the drop-down menu of the raster mask.
        You can easily identify the mask by the name of the module it was defined in.
      </para>
    </sect5>  

  </sect4>

</sect3>
