<!DOCTYPE sect3 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect3 status="final" id="color_mapping">

  <title>Color mapping</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>modules</primary>
    <secondary>color mapping</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>color mapping</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect4>

    <title>Overview</title>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              This module transfers the look and feel from one image onto another. It
              statistically analyses the color characteristics of a source image and a target
              image. The colors of the source image are then mapped to corresponding colors of
              the target image.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/colormapping.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

  </sect4>

  <sect4>

    <title>Usage</title>

    <para>
      To use this module two steps are required.
    </para>

    <para>
      First you open the source image in darkroom mode and acquire its color characteristics by
      pressing the <quote>acquire as source</quote> button. A set of color clusters is generated
      and displayed in the <quote>source clusters</quote> area. Each cluster is represented by a
      set of color swatches with the mean value in the center surrounded by swatches indicating
      the color variance within that cluster. The clusters are sorted in ascending order by
      their weight, i.e. the number of pixels that contribute to the clusters.
    </para>

    <para>
      Next you open your target image in darkroom mode. darktable has remembered the previously
      collected source clusters; if they are not yet displayed, press the
      <inlinegraphic fileref="&icon_module_reset;"  scalefit="1" width="2%" align="center"/>
      button. You now press the <quote>acquire as target</quote> button to generate a
      corresponding set of color clusters for your target image, which gets displayed in the
      <quote>target clusters</quote> area.
    </para>

    <para>
      When both source and target clusters are collected an automatic color mapping is applied
      to the target image. In its default settings the overall effect is quite exaggerated. A
      set of sliders gives you control of the effect's strength. You can also use blending
      operator <quote>normal</quote> to tame the effect (see
      <xref linkend="blending_operators"/>). As the <emphasis>color mapping</emphasis> module
      comes early in the pixelpipe, you can finetune the colors with modules like <emphasis>tone
      curve</emphasis> (see <xref linkend="tone_curve"/>) or <emphasis>color
      correction</emphasis> (see <xref linkend="color_correction"/>).
    </para>

    <sect5>
      <title>acquire as source/target</title>
      <para>
        Press these buttons to generate color clusters for the source and target image,
        respectively. The processing takes a few seconds during which the GUI remains
        unresponsive.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>number of clusters</title>
      <para>
        Sets the number of color clusters to use. If you change this parameter all collected
        color clusters are reset and need to be acquired anew.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>color dominance</title>
      <para>
        This parameter controls the mapping between source and target clusters. At the lowest
        value mapping is based on color proximity. This typically leads to very subtle effects
        on the target image. At the maximum value mapping is based on the relative weight of the
        color clusters&nbsp;&ndash; dominant colors of the source image are mapped to dominant
        colors of the target image. This typically leads to a very bold effect. In-between
        values incrementally shift between the extremes.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>histogram equalization</title>
      <para>
        Besides mapping of color characteristics this module can modify the target image's
        contrast by matching its histogram with the histogram of the source image. This slider
        controls the extent of the effect.
      </para>
    </sect5>

  </sect4>

  <sect4>

    <title>Examples</title>

    <para>
      <informaltable frame="none">
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
          <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
          <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/colormapping_ex1.png" scalefit="1" width="90%" align="center" />
              </entry>
              <entry>
                The source image taken shortly after sunset under front lighting conditions.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/colormapping_ex2.png" scalefit="1" width="90%" align="center" />
              </entry>
              <entry>
                The target image taken in the afternoon with a partly clouded sky. Our goal is
                to transfer the evening atmosphere of the source image.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/colormapping_ex3.png" scalefit="1" width="90%" align="center" />
              </entry>
              <entry>
                The target image with color mapping applied. A number of 2 clusters was used.
                <quote>color dominance</quote> is set to 100% for a bold but still credible
                effect. <quote>histogram equalization</quote> is set to 80%.
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </para>

  </sect4>

</sect3>
