<!DOCTYPE sect3 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../../../dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<sect3 status="final" id="splittoning">

  <title>Splittoning</title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>modules</primary>
    <secondary>splittoning</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>splittoning</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect4>

    <title>Overview</title>

    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              darktable's splittoning method creates a two color linear toning effect where the
              shadows and highlights are represented by two different colors. In the example
              image below you can see an original black and white image and one where a
              splittoning effect is applied with blue in shadows and a yellowish color in
              highlights.
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/splittoning.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

    <para>
      Compared to traditional splittoning our module has more parameters to influence its
      behavior. We have parameter <quote>balance</quote>, which offsets the 50% gray level in
      your image&nbsp;&ndash; at your choice&nbsp;&ndash; more to the shadows or more to the
      highlights. Additionally, with parameter <quote>compression</quote> you can compress
      toning in the shadows and highlights and leave a gap in the mid-tones, which remain
      untouched by the effect.
    </para>

    <para>
      The splittoning module does not convert images to black and white and has limited benefits
      on color images. So, if you want to do traditional splittoning, use the
      <emphasis>monochrome</emphasis> module (see <xref linkend="monochrome"/>) to make the
      image black and white before playing around with splittoning effect.
    </para>

  </sect4>

  <sect4>

    <title>Usage</title>

    <sect5>
      <title>shadows and highlights color</title>
      <para>
        These controls are used to set the color of the splittoning effect, you select the
        desired color and saturation for both shadows and highlights. Clicking on the colored
        squares will open a color selector dialog which offers you a choice of commonly used
        colors, or allows to define a color in RGB color space.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>balance</title>
      <para>
        This parameter represents the ratio of toning between shadows and highlights. For a
        value of 50% half of the lightness range in image is used for shadows toning and the
        other half for highlights toning.
      </para>
    </sect5>

    <sect5>
      <title>compression</title>
      <para>
        Compression is a percentage of total lightness range that is not affected by color
        toning. Default value is set to 33%; this is not the default behavior of an original
        splittoning which would be 0% compression. The choice of 33% as a default is to invite
        you experimenting with these parameters and how it extends the original splittoning
        method.
      </para>
    </sect5>

  </sect4>

  <sect4>

    <title>Examples</title>

    <para>
      <informaltable frame="none">
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
          <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
          <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/splittoning_ex1.png" scalefit="1" width="90%" align="center" />
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Original black and white image.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <graphic fileref="darkroom/modules/images/splittoning_ex2.png" scalefit="1" width="90%" align="center" />
              </entry>
              <entry>
                Splittoning with blue shadows and yellow highlights.
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </para>

  </sect4>

</sect3>
