<chapter>
<chapterinfo>
<keywordset>
  <keyword>darkroom</keyword>
  <keyword>view</keyword>
</keywordset>
</chapterinfo>
<title>Darkroom</title>
<para>The darkroom view is where you develop your image...</para>
<screenshot>
	<screeninfo>The darkroom view</screeninfo>
	<graphic fileref="images/darkroom_view.png" scalefit="1" width="80%"></graphic>
</screenshot>

<sect1><title>Overview</title>
	<para>In darkroom you are in develop mode for the specific image; here you have a lot of tools (named module) to
		develop you image.
	</para>
	<para>On the left side you have the navigation, snapshots and history panels, each of them being described below; 
	in the right panel you can see the histogram and then a list of available modules to use when working with your image. 
	At the bottom of the right panel you can enable/disable view of individual modules.
	</para>
	<para>Since darktable 0.6.1, modules are grouped into four groups: basic, color, correct, effect.
	However, you can view all modules by selecting no group.
	</para>
	<para>For those interested in how it works, modules are applied on images following a bottom-to-top order.
	That means, that if you activated the view of all modules (by selecting no groups), the first module to be applied
	will be "import a RAW" at the bottom of the right panel, whereas the last one will be "splittoning" at the 
	top of the right panel.
	That order can not be changed by user, so modules are always applied following the same order.
	</para>

	<para>You can use <emphasis>middle-click</emphasis>  to zoom 1:1. A double <emphasis>middle-click</emphasis>  takes you to 2:1.
	</para>

	<para>You can export directly from the darkroom by using <emphasis>ctrl-e</emphasis> shortcut. Parameters are those currently selected in lighttable.</para>

</sect1>
<sect1 status="draft"><title>Filmstrip</title>
	<para>The filmstrip is used to quickly switch between image to develop in darkroom view, the images viewed are the same
		as the ones in the lighttable view. 
	</para>
	<para>The filmstrip can be switch on and off using <emphasis>ctrl-f</emphasis> shortcut.</para>


</sect1>
<sect1><title>Panels</title>
	<sect2 status="draft"><title>Navigation</title>
		<informaltable frame="none"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
				<colspec colwidth='70%'/>
				<colspec colwidth='30%'/>
				<tbody>
					<row>						
						<entry>This panels shows the whole image and a rectangle is showing the current zoom view that  you see, you can move this rectangle to 
								pan around in same zoomlevel.
						</entry>
						<entry>
							<graphic fileref="darkroom/images/panel_navigation.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
						</entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</informaltable>
	</sect2>
	<sect2 status="final"><title>Snapshots</title>
		<informaltable frame="none"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
				<colspec colwidth='70%'/>
				<colspec colwidth='30%'/>
				<tbody>
					<row>						
						<entry>You can take a snapshot of what is displayed in the center view; 
							this snapshot can then be selected and is overlayed in the current center view to help you with a side by side comparasion 
							(left: snapshot, right: active) when you are tuning parameters of a module. 
							In the active view, history remains usable in order to compare with the snapshot.
						</entry>
						<entry>
							<graphic fileref="darkroom/images/panel_snapshots.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
						</entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</informaltable>
	</sect2>
	<sect2 status="draft"><title>Metadata</title>
		<para>Shows the metadata for an image, same as in lighttable mode.
		</para>
	</sect2>
	<sect2 status="draft"><title>History</title>
		<informaltable frame="none"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
				<colspec colwidth='70%'/>
				<colspec colwidth='30%'/>
				<tbody>
					<row>						
						<entry>
						<para>The historystack lists every change of state (activate/de-activated) for all modules.
            					Here you can select a point in stack to return to that point of development history.
            					If you then activate a new module, all modules above the current point will be discarded.
						</para>
						<para>
            					Hitting 'compress historystack' generates the shortest historystack that produces the
            					current image, i.e. suppressing all de-activated modules.
						</para>
						<para>The button to the right lets you create a new styles by poping-up a new window.
						Use the first line to name your style, the second to add a searchable description.
						The "advanced presets" allows you chose which modules are to be taken into account for the styles.
						</para>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							<graphic fileref="darkroom/images/panel_history.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
						</entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</informaltable>
	</sect2>
	<sect2 status="draft"><title>Histogram</title>
		<informaltable frame="none"><tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
				<colspec colwidth='70%'/>
				<colspec colwidth='30%'/>
				<tbody>
					<row>						
						<entry>Show a logarithmic histogram of the developed image; you can change exposure by left mouse click in the right side of histogram and drag 
								right for increase or left to decrease the exposure. The same goes for the black level but you left click in the left part of histogram.
						</entry>
						<entry>
							<graphic fileref="darkroom/images/panel_histogram.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
						</entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</informaltable>
	</sect2>
</sect1>

<!-- Modules -->
<xi:include href="modules/modules.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>

<!-- Examples -->
<xi:include href="examples/examples.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>

</chapter>
