<chapter>
<chapterinfo>
<keywordset>
  <keyword>darkroom</keyword>
  <keyword>view</keyword>
</keywordset>
</chapterinfo>
<title>Darkroom</title>
<para>The darkroom view is where you develop your image...</para>
<screenshot>
	<screeninfo>The darkroom view</screeninfo>
	<graphic fileref="images/darkroom_view.png" scalefit="1" width="80%"></graphic>
</screenshot>

<sect1><title>Overview</title>
	<para>In darkroom you are in develop mode for the specific image, here you have alot of tools to
		develop you image.
	</para>
	<para>On the left side you have the navigation, snapshots, history and history panel each of them are described below, 
		in the right panel you can see the histogram and then a list of available modules to use when working with your image.
		And at bottom of right panel you can enable/disable individual modules which will remove them from the right panel.
	</para>
	<sect2><title>Panels</title>
		<sect3><title>Navigation</title>
			<para>This panels shows the whole image and a rectangle is showing the current zoom view that  you see, you can move this rectangle to 
				pan around in same zoomlevel.
			</para>
		</sect3>
		<sect3><title>Snapshots</title>
			<para>You can take a snapshot of what is displayed in the center view, this snapshot can then be selected and is overlayed in the current center
				view to help you with a side by side comparasion when you tuning parameters of a module.
			</para>
		</sect3>
		<sect3><title>Metadata</title>
			<para>Shows the metadata for an image, same as in lighttable mode.
			</para>
		</sect3>
		<sect3><title>Historystack</title>
			<para>The historystack is each change of module in history, here you can select a point in stack an hit compress historystack button to get back
				to the select point of changes...
			</para>
		</sect3>
		<sect3><title>Histogram</title>
			<para>Shows an histogram for the result of developed image, you can change exposure by left mouse click in right side of histogram and drag 
			right for increase or left to decrease the exposure, same goes for the blacklevel but you left click in the left part of historgram.
			</para>
		</sect3>
	</sect2>
		
</sect1>

&darkroom_modules;

</chapter>