<chapter id="darkroom chapter">
<chapterinfo>
<keywordset>
  <keyword>darkroom</keyword>
  <keyword>view</keyword>
</keywordset>
</chapterinfo>
<title>Darkroom</title>
<para>The darkroom view is where you develop your image...</para>
<screenshot>
	<screeninfo>The darkroom view</screeninfo>
	<graphic fileref="images/darkroom_view.png" scalefit="1" width="80%"></graphic>
</screenshot>

<sect1><title>Overview</title>
	<para>In darkroom you are in develop mode for the specific image; here you have a lot of tools (named modules) to
		develop you image.
	</para>
	<para>On the left side you have the navigation, snapshots and history panels, each of them being described below. 
	In the right panel you can see the histogram and then a list of available modules to use when working with your image. 
	At the bottom of the right panel you can enable/disable view of individual modules.
	</para>
	<para>Since darktable 0.6.1, modules are grouped into four groups: basic, color, correct, effect.
	However, you can view all modules by selecting no group.
	</para>
	<para>For those interested in how it works, modules are applied on images following a bottom-to-top order.
	That means, that if you activated the view of all modules (by selecting no groups), the first module to be applied
	will frequently be <link linkend="whitebalance"><emphasis>whitebalance</emphasis></link> quite at the bottom of the right panel, whereas the last 
        one will be <link linkend="dithering"><emphasis>dithering</emphasis></link> at the top of the right panel.
	That order can not be changed by user, so modules are always applied following the same order.
	</para>

	<para>You can use <emphasis>middle-click</emphasis>  to zoom 1:1. A double <emphasis>middle-click</emphasis>  takes you to 2:1.
	</para>

	<para>You can export directly from the darkroom by using <emphasis>ctrl-e</emphasis> shortcut. Export parameters are those currently selected in lighttable.</para>

</sect1>
<sect1 status="draft" id="filmstrip"><title>Filmstrip</title>
	<para>The filmstrip is used to quickly switch between images to develop in darkroom view, the images viewed are the same
		as the ones in the lighttable view.
	</para>
	<para>The filmstrip can be switched on and off using <emphasis>ctrl-f</emphasis> shortcut. You can scroll with your mouse to quickly navigate
              through the images. The height of the filmstrip panel can be changed by dragging the corresponding marker.</para>
	<graphic fileref="darkroom/images/filmstrip.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />

</sect1>


<!-- Panels -->
<xi:include href="panels/panels.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>

<!-- Modules -->
<xi:include href="modules/modules.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>

<!-- Examples -->
<xi:include href="examples/examples.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>

</chapter>
