<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
                <!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "../dtd/darktable.dtd">
                %darktable_dtd;
                ]>
<sect1 status="final" id="darktable_chart">

  <title>Using <filename>darktable-chart</filename>

  </title>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>darktable-chart</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect2 status="final" id="darktable_chart_overview">

    <title>Overview</title>

    <para>
      With <filename>darktable-chart</filename> we provide a tool for extracting luminance and
      color values out of images taken from color reference cards like IT8.7/1 charts. Its main
      purpose is to compare a source image (typically a largely unprocessed raw image) to a
      target image (typically a JPEG image created in-camera) and produce a darktable style that
      is able to convert luminance and color values of the source image to produce the target
      image. This style employs the <emphasis>base curve</emphasis> module, the <emphasis>input
      color profile</emphasis>, and the <emphasis>color look up table</emphasis> module for that
      purpose (see <xref linkend="base_curve"/>, <xref linkend="input_color_profile"/>, and
      <xref linkend="color_look_up_table"/>).
    </para>

    <para>
      Some cameras are particularly advanced in offering various film simulation modes of your
      choice. With the help of <filename>darktable-chart</filename> and the underlying modules
      you can now create styles that replicate these film simulations from within darktable.
    </para>

  </sect2>

  <sect2 status="final" id="darktable_chart_usage">

    <title>Usage</title>

    <para>
      <informaltable frame="none">
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
          <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
          <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                The tool is organized into three tabs in the upper part and a text output frame
                in the lower part.
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <graphic fileref="images/darktable_chart_overview.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </para>

    <para>
      The first tab is used to define the source image, the second tab defines the reference
      (target) and the third tab contains the controls to generate the resulting darktable
      style.
    </para>

  </sect2>

  <sect2 status="final" id="darktable_chart_source_image">

    <title>Source image</title>

    <para>
      In the <quote>source image</quote> tab you set your source image which requires two
      elements. The first element is an input file in Lab Portable Float Map format (extension
      <emphasis>.pfm</emphasis>). The source file represents the largely unmodified data as the
      camera sees them. Details on taking photos of a color reference card and producing a
      <emphasis>.pfm</emphasis> output file are described below. The second element is a chart
      file that contains a formal description of the underlying color reference card's layout
      (extension <emphasis>.cht</emphasis>). Chart files are usually shipped with your color
      reference card or can be downloaded.
    </para>

    <para>
      In real life the photo taken from the color reference card will show some perspective
      distortions relative to the layout defined in the chart file. For that reason the layout
      is displayed as a grid over the image and can be modified.
    </para>

    <para>
      <informaltable frame="none">
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
          <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
          <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                You can move the corners of the grid using the mouse to reach best alignment of
                grid and image.
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <graphic fileref="images/darktable_chart_source.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </para>

    <para>
      A rectangular frame is displayed for each patch and defines the area from which
      <filename>darktable-chart</filename> will actually sample the needed input data. It may be
      required to modify the size of these rectangles so that the sampling area is big enough
      but does not overlap with neighboring patches. Use the <quote>size</quote> slider in the
      upper right part of the GUI. Higher values lead to smaller sizes.
    </para>

  </sect2>

  <sect2 status="final" id="darktable_chart_reference_values">

    <title>Reference values</title>

    <para>
      The <quote>reference values</quote> tab determines the target values to which the source
      image is to be modified by the resulting style. You can either supply reference values in
      the form of measured data of your color reference card (mode <quote>cie/it8 file</quote>),
      or you supply a photographic image (mode <quote>color chart image</quote>) much in the
      same way as described above. This second image must also be supplied in Lab Portable Float
      Map format. There is no need to supply the chart file again as
      <filename>darktable-chart</filename> takes the same one as defined under <quote>source
      image</quote>. You only need to again align the layout grid and the image and potentially
      adjust the <quote>size</quote> slider.
    </para>

    <para>
      In a typical use case the second image will be based on a JPEG file produced in-camera.
      This way you can create a style to simulate the in-camera processing within darktable.
    </para>

    <para>
      In the lower text output frame you see the color values extracted from the available data
      for each individual color patch. The first column gives the name of the patch, the second
      and third column show the corresponding color values of the source image in RGB and Lab
      format, respectively. The fourth column contains the Lab value coming from the reference
      (or from the chart file if no reference image has been given). Finally, the fifth and
      sixth columns display how strongly source and reference values deviate in terms of delta E
      values.
    </para>

  </sect2>

  <sect2 status="final" id="darktable_chart_process">

    <title>Process</title>

    <para>
      <informaltable frame="none">
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
          <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
          <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                If all required settings in <quote>source image</quote> and <quote>reference
                values</quote> are ready you can move to the <quote>process</quote> tab.
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <graphic fileref="images/darktable_chart_process.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </para>

    <para>
      You first need to tell <filename>darktable-chart</filename> which of the patches represent
      the gray ramp. In the screenshot displayed further above the gray ramp is positioned in
      the lower part of the color reference chart, denoted as <quote>GS00...GS23</quote>.
    </para>

    <para>
      The input <quote>number of final patches</quote> defines how many editable color patches
      the resulting style will use within the <emphasis>color look up table</emphasis> module
      (for more details see <xref linkend="color_look_up_table"/>).
    </para>

    <para>
      By clicking the <quote>process</quote> button you start the calculation.
    </para>

    <para>
      The quality of the result in terms of average delta E and maximum delta E are displayed
      below the button. These data show how close the resulting style applied to the source
      image will be able to match the reference values&nbsp;&ndash; the lower the better.
    </para>

    <para>
      <informaltable frame="none">
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
          <colspec colwidth="6*"/>
          <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                Once you are happy with the result you can click on <quote>export</quote> and
                save the generated style.
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <graphic fileref="images/darktable_chart_save.png" scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" />
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </para>

    <para>
      You supply a style name and a style description under which the style will later appear in
      darktable. <filename>darktable-chart</filename> saves the style as a
      <emphasis>.dtstyle</emphasis> file which can be imported into darktable (see
      <xref linkend="styles"/>) and shared with others.
    </para>

    <para>
      The <quote>export raw data as csv</quote> button allows you to save the extracted raw data
      as a CSV file for debugging purposes or later usage. <filename>darktable-chart</filename>
      offers a command line option to produce a style with the desired number of final patches
      from a supplied CSV file (see <xref linkend="darktable_chart_commandline_parameters"/>).
    </para>

  </sect2>

  <sect2 status="final" id="darktable_chart_making_input_images">

    <title>Making input images for <filename>darktable-chart</filename>

    </title>

    <para>
      To start with, you need a suitable photo of your color reference card in RAW+JPEG format.
      It goes beyond the scope of this manual to explain the details of how to take this photo,
      but in a nutshell you need to make the shot on a sunny day around midday with the light
      source (sun) shining at an angle onto the card. You need to avoid any glare in the image.
      The neutral white color patch in the gray ramp (G00) should end up at the L value
      specified in the description of your card. Often this is L=92 and requires you to
      overexpose the shot by about 1/3 EV. Ideally you make several shots with slightly
      different exposures to later select the right one in darktable. Make sure that the chart
      fills up most of the frame. Take a lens with a <quote>normal</quote> focal length (e.g.
      50mm equivalent) and stop down a bit to avoid vignetting.
    </para>

    <para>
      You then open the raw file in darktable and disable most modules, especially
      <emphasis>base curve</emphasis>. Select the standard input matrix in the <emphasis>input
      color profile</emphasis> module and disable gamut clipping. Select <quote>camera white
      balance</quote> in the <emphasis>white balance</emphasis> module (see
      <xref linkend="base_curve"/>, <xref linkend="input_color_profile"/>, and
      <xref linkend="whitebalance"/>).
    </para>

    <para>
      There is a special situation if your camera automatically applies some lens corrections,
      namely vignetting correction, to the resulting JPEG file. In this case you need to
      activate the <emphasis>lens correction</emphasis> module in darktable so that raw
      processing matches the JPEG in this respect (see <xref linkend="lens_correction"/>).
    </para>

    <para>
      To output your image you go to the <quote>export</quote> module in darktable (see
      <xref linkend="export_selected"/>).
    </para>

    <para>
      You need to select <quote>Lab</quote> as output color profile. This color space is not
      visible in the combobox by default. You first need to enable it by setting
      allow_lab_output to TRUE in <filename>$HOME/.config/darktable/darktablerc</filename>.
      Alternatively, you can start darktable with:
    </para>

    <para>
<programlisting>darktable --conf allow_lab_output=true
</programlisting>
    </para>

    <para>
      Then select <quote>PFM (float)</quote> as output format and press <quote>export</quote> to
      generate the source image file.
    </para>

    <para>
      In a similar way you produce the corresponding reference (target) image from the JPEG.
      Also this time you need to disable all modules and export with <quote>Lab</quote> output
      color profile in <quote>PFM (float)</quote> format.
    </para>

  </sect2>

</sect1>
