<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
		<!ENTITY % darktable_dtd SYSTEM "dtd/darktable.dtd">
		%darktable_dtd;
		]>
<book lang="en">

  <title>darktable 1.6</title>

  <bookinfo>

    <legalnotice>

      <para>
        The owner of the darktable project is Johannes Hanika. Main developers are Johannes
        Hanika, Henrik Andersson, Tobias Ellinghaus, Pascal de Bruijn and Ulrich Pegelow.
      </para>

      <para>
        darktable has been developed with major contribution by Aldric Renaudin, Alexandre
        Prokoudine, Ammon Riley, Andrew Toskin, Andrey Kaminsky, Antony Dovgal, Artur de Sousa
        Rocha, Brian Teague, Bruce Guenter, Cherrot Luo, Christian Himpel, Christian Tellefsen,
        Dan Torop, David Bremner, Dennis Gnad, Dimitrios Psychogios, Eckhart Pedersen, Edouard
        Gomez, Frédéric Grollier, Gaspard Jankowiak, Ger Siemerink, Gianluigi Calcaterra,
        Guilherme Brondani Torri, Igor Kuzmin, Ivan Tarozzi, James C. McPherson, Jean-Sébastien
        Pédron, Jérémy Rosen, Jesper Pedersen, Jochen Schröder, Johanes Schneider, José
        Carlos Casimiro, Jose Carlos Garcia Sogo, Josep Vicenç Moragues Pastor, Kaminsky
        Andrey, Kanstantsin Shautsou, Karl Mikaelsson, Loic Guibert, Marcel Laubach, Mauro
        Bartoccelli, Michal Babej, Michel Leblond, Mikko Ruohola, Milan Knížek, Moritz Lipp,
        Olivier Tribout, Pascal Obry, Pedro Côrte-Real, Petr Styblo, Richard Hughes, Richard
        Levitte, Richard Wonka, Robert Bieber, Roman Lebedev, Rostyslav Pidgornyi, Sergey
        Pavlov, Simon Spannagel, Stuart Henderson, Tatica Leandro, Thomas Pryds, Victor Lamoine,
        Wolfgang Goetz, Wyatt Olson and many others.
      </para>

      <para>
        darktable is free software: you can redistribute it and/or modify it under the terms of
        the GNU General Public License as published by the Free Software Foundation, either
        version 3 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.
      </para>

      <para>
        darktable is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY;
        without even the implied warranty of MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR
        PURPOSE. See the GNU General Public License for more details.
      </para>

      <para>
        You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License along with darktable.
        If not, see <ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/licenses/"> <emphasis>the GNU
        homepage</emphasis></ulink>.
      </para>

      <para></para>

      <para>
        The present user manual is under license <emphasis>cc by-sa </emphasis>, meaning
        <emphasis>Attribution Share Alike </emphasis>. You can visit
        <ulink url="http://creativecommons.org/about/licenses/"> <emphasis>the creative commons
        page</emphasis></ulink> to get more information.
      </para>

    </legalnotice>

    <copyright>
      <year>2010-2012</year>
      <holder>P.H. Andersson</holder>
    </copyright>

    <copyright>
      <year>2010-2011</year>
      <holder>Olivier Tribout</holder>
    </copyright>

    <copyright>
      <year>2012-2014</year>
      <holder>Ulrich Pegelow</holder>
    </copyright>

    <copyright>
      <year>2013-2014</year>
      <holder>Jérémy Rosen</holder>
    </copyright>

  </bookinfo>

  <preface id="overview">

    <title>Preface to this manual</title>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>darktable</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <indexterm>
      <primary>Preface</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>
      User manual version and applicable darktable version are listed below:
      <informaltable frame="none" width="80%">
        <tgroup cols="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
          <colspec colwidth='3cm'/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry>
                version
              </entry>
              <entry>
                date
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                user manual
              </entry>
              <entry>
                1.6.0
              </entry>
              <entry>
                November 2014
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                darktable
              </entry>
              <entry>
                1.6
              </entry>
              <entry>
                November 2014
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </para>

    <para>
      Translations of this manual to local languages are brought to you by Federico Bruni,
      Victor Lamoine, and Michel Leblond.
    </para>

    <para>
      Many thanks to all contributors to this user manual. Special thanks for proof reading,
      style improvement, constructive criticism, and valuable contributions go to Colin Adams,
      Mark Garrow, Simon Harhues, István Kovács, Michel Leblond, Rudolf Martin, Ammon Riley,
      Rob Z. Smith, Andrew Toskin, and David Vincent-Jones.
    </para>

  </preface>

<!-- Overview chapter -->

  <xi:include href="overview/overview.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>

<!-- Lighttable chapter -->

  <xi:include href="lighttable/lighttable.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>

<!-- Darkroom Chapter -->

  <xi:include href="darkroom/darkroom.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>

<!-- Tethering Chapter -->

  <xi:include href="tethering/tethering.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>

<!-- Geotagging  Chapter -->

  <xi:include href="map/map.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>

<!-- Slideshow  Chapter -->

  <xi:include href="slideshow/slideshow.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>

<!-- Preferences and Settings Chapter -->

  <xi:include href="preferences/preferences.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>

<!-- Scripting with Lua -->

  <xi:include href="lua/lua.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>

<!-- Special Topics Chapter -->

  <xi:include href="topics/topics.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>

<!-- The Index -->

  <index>
    <title>Index</title>
  </index>

</book>
